<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Brummbär Money Lender</chaptertitle>
    <section>        
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Dramatis Personae</subsectiontitle>        

	<descriptions>
	  <term>Brummbär Geldszwerg</term>
	  <description>
	    Dwarven money lender.   A portly looking dwarf,
	    with a large scar across his face, a number of
	    heavy necklaces with many large golden medallions
	    (actually gilded lead), a kaftan, and chaperon.
	    He has 13 children and his wife, at home, runs his life.
	    He talks about them quite a lot.
	  </description>

	  <term>Snorri Zwergsen</term>
	  <description>
	    Dwarven Bodyguard.  Overprotective.  Blond hair.  Snorri has been
	    with Brummbär for twenty years since they were in the army
	    together.
	  </description>

	  <term>Timo Yodelszwerg</term>
	  <description>
	    Dwarven Thug.. one eye.
	  </description>

	  <term>Alberich</term>
	  <description>
	    Dwarven Thug.. Somewhat portly.
	  </description>
	</descriptions>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Overview</subsectiontitle>        
	<p>
	  Initial meeting with Brummbär Geldszwerg.  The characters need to borrow
	  money for some reason.
	</p>	  	
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Intro</subsectiontitle>        
	<p>
	  Brummbär Geldszwerg is setup in the market in an
	  oiled cloth tent stall with three sides, open at the front.  There are a number of
	  folded chairs open.   There's a large wooden sign out the front, painted with the
	  following: "Brummbär Money Lender" in Merovingian, and then again underneath in smaller
	  lettering in Dwarven.  The sign has three golden balls (gilded) which indicates that
	  Brummbär is a a licensed member of the money lenders guild, and therefore subject to a certain
	  code of conduct, policed by the money lenders guild.  Snorri, Timo and Alberich stand outside.
	  Brummbär is sitting in a chair inside.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Snorri will be eyeing passers, if people read the sign, he'll offer money lending services..
	  "Good morning sirs.. I'm thinking that perhaps ye might be in need of our pecuniary services?".
	  If they're interested he'll gesture them in where Brummbär will question them for a bit.  If
	  they seem like they are a potential customer he'll offer them some ale.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Brummbär wants to lend them some money, that's how he makes his living.  He doesn't want to lend
	  too much though as that represents extra risk for him should the borrowers default. He also
	  doesn't want to lend the money to people who can't pay it back.  He will complement the characters,
	  try and connect with them some way, if only at a ``ah we both hate rainy days'' level.
	  He will be angling to find out three things: what do the characters have for collateral?,  how much
	  money do the characters want to borrow? and how much money do the characters earn?  He doesn't want
	  to spend too much time doing this because there is an opportunity cost here.  He wants to
	  spend minimal time filtering out the bad bets from his potential customers.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  If the characters do not seem like a good prospect to Brummbär.. he will explain delicately that
	  he is very sorry that he cannot lend the characters any money as he is in the business of money
	  lending 
	</p>

	<p>
	  Once Brummbär decides that he wants to do business with the characters he will offer them more ale.	  
	  At this stage, He's happy to talk at length as he's trying to get the characters onside.
	  If the characters ask questions, he will share any information he has.  He will freely
	  offer up other pieces of information about himself to make himself likeable to the characters,
	  for example he might offer that his medallions are gilded lead to impress the commoners, or
	  that he came from common upbringings.  He will claim that now that they are such good friends that
	  he can offer them a special deal.	  
	</p>

	<p>
	  The deal.. He'll offer them the money with a vig of 7% per month.  This is over the normal rate
	  by a few percent, but not drastically so.  He's a fairly straightforward fellow at heart.  He
	  believes deceit is bad for business.  Depending on how risky the loan will be he can be negotiated
	  down to 4%.	  
	</p>

	<p>
	  If the deals is for a lot of money 500gp or more then after the deal is done he will pack up his
	  necklaces in his safe box and be done for the day.   The money is not in the safe box.  It's just for
	  show.  He will arrange for it to be delivered later.  There's a one page contract that is drawn
	  up and the characters get a copy.   The loan will have a total number of days late before
	  Brummbär can rightfully claim the collateral by law.  He probably won't though..  He wants the
	  interest he doesn't want the collateral.  He also cares about his good name.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
