<encounter>
  <encounterid>the_will.fulcades_forgery</encounterid>  
  <name>Fulcade's Forgery</name>  
  <precis>Introduce the problem of Fulcade's forgery. How to prove the doc is a forgery?</precis>  
  <motivation>Stop the Fulcades</motivation>  
  <timers>Has to be done before the will is executed.</timers>
  <threats>Fulcades winning.</threats>
  <treats>Complete their mission.</treats>
  <progression>When Pilichin has enough he phases out.</progression>  
  <difficulty></difficulty>  
  <strategy></strategy>  
  <outs></outs>  
  <monster><id>human.peasant</id><name></name><count>13</count></monster>
  <details>

    <p>Location, private Room at Hyman Kreitman's Inn.</p>
    
    <p>
      Fulcade has spies in the inn.  Sibelle a well endowed young lass is on their payroll.
      She will swan about,  offering the players food and drink, and flirting, ostenisbly for tips.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Background: The Gelfrat family seal was dropped and broken a new one was commissioned two years ago.
      The will is dated from six years earlier and sealed with the new seal.  It must be forged.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      If Toby turns up he's delivering a message that a <emph>forger has claimed that he forged
      the Fulcade Will using a seal supplied to him by Fulcade</emph>.  This testimony will not stand
      up in court though.  Failing that we could have a messenger deliver the message.
      Alternatively, <emph>someone can take a look at the docs and recall that the seal doesn't
      look the same as the ones on the docs in Gelfrats study</emph>.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Also delivering a letter from Ottmar Fulcade, Magister of the Laibstadt Regierungsbezirk, Serjant
      at Law instructing Hyman Kreitman which informs him that information has come to him that
      <list>
      	<li>There are nefarious forces at work trying to unjustly effect the outcome of the process</li>
      	<li>However do not fear.  I have successfully petitioned the Emperor to have the execution of the
      	will expedited to no later than tomorrow.</li>
      </list>
    </p>

    <p>
      All this should lead the characters to Mrs Mandel's house, via the Gelfrat mansion. Failing that they
      could go to get the Seal Registery document from the Imperial Chancery Roll and Cartulary
    </p>
  </details>  
</encounter>
