<encounter>
  <encounterid>the_will.the_execution</encounterid>  
  <name>The Execution of the Will</name>  
  <precis>The climax</precis>  
  <motivation></motivation>  
  <timers>Peasants getting killed as collateral damage</timers>
  <threats>Fulcades winning.</threats>
  <treats>Complete their mission.</treats>
  <progression>.</progression>  
  <difficulty></difficulty>  
  <strategy></strategy>  
  <outs>The heavy cavalry will arrive from the fortifications that guard the bridge.  The Ghouls can open a gate to the City of Brass if things get desperate</outs>  
  <monster><id>ghoul.gatewalker</id><name>Osprant Kruger, Pankratz Schenk</name><count>2</count></monster>
  <monster><id>construct.bronze_scorpion</id><name>Bronze Scorpion</name><count>1</count></monster>
  <monster><id>ghoul.eater-of-the-dead</id><name>Clare Albrecht, Ute Sieger, Wolf Drechsler and Arnold Faerber</name><count>3</count></monster>
  <monster><id>human.thug</id><name>Thugs</name><count>6</count></monster>
  <monster><id>human.peasant</id><name>Hirelings</name><count>13</count></monster>
  <details>
    <p>
      Town square, this is big news and must be seen to be an open process
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Order of things..
      <list>
      	<li>Crowd gathers with the PCs and Hyman, and the claimants, and various members of the university (Berold Falkenrath Chancellor and Dr Johannes Walkenhorst, hoping for an endowment perhaps).  Melchior has a large group of thugs and ne'r-do-wells with him, twenty or so. Sibelle is standing with Melchior Fulcade.  Arnold Faerber and his three friends will be standing with Osprant Kruger.</li>
      	<li>Hyman will explain what the meeting is all about.  Execution of the will.</li>
      	<li>Hyman will explain the claims being made.</li>
      	<li>Hyman will explain the claims will be addressed as dictated by the will presented and failing that by any peritinent principles of primogeniture.</li>
      	<li>Fulcades claim will be addressed first.  If the Fulcade forgery has not been found then Hyman will say that the Fulcades have been inherited the estate.
      	Otherwise, Hyman explains that the Fulcades claim will not be honoured as the will is deemed to be inauthentic and that no documents attesting to any relationship between
      	the Fulcades and the Gelfratzs have been found.  The Fulcade group will act shocked/outraged by this.</li>
      	<li>If the Fulcade forgery <emph>has</emph> been found then Osprant Kruger will look very smug and ask Hyman to clarify before we proceed any further that the inheritance includes all
      	artifacts and tomes currently in the house and on loan to the library are part of the estate..  Hyman will attest to this.</li>
      	<li>Hyman will state that next we will address the claims by Osprant Kruger.  The will presented names Osprant the bastard son of Gelfrats and leaves the inheritance to Osprant.</li>
      	<li>However, Hyman explains that there is a verified will.  It is ten years old and leaves all goods and chatels to Gelfrats wife lady Herlinde Grezinger.  Who has sadly passed eight years prior.
      	The will presented by Master Kruger is dated twelve years prior and so since none of the wills presented are acceptable we conclude that Burgrave Gelfrat Greniczer has died intestate.
      	Execution of the will will therefore proceed based on primogeniture.
      	</li>
      	<li>Since no relationship between Lord Fulcade and Burgrave Greniczer can be found the two remaining claimaints are Abbott Dietmar Löwe and Master Osprant Kruger.  Since it is well-documented that
      	Abbott Lowe is the second cousin, while Master Kruger only claims to be the bastard son I must award the inheritance to Abbott Lowe on the basis of primigeniture.
      	</li>
      	<li>At this point both Melchior and Osprant will pipe up about the mendicancy laws.  Hyman will address it.  The mendicancy laws can be bypassed in this case if Abbott Lowe signs a waiver assigning
      	any corporal goods to the church before he accepts the will.  Such a document I have prepared here.
      	</li>
      	<li>
      	  If the Fulcades do not get the estate then after a minute Melchior will yell "Watch out, they're attacking us!".
      	  This is the signal for Melchiors henchmen to attack and kill the other two claimants.
      	</li>
      </list>
    </p>

    <p>
      At this point there will be a fight.  On one side we have Melchior Fulcade and his twenty thugs.  They will start pushing and cutting their way through the crowd to get to the Abbott and Kruger.
      Abbott Dietmar has a handful of Confessor Militants with him.  He will back off into an alley.
      On the third side we have Osprant Kruger, Pankratz Schenk, Clare Albrecht, Ute Sieger, Wolf Drechsler and Arnold Faerber  (they'll all turn into ghouls. Arnold Faerber will be surprised as hell).  They'll
      want to attack Abbott Dietmar as well, but get caught up fighting Fulcades goons.  The Ghouls have a Bronze Scorpion.  A large extra planar construct that they will deploy after two of them go down.
    </p>
  </details>  
</encounter>
