<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Abjuration</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>abjuration</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><magical/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        Abjuration involves the	use of raw magical energies and focuses on casting
	protective, shielding and counter magics.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Abjuration</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>abjuration</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><abjuration/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="9">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p noindent="true">
	This ability represents the knowledge of the theoretical foundations
	of abjuration.  Expertise in this ability is a prerequisite for casting spells
	in this group.  Players can check against this ability to answer questions
	about this field of study and its history. 
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Banish</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>abjuration.banish</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><abjuration/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="2"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="5">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Willpower">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>abjuration_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="120" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	Banishing is an attempt to disrupt a demons tenuous contagious
	connection with its simulacrum.  If the banishment succeeds the demon must make
	a DC 7 Mettle check or its simulacrum is destroyed.  In the event of an overcharge make
	Demon must make a second DC 3 Morale Check and make a DC 15 Willpower Check on, a fail
	the caster takes 2d4 damage, on a bane make an additional roll on the Magic Overcharge
	Effects table, on a boon the character may refresh a magic dice into their pool, snatched
	from the energy the demon is using to control their simulacrum.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Circle of Protection</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>abjuration.circle_of_protection</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><full-turn/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><abjuration/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="2"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="7">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>abjuration_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-75" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	A circle of protection is a circle drawn upon the ground and infused
  	with magical energy that breaks thaumaturgic contagion.  As such it
  	is hard for summoned creatures to cross, either in or out.  It takes
	about three turns to create a circle of protection.  A circle of protection
	cannot be created while the caster is being attacked in melee.
      </p>

      <p>
  	If successful Creates a DC 25+5xRank protective barrier against extra planar
	creatures.  To pass through the barrier the extra-planar character must roll above
	the DC using their Magic pool.  Creatures striking the protective barrier will
	lose D4 hit points for each attempt.
      </p>
      
      <p>
  	The circle can be marked using chalk, salt, enscribed in the floor
  	or a multitude of other ways.
      </p>
      <p>
	It is possible to create an Inverted Circle of Protection which is usually called
	a Circle of Containment.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Contego</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.contego</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction-or-minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><abjuration/><ranged/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="5">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>    
    <prereqabilityrank>abjuration.circle_of_protection_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="30" y="30"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <p noindent="true">
	The caster creates a magical shield around a person, or anything tagged medium or small.
	The barrier from outside appears as a blurred humanoid shape.  Kinetic
	weapons do half damage to the character thus shielded.  It also provides
	brief protection from fires, poisonous gases <etc/>.  The shield is ablative
	and is represented in game by 8+3xRank temporary Staamina.  
	It lasts five minutes/30 rounds.
      </p>

      <p>
	If overcharged the shield may explode upon being hit, make a Std Check vs DDC 9 every
	time the shield is hit or explode.   Explosions do 2d4 damage to all adjacent creatures
	including the character being shielded.  Adjacent creatures may save, Speed or Dodge vs DDC 12,
	to take half damage.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
  </ability>



  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Commune</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.commune</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><abjuration/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="2"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="7">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>abjuration_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="60" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	Commune is a spell that communicates with a named entity from beyond.
  	The character must know the name of the entity to contact.  On overcharge
  	the character must make an opposed will check against the demon or become
  	enthralled by the demon.  Enthralled characters will seek to summon the
  	demons simulacrum to this plane to further their nefarious plans.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Summoned demons are not compelled to cooperate with the character, nor tell
  	the truth.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Eldritch Shield</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.eldritch_shield</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><abjuration/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="2"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="3">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>abjuration_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="60" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The caster uses raw magical energy to knock arrows and crossbow bolts out
  	of the air.  The caster must be aware of the attack, <ie/> not
  	ambushed or surprised.  The size of the missile that can be
  	diverted depends on the rank of the casters ability.  The missile
  	does not have to be aimed at the caster in order for the caster
  	to cast this spell.  This spell is cast as a reaction after
  	the target is hit, the caster can tell that the missile would hit
  	and acts accordingly before it does.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Flesh Ward</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.flesh_ward</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction-or-minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><abjuration/><touch/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="5">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>abjuration_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The Flesh Ward spell provides magical protection
  	for the caster against physical attacks, their skin
  	knits itself up if they take damage.  A Flesh Ward
  	lasts the duration of combat and a character can only
	have one Flesh Ward active at a time.
      </p>

      <p>
  	In game the effect of flesh ward is represented
  	in the form of a limited regeneration.  If the cast
  	succeeds, for the duration of the combat the character heals
	1d4 hit-points every time they are hit, note that this does not
	mean every turn.  If the cast overcharges the spell then the
	caster suffers damage equal to the difference between the DC and
	their roll.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
</abilitygroup>



  

