<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Conjuration</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>conjuration</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><magical/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
	Conjuration is the most versatile, powerful and therefore hardest to control and
	most dangerous of all magical schools.   It involves harnessing raw magic and 
	Conjuration involves the unsophisticated use of raw magic powers.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Conjuration Lore</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>conjuration</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><conjuration/><lore/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents the characters knowledge of conjuration
	magic and its theory.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <spline></spline>
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>
  
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Eldritch Push</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.eldritch_push</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><conjuration/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The caster shoots a raw stream of thaumic energy from
	their hands at a target.  If successful the caster makes
	a second Std Check +6+Level bonus attack against the targets Dodge, Agility, or Strength Defence.
      </p>

      <p>
	If they hit the target, the target suffers 8 damage
	and is pushed  <measurement><imperial>30'</imperial><metric>10m</metric></measurement>
	away from the caster.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="90" y="30"/></spline>
    <prereqabilitylevel>conjuration_2</prereqabilitylevel>
    <abilitycheck dc="2" overcharge="5+Level"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg>4 +Level</abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Eldritch Grasp</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.eldritch_grasp</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><conjuration/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The caster uses a raw stream of thaumic energy to grab a target
	crushing it and pulling it towards him.  If successful the caster makes
	a second attack against the targets Dodge, Agility, or Strength Defence Check,
	with a +6+Level bonus.
      </p>

      <p>
	If they hit the target, the target suffers damage
	and is either pushed or pulled  <measurement><imperial>30'</imperial><metric>10m</metric></measurement>
	in any direction.  
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <prereqabilitylevel>magic.eldritch_push_2</prereqabilitylevel>
    <abilitycheck dc="2" overcharge="5+Level"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg>8 +Level</abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Scry</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.scry</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><conjuration/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
    	The character can view events from the past.  Viewing events in
    	the future is incredibly difficult and unreliable (See Scry, Greater).
      </p>

      <p>
    	The caster first names a target, holding items with contagious links to the target,
    	then checks to see whether the spell succeeds. If it does, they see an important
    	scene from targets life (the GM narrates the scene to the player). The caster may
    	then choose to look far forward, forward, back or far back in time.  Each time
    	the player attempts to view another scene from the targets life they
    	make another check with their remaining magic pool against a DC 9.
    	The caster may continue to view scenes from the targets life until they
    	fail or choose to stop scrying.
      </p>

      <p>
    	Contagion is very important to this spell.  A good contagious link, the
    	targets blood, or hair for example, can	reduce the difficulty of this
    	spell by five or more.  Subsequent contagious items have reduced effectiveness.
    	For example the GM might rule that if the caster has the blood and hair of the target
    	an item of their clothes and their diary the DC is reduced by from fifteen by ten down
    	to five.  These contagious links diminish rapidly and so will be of little advantage
    	after a day or two.  Most intelligent adversaries will take care not to allow contagious
    	items to be obtained by their opponents.
    	If the caster fails any checks while scrying their contagious link is destroyed.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="60"/></spline>
    <prereqabilitylevel>conjuration_2</prereqabilitylevel>
    <abilitycheck dc="9 initial, 5 subsequent" overcharge="14+Level initial, 10+Level subsequent"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Scry, Greater</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.scry_greater</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><conjuration/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character can view events from a targets present and their future as well
	as their past. 	This spell works like the lesser Scry but because the future
	is not predetermined the results are often very unreliable and inaccurate.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <prereqabilitylevel>magic.scry_2</prereqabilitylevel>	
    <abilitycheck dc="7 initial, 5 subsequent" overcharge="9+Level initial, 10+Level subsequent" />
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="2"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Wither</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.wither</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><conjuration/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The caster grabs an opponent.
	On success the caster acts as a conduit to one of the dread
	planes,	life is drained from the target.  Anything that
	increases contagion will increase damage for this spell.
	The target is momentarily transfixed (checks Will vs the casters
	successful magic roll +13 or loses their turn).	
      </p>

      <p>
	If the check is successful the target suffers 2d8 damage.
	On overcharge the caster suffers 1d8 damage.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="-90" y="30"/></spline>
    <prereqabilitylevel>conjuration_2</prereqabilitylevel>
    <abilitycheck dc="4"
    overcharge="9 +Level" />
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>    
</abilitygroup>
