<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>


  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Evocation</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>evocation</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><magical/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>

      <p noindent="true">
	Demons inhabit the cold lower planes.  There is much recorded
	of their nature and their history in old and long forgotten tomes.
	Evocation represents the study of that lore.  
	Such books are not easily come by, nor should they be read lightly.
	<indexentry>Demonic Lore<subentry>See Evocation</subentry></indexentry>
      </p>

      <p>
	Evocation magic specializes in summoning or communicating with extra planar
	entities, binding extra planar entities, opening gates and the like.
      </p>

      <p>
        Magic abilities involve the use of the characters magic pool and
	are only available to certain archetypes.
      </p>      
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>



  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Bind</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.bind</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype> 
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="5"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Bind holds an opponent using magical energies.  
	If successful The target makes a will check DC 6 in the first round and are held 
	until they succeed.   The difficulty decreases by two every round the target
	is held.  The caster may release the target at any time.  
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="15" y="30"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Evocation Lore</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/><lore/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents the characters knowledge of the theory and
	history of evocation magick.  Players can make this check to
	see if their characters have pertinent information about the situation
	in which they find themselves.  For this ability, exhausted dice are
	not removed from the pool but exhausted dice and overcharge increases
	the unreliablility of the information that the GM provides to the players.
	If the check fails the character has no useful additional information.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline></spline>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Greater Portal</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.greater_portal</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="26"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This is a very rapid invocation of the normal portal spell.
	The spell is cast in one action.  The character can open a portal
	between two well known places in this plane.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="0" y="15"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation.portal_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Lesser Portal</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.lesser_portal</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><ritual/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="20"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The user creates a portal in a wall or floor.   The portal remains
	open for 2d4 minutes or until the caster wills the gate shut.  Casting
	portal requires marking a magical circle in the ground or against a wall
	which takes minutes to prepare.
	The portal opens a path within the current plane, to a point up to
	<measurement><metric>three meters</metric>
	<imperial>ten feet</imperial></measurement> per rank of the spell.
	Note that this is a non-combat spell though it only takes a minute or
	two to cast.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Phantasmal Leech</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.phantasmal_leech</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p noindent="true">
	<emph>Like one who, on a lonely road, Doth walk in fear	and dread,
	And, having once turned round, walks on, And turns no more his head;
	Because he knows a frightful fiend Doth close behind him tread.</emph>
      </p>
      
      <p>
	Given an object with a contagious connection to a target, the caster
	summons a Phantasmal Leech to track the target.  A Phantasmal Leech is
	a cat sized, snake-like demon with membraneous wings and a cyclostomatic head
	with five lidless black eyes.  It is translucent, and insubstantial.  The starving
	Leech craves the blood of the target and the caster sees through its eyes as it
	tracks the target.   The leeches projection onto this plane is volatile and it
	is easily destroyed by magic.  If not dismissed	it will involuntarily return
	to its home plane after ten minutes. Furthermore the leech cannot interact with
	objects in this plane and may pass through walls, doors <etc/>   The leech cannot
	attack.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	If successfully cast the target gets a perception check with DC 14+rank to notice the presence
	of the leech following.  if the target has magical attacks these will almost
	certainly work against the leech, sending it back from whence it came.  If the
	target has no magical attacks it cannot harm the creature.  
      </p>

      <table>
	<tablecategory>Standard</tablecategory>
	<tablespec><fixed>0.3</fixed><fixed>0.6</fixed></tablespec>
	<tabletitle>Phantasmal Leech Overcharge Table</tabletitle>

	<tableheaderrow>
	  <td>Roll d88</td>
	  <td>Overcharge Effect</td>
	</tableheaderrow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>11-28</td>
	  <td>The caster summons a Phantasmal Vulture instead (as per the spell of the
	  same name).</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>31-38</td>
	  <td>Something from beyond takes a small bite out of the caster.  Caster suffers
	  d6 health damage.</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>41-48</td>
	  <td>Something from beyond takes a big bite out of the caster.  Caster suffers
	  3d6 health damage.</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>51-88</td>
	  <td>Weirdness ensues.. Reroll on the Overcharge Effects Table..</td>
	</tablerow>
	<tablelabel>fig:leech-overcharge</tablelabel>
      </table>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="90" y="30"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Phantasmal Vulture</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.phantasmal_vulture</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p noindent="true">
	Given an object with a contagious connection to a target, the caster
	summons a Phantasmal Vulture to track the target.  A Phantasmal Vulture is
	a dog sized, vulture-like demon with membraneous wings, a tentacled face and
	stinging tail. 	Like a Phantasmal Leech it is translucent, susceptible to magical
	attacks and has the same difficulty of detection.  Unlike the Leech the Vulture
	can summon its magical reserves to phase into this plane momentarilly to attack.
	It may attack once before being dispelled to its home plane and will automatically
	do so when it finds its prey (it is not up to the caster).
      </p>

      <p>
	The vulture makes a single Std + 2 attack vs AC for 1d8 damage (if
	the target has not perceived the vulture, Perception Check 12+Level, it is considered
	to be Blind to the attack, -4 to AC).
      </p>
      <table>
	<tablecategory>Standard</tablecategory>
	<tablespec><fixed>0.3</fixed><fixed>0.6</fixed></tablespec>
	<tabletitle>Phantasmal Vulture Overcharge Table</tabletitle>

	<tableheaderrow>
	  <td>Roll d49</td>
	  <td>Overcharge Effect</td>
	</tableheaderrow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>10-19</td>
	  <td>Something from beyond takes a small bite out of the caster.  Caster suffers
	  d6 health damage.</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>20-29</td>
	  <td>Something from beyond takes a big bite out of the caster.  Caster suffers
	  3d6 health damage.</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>30-49</td>
	  <td>Weirdness ensues.. Reroll on the Overcharge Effects Table..</td>
	</tablerow>
	<tablelabel>fig:vulture-overcharge</tablelabel>
      </table>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="0" y="15"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation.phantasmal_leech_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Portal</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.portal</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="26"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This is a very rapid invocation of the lesser portal spell.
	The spell is cast in one action.  The character can open a portal
	in a wall or floor.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="0" y="15"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation.lesser_portal_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Shade</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.shade</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="16"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	A shade is one of the lesser demons.  It can be summoned to attack
	a living creature.  If there are no living opponents left it will turn on
	its attacker.   Shades are insubstantial and visible only as a lack of light.
	Shades take double damage from fire and magical based attacks.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="-30" y="15"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation.lesser_portal_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Summon</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.summon</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype> 
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="6"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character makes a check to open a minute portal into one of the near planes.
	This allows some creature on the other side to project a simulacrum
	of themselves into this plane.  If successful a single demon manifests in
	this plane. It is highly likely that the entity will be ravenous and seek to
	devour the animus of the caster or others nearby.  For this reason the caster
	usually also casts a Circle of Containment immediately before summoning the demon.
	For the caster to create and control the portal they must use a specially prepared
	fetish that is placed inside the circle before the summoning.  The fetish provides
	a channel to the Summon spell via an external plane, thereby circumventing the
	Circle of Containment.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	If the caster does not commune with an entity before the summoning they may
	summon any extra planar creature.  This can be incredibly dangerous.  In addition
	demons may lie about their names and their capabailites.  So the only, even
	moderately safe way of summoning demons is to: commune with a demon of a known
	name, then to summon them into a circle of protection.  Note that demons are
	deceitful creatures and will jump at the chance to try to trick a summoner into
	calling them into the world and once here they will try to establish a foothold
	and not leave.   They will try to break the circle of protection or bargain
	for information about the caster which will allow them to break the circle via
	contagion.
      </p>

      <p>
	Closing the portal cuts the simulacrums link to the demon.  Powerful demons
	may be able to keep the portal open themselves, once they have created a
	simulacrum.  Note that the demons simulacrum need not look like the demon
	who created it and often times it does not as the demon will wish to disguise
	their identity.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-75" y="30"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Wyld Portal</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>evocation.wyld_portal</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><evocation/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability enables the user to recognize gateways,
	areas with an affinity with the Wyld.  At
	these places the caster may cast a portal which opens to
	the Wyld.
      </p>

      <p>	
      	It is not known how many such gateways exist. Given
	the near suicidal nature of travelling in the Wyld
	the knowledge of their locations is quickly forgotten.
      </p>

      <p>	
	Finally, it should be added that the Wyld is a
	many-varied place.  Gateways can be found in swamps,
	deserts and sewers, as well as forested groves.
	Often the presence of a gateway is indicated by an incongrousness
	in the environment as the gateway forms a contagious link
	between the two planes at its locus.  The nature of the
	Wyld bleeds into this plane at the gateway which can
	indicate the nature of the Wyld beyond.
      </p>	
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="0" y="15"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>evocation.greater_portal_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>
</abilitygroup>
