<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Lore Abilities</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>lore</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><lore/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        Represents book learning on a wide variety of fields through academic study.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Alchemy</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.alchemy</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.alchemy_lesser_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="60" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character may call themselves an Apothecary, and can prepare poisons,
	Laudanum, War-Fire, Foaming Plaster, Colloidal Silver, and medicines for
	certain diseases. The character must have alchemical equipment and the requisite
	ingredients to do this.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Alchemy, Lesser</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.alchemy_lesser</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.natural_history_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Alchemy is concerned with the creation of chemical substances,
	the creation of cures for various diseases, the creation of solvents (acids),
	liquid fire, dies, gunpowder, etc. If the character has the necessary ingredients
	they can check to manufacture acids, dyes, blackpowder, inks, petards, grenades,
	poultices etc. They can identify many chemical substances.  In need they may be
	able to substitute some substances during creation to make solutions of lesser
	strength.  Possesion of relevant equipment such as a Mortar and Pestle should
	provide	a bonus to the Check, at the GM's discretion.
      </p>

      <p>
	The ingredient used to manufacture these items may be expensive.  Furthermore they
	may have a limited shelf life as moisture in the air and internal alchmical reactions	
	can reduce the efficacy of these items over time.  For these reasons alchemical
	creations are often created before embarking on an endeavour and any unused items are
	discarded afterwards.
      </p>

      <p>
	In addition the character can make lore checks regarding the chemical composition
	of solutions, metals etc and might be able to conjecture on their origins and
	purposes.
      </p>
      	
      <p>
	Two, as yet, unattained goals of alchemy are the transmutation of lead into gold,
	and the creation of an elixir of immortality.  
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Alchemy, Greater</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.alchemy_greater</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.alchemy_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character can prepare Alkahest (requires Bile of the White Worm),
	a Potion of Living Death (requires serpents venom), Tears of Lethe
	(requires Laudanum), Limaceous Grease (requires the ichor of a demon),
	Smoked snigglets (requires fresh swamp snigglets), Ignis Sacer (requires
	rye bread and a few weeks of time), or Spirits of Quickening.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Artillery</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.artillery</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Defence" effect="Attack using artillery pieces.">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.alchemy_lesser_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character is trained in the use of artillery in sieges or naval warfare.
	The can arm, aim, fire and on some occasions repair artillery pieces.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Antiquarian</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.antiquarian</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>common.history_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="15"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character has studied the history of antique objects, furniture,
	vases, coins, maps, swords, etc. They can check to evaluate the worth
	and provenance of these objects.  At higher ranks they can, with
	difficulty, discern the nature of certain well-known eldritch objects.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Barber</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.barber</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="450"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character has an understanding of minor surgery:
	setting bones, trepanning, dentistry, cataract couchery,
	pig-gelding, and cutting hair.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Book Keeping</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.book_keeping</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.mathematics_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-40" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Book keeping encompasses accounting and financial abilities. 
        Book keeping is used by merchants, clerks, and castellans, to manage 
	finances.  With this ability an character can examine the books of a business to 
	get an idea of how the business operates, whether it is doing well or badly,
	how much debt is owed if any, where the money is coming from and going to,
	and so on.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Book Learning</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.book_learning</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="15">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline></spline>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character has had access to and has read some books.  They have 
	a broader understanding of the world than their less educated peers.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Explosives</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.explosives</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>    
    <abilityranks untrained="-6" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.smoke_bomb_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character knows how create explosives.  They keep on their person some explosive material at all
	times which may be used to create an ersatz grenade or petard.  A grenade is an anti personal explosive
	thrown at a target which does an area of effect damage.  A petard is a breaching charge used to blow
	a hole in a door or thin wall.  When required the character makes a check.  If unsuccesful the bomb is
	a dud and fails to ignite.  If successful the bomb they are carrying lights successfully and performs
	as the equipment item of the same name.  Note that these explosives are a little unstable, and a little
	unweildy.  The character only carries enough ingredients to create one of these items, after which they
	must create more in their lab.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>  
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Grand Discovery</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.grand_discovery</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="None">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.alchemy_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="70" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The alchemist makes a Grand Discovery!! (maybe).
	Every time the character gains a rank in this ability roll 2d12 on the
	Grand Discovery table.  If the character makes several Grand Discoveries and
	receives a duplicate result then they reroll, except for the Disappointment,
	Transmutation and Surprise Discovery results.  Mastery for this ability is one,
	so the character only needs to make this check once before being able to gain
	the next rank of this ability.  Only one check is allowed per rank.   It takes
	the character 3d4 days to perform the applied experimentation for this check,
	for which they require a suitably equipped laboratory.  This experimentation
	must be done prior to making the check.
      </p>

      <table>
	<tablecategory>Standard</tablecategory>
	<tablespec><fixed>0.09</fixed><fixed>0.8</fixed></tablespec>
	<tabletitle>Grand Discoveries Table</tabletitle>
	<tablelabel>fig:grand-discoveries</tablelabel>

	<tableheaderrow>
	  <td>Std</td>
	  <td>Result</td>
	</tableheaderrow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>2-4</td>
	  <td>Possession.  The character becomes possessed!</td>
	</tablerow>
	
	<tablerow>
	  <td>5</td>
	  <td>Untamed Brute.  The characters brutish nature comes to the fore at times
	  of stress.  Gain the “Untamed Brute” Aspect.</td>
	</tablerow>
	
	<tablerow>
	  <td>6-16</td>
	  <td>Disapointment!  No discovery made</td>
	</tablerow>
	
	<tablerow>
	  <td>17</td>
	  <td>Unexpected Discovery.  Gain a rank in alchemy.</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>18</td>
	  <td>Poison Resistance, +5 to saves vs being poisoned.</td>
	</tablerow>	
		
	<tablerow>
	  <td>19</td>
	  <td>Arcane Knowledge.  Gain 1x promotions in magic and 2x promotions in
	  fine arts, lore or special abilities (promotions cannot be used to gain more
	  Grand Discoveries)</td>
	</tablerow>
	
	<tablerow>
	  <td>20</td>
	  <td>Transmutation.  After years of practice you finally are able to transmute
	  lead into gold.  Unfortunately you can't work out how to repeat the process.
	  Fortunatly you transmute a lot of lead the first time.</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>21</td>
	  <td>Enhanced Ability: Roll d6 on a 1: Gain Speed +2, 2: Gain
	  Str +2, 3: Gain Agility +2, 4: Gain Perception +2, 5: Gain Endurance +2,
	  6: Choose. This change is permanent</td>
	</tablerow>		
	
	<tablerow>
	  <td>22</td>
	  <td>Elixir of Life.  The alchemist has somehow ceased their own aging.</td>
	</tablerow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>23</td>
	  <td>Forbidden Knowledge.  Gain 3x promotions in magic and 3x promotions in
	  fine arts, lore or special abilities (promotions cannot be used to gain more
	  Grand Discoveries).  Gain a Patreon.</td>
	</tablerow>
		
	<tablerow>
	  <td>24+</td>
	  <td>Surprise Discovery.  Choose a Grand Discovery - no duplicates allowed.</td>
	</tablerow>
      </table>      
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>History</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>common.history</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><common/><lore/><general/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.book_learning_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="45"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	History is the study of the events of the civilized peoples.
	Its study is both interesting and useful.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Law</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.law</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-6" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.book_learning_2</prereqabilityrank>    
    <spline><p x="75" y="15"/></spline>
    <specializations>
      <specialization>Laibstadt</specialization>
      <specialization>Hibernia</specialization>
    </specializations>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	An understanding of the law grants the character insight into the way society
	works.  The practice of law invariably leads to the heart of industry and
	the seats of power.  Characters may be able to discern the motive behind
	political machinations and they may be able to cite a legal precedent in
	order to compel or cease certain courses of events in a civilized society.	
      </p>

      <p>
	Law is the study of the laws of a particular society.  The study of the
	laws of one society is not necessarilly applicable to another.  When choosing
	the law ability the player must specify which legal system they are studying.
      </p>

      <p>
	At first rank this represents having a good, but not professional,
	understanding of the law of some land.  Usually, the characters homeland.
	At higher ranks this ability represents a professional rank of understanding
	of the law, and some understanding of the laws in surrounding regions.  
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Mathematics</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.mathematics</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.book_learning_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="100"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Maths is the lingua franca of science.  A basic understanding
	of maths is a prerequisite for many other abilities.  It can be
	applied in a very large and diverse range of circumstances.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Natural History</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.natural_history</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.book_learning_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="70"/><p x="50" y="30"/><p x="0" y="90"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The study of nature. The character has some knowledge of the flora
	and fauna.  They may identify many plants and
	may know about useful herbal remedies for certain diseases or for use
	in the the making of poultices.  They have some understanding
	of zoology and anatomy.  They may be able to identify interesting
	information about natural beasts.
      </p>

      <p>
	Natural History is related to Survivalism.  The former is more
	technical, based on oral or written sources, the latter is more practical
	and applicable in the wild.	
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Occult</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>common.occult</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><common/><lore/><general/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-6" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.book_learning_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/><p x="75" y="20"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The study of religions, their belief systems, rituals and history.
	At rank 1 the character has some knowledge of religious philosophies,
	legends and lore.  At higher ranks the they can
	identify most religious symbols and quote from their texts.  In order to
	cast clerical spells the character also needs Theurgic Lore which deals
	which deals with the mechanics of theological spell casting.
      </p>
      <p>
	At rank 4 the character has a deep knowledge of numerous religions both
	living and dead.  The characters depth of knowledge is deep enough that
	they may pass as a follower of many faiths when questioned.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	At fifth rank the character can enter a trance that releases stress, appears
	as if the character is dead, can reduce the characters oxygen consumption,
	and reduce the effect of poisonous miasmas.
      </p>	
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Physician</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.physician</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.natural_history_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="75" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character is a specialist medical diagnostician.  They
	are responsible for diagnosing what is wrong with people
	and balancing their humours.  Their treatments include
	modifying the diets of their patients, proscribing, but
	not creating, ointments, tinctures and potions, 
	and the medicinal application of leeches.	
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Physics</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.physics</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.mathematics_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="30" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Physics involves the study of the natural laws of the universe, movement and
	energy, celestial mechanics, astronomy and meterology.  Its practioners usually make
	a clear	deliniation between the study of physics and the study of the wyrd, unworldly
	and unnatural laws (possibly to protect themselves from pogroms and witch hunts).
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Politics [Society?]</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.politics</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.book_learning_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="50"/><p x="120" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents the study of the machinations that occur in the
	upper ranks of power in society, its application, its history and its heraldry.
	This includes political theory: Real Politics and Machiavellian dealings
	and important historical treaties and maneveurings.
      </p>

      <p>
	At first rank the character has knowledge of the history and current affairs
	of some local regions nobility and royalty.  They know the heraldic insignias
	of these nobles and important state organizations.  They understand
	the laws of succession in that region.  They know most of the
	commonly known court intrigue and have a decent understanding of the machinations and
	manoevering of the ruling classes.
      </p>

      <p>
	At each rank above the first the character gains this understanding for
	a new Society.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>    
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Potion Making</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.potions</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.alchemy_1</prereqabilityrank>	
    <spline><p x="-40" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p noindent="true">
	The character knows how to make magical potions given
	a lab, time and the right ingredients.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Smoke Bomb</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>lore.smoke_bomb</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><lore/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="11" effect="Defensive checks against missile attacks made at +3×Rank">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.alchemy_lesser_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character has on his person a smoke bomb that he had created earlier.  When required the
	character makes a check.  If unsuccesful the bomb is a dud and fails to ignite. In the event of failure
	further attempts at lighting the bomb may be made.
	If successful the smoke bomb they are carrying lights successfully creates a billowing cloud
	of grey smoke surrounding the bomb with a radius of
	<measurement><imperial>20'</imperial><metric>6m</metric></measurement>
	on the first turn <measurement><imperial>30'</imperial><metric>9m</metric></measurement> on the
	second turn and <measurement><imperial>40'</imperial><metric>12m</metric></measurement> on the third
	turn.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	This cloud gives +3×Rank to defensive rolls against missile attacks.  It is clearly visible during
	the day, but may not be noticeable at night depending on the lighting.    The cloud also provides
	+Rank against area-of-effect attacks.   Note that after successfully lighting the bomb, the character
	must take a long rest before they can build another bomb which allows them to make this check again.
	Smoke bombs take time to prepare and are do not age well, so the character cannot produce a never ending
	stream of smoke bombs.  Furthermore smoke bombs require a small amount of specialised equipment and the
	character must have access to this equipemnt to create smoke bombs.  The smoke bomb may be thrown as if
	it were a rock.  If the character uses a thurible this grants a +1 to the check and also allows the
	smoke bomb to be thown as if it were a sling (if not retrieved the thurible will then be lost).
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Thaumaturgy</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>common.thaumaturgy</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><common/><lore/><general/><scholar/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-6" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>lore.book_learning_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/><p x="75" y="20"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Thaumaturgy is the academic and theoretical study of magic, mythos
	and the occult.  This ability does not extend to casting spells though
	it is a prerequisite to do so.
      </p>	
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>  
</abilitygroup>
