<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>
  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Martial Proficiency</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid><martial/></abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><martial/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
	Generic martial abilities.
      </p>      
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Adversary</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>adversary</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <name>Check</name>
      <trigger>Boon on a Successful attack with a basic attack against an opponent of the given type.</trigger>
      <actiontype><free/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <indifferent></indifferent>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><self/></range>
      <keywords></keywords>
      <dc>11</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="70" y="90"/></spline>
    <specializations>
      <specialization>Green-Skins</specialization>
      <specialization>Froche</specialization>
      <specialization>Fey</specialization>
      <specialization>Giants</specialization>
      <specialization>Humanoids</specialization>
      <specialization>Demons</specialization>
      <specialization>Animals</specialization>
      <specialization>Undead</specialization>
    </specializations>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character bears an animosity towards, and/or have been trained
	to fight opponents of a given monster-class.
      </p>

      <p>
	This ability is triggered after a character with this ability
	makes their first successful blessed melee attack against a creature
	having a monster-class that this character is adversarial to.
	Once triggered the characters  training/experience kicks in and 
	the ability remains active for the rest of the combat.
      </p>

      <p>
	While triggered the character gains a bonus equal to
	their adversary rank for combat checks against monsters of the given
	monster-class (the bonus is to the check only and not to damage).
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Armour</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>armour</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <name>Defend</name>
      <actiontype><free/></actiontype>
      <!-- <critsuccess></critsuccess> -->
      <!-- <critfail></critfail> -->
      <!-- <boon></boon> -->
      <!-- <indifferent></indifferent> -->
      <!-- <bane></bane> -->
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><defend/><save/></keywords>
      <dc>Opponent's Attack DC</dc>      
    </abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="90" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character takes the brunt of the attack on their armour, hoping that it
  	will protect them.  The bonus for this check is determined by the armour the
  	character is wearing. A character may be harder to hit because they are wearing
  	armour or carrying a shield.
      </p>

      <p>
	<label>ability:armour</label>
        <indexentry>Armour Check</indexentry>	
	After the character gets attacked they make an <defn>armour check</defn> to see if that attack
	was successfully defeated by the characters armour. If successful the character takes no damage
	from the attack.  This can be interpreted as either the armour taking the force of the blow
	and protecting the character, or the character moving in such a way that the
	the character is struck a glancing blow leaving them uninjured.
      </p>

      <p>	
	Instead of making an armour check the character may
	choose to dodge, shield block, parry or use some
	other attack-reaction ability.   Armour is not a reaction and does not use the characters
	reaction for the current turn unlike many other defence check abilities.  
      </p>

      <p>
	To make an Armour Check the modifier is calculated as follows.  First calculate the bonus
	for the type of armour worn by the character, <eg/>Plate provides +1, No armour provides -3.
	If the character is wielding a shield they get a shield bonus of +1.
	The Armour Ability Modifier is then the Armour Bonus plus the Shield bonus plus Rank of their
	Armour ability.
      </p>

      <p>
	If the armour result fails and a boon is rolled the attack deals half damage.  If
	the armour result fails and a bane is rolled the attack deals double damage.
	If the armour check succeeds the attack does no damage.  If it fails the attack does
	normal damage.
      </p>

      <p>
	Some attacks cannot be defended with armour, <eg/> a dragons breath weapon.  If no other
	attack-reaction ability is used the attack automatically does normal damage.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Artillery</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>artillery</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <name>Check</name>
      <actiontype><standard/></actiontype>

      <!-- Mastery -->
      <critsuccess>Deal 3×Damage</critsuccess>
      <righteoussuccess>Deal 2×Damage</righteoussuccess>
      <success>Deal Damage</success>
      <fail>No Effect</fail>
      <grimfail></grimfail>
      <critfail>Roll on the ranged consequence table</critfail>

      <!-- Fate -->
      <blessed>+6 Damage</blessed>
      <boon>+3 Damage</boon>
      <indifferent></indifferent>
      <bane>Fumble: Lose remaining actions this round</bane>
      <damned>Roll on Misfortune Table</damned>

      <range><ranged-extremely-long/></range>
      <keywords><black-powder/></keywords>
      <dc>Target's Defence</dc>
      <dmg>Weapon</dmg>
      <effect>Attack using artillery pieces.</effect>      
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>alchemy_lesser_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character is trained in the use of artillery in sieges or naval warfare.
	The can arm, aim, fire and on some occasions repair artillery pieces.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Blood Frenzy</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>martial.blood_frenzy</abilityid>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>pool_cost_1</defaults>
      <name>Check</name>
      <actiontype><minor/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <!-- <boon></boon> -->
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <!-- <bane></bane> -->
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <dc>13</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank></prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	After your character makes a successful melee attack you can make 
	a Blood Frenzy Check.  If successful you enter a Blood Frenzy and
	get advantage for standard basic melee attacks.  While in a frenzy the character
	must perform a basic melee attack every turn.  If the character does
	not perform a basic melee attack in their turn or if their are no opponents left
	the character automatically recovers from their frenzy.	The character must make a
	morale check to voluntarily recover from their frenzy.  
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Brawl</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>brawl</abilityid>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <name>Check</name>
      <actiontype><standard/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <!-- <boon></boon> -->
      <!-- <indifferent></indifferent> -->
      <!-- <bane></bane> -->
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords></keywords>
      <dc>Target's Defence</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="90" y="90"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Brawling is the art of unarmed combat. It involves grappling, head butting,
	punching, or knocking out opponents.  The check has a -3 penalty against
	larger creatures, and a -6 penalty against much larger creatures.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Grappling<subentry>See Brawl/Grappling</subentry></indexentry>	
  	<emph>Grappling</emph> involves grabbing, tackling or wrestling an opponent and holding
  	them without harming them.  Other attacks against a grappled opponent
  	are hindered by the grappler being close to the opponent and the opponents
  	struggling. Every round that an opponent is grappled they may make an opposed
	Brawl|Str test against their grappler to escape.  Once grappled it takes a round for
  	a second character to tie-up, or otherwise constrain, the opponent.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Head Butt<subentry>See Brawl/Head Butt</subentry></indexentry>	
	A <emph>Head Butt</emph> involves the attacker driving their head into the bridge 
	of the defenders nose.  Head butting is mainly used as an attack of last resort or 
	as a surprise attack.  An attacker may only head butt someone immediately in 
	front or behind them.  An character may head butt when grappled or otherwise constrained.
	Head butts do 1d3+Str damage, +1 damage if the attacker is wearing a helmet and -1 damage
	if the defender is wearing a helmet.  
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Punch<subentry>See Brawl/Punch</subentry></indexentry>	
        <indexentry>Kick<subentry>See Brawl/Kick</subentry></indexentry>	
	When a character makes a <emph>Punch or Kick</emph> attack the attacker attempts to hit
	their opponent using their fists.  The attack is a Brawl vs Targets Defence.  It
	does 1d3+Str damage, +2 damage if the attacker is wearing gauntlets, -2 damage
	if the attacker is wearing a helmet.  
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Knockout<subentry>See Brawl/Knockout</subentry></indexentry>	
        <indexentry>Subdue<subentry>See Brawl/Knockout</subentry></indexentry>	
	After a character reduces an opponents hit points to zero using a Brawl attack or when attacking
	with a non-lethal weapon, they may make an attempt to knock the opponent out instead of killing
	them Brawl vs DC 13. If the character succeeds in their check the opponent becomes Unconscious.
	If the check fails then the opponent is killed.   
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>



  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Dirty-Fighter</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>dirty-fighter</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>    
      <name>Check</name>
      <trigger>Bane with a Success in a melee attack against an opponent of Appropriate Size</trigger>
      <actiontype><free/></actiontype>
      <range><melee/></range>
      <keywords><no-check/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent></indifferent> -->
      <!-- <dc>Triggers Ability</dc> -->
      <effect>Make a Brawl attack with a Dirty Fighter Rank bonus.</effect>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>brawl_1</prereqabilityrank>	
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	When the character makes a successful melee attack with a bane, they may immediately
	make a Brawl attack as a minor action adding their Dirty-Fighter Rank to any damage
	that the Brawl attack does.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
    
  
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Dodge</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>dodge</abilityid>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="6"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <name>Defend</name>
      <actiontype><reaction/></actiontype>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><defend/><save/></keywords>
      <dc>Opponent's Attack DC</dc>      
    </abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="90" y="120"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>      
      <p>
	<label>ability:dodge</label>
	The character may attempt to dodge, to leap out of the way of the
  	attack, <emph>instead</emph> of making an armour roll.
	Doing so uses the characters reaction for the round.
	If successful the attack is dodged and the character takes no damage.
	If the dodge fails and a bane is rolled the attack does double damage.
	If the dodge fails and a boon is rolled the attack does half damage.	
      </p>

      <p>
	Some types of attack cannot be dodged, e.g. surprise attacks or
	poisonous gas attacks.  Other types of attack <eg/> the acid or 
	fire attacks of dragons may be dodgeable depending on the context
	and deal half or no damage (at the GM's discretion).
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>  

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Juggernaut</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>juggernaut</abilityid>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <name>Check</name>
      <actiontype><standard/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <!-- <boon></boon> -->
      <!-- <indifferent></indifferent> -->
      <!-- <bane></bane> -->
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords></keywords>
      <dc>Target's Strength</dc>
      <dmg></dmg>
    </abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="90"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The attacker uses his mass and strength to brush aside those who
  	stand in his way.  Such is the force of his unstoppable charge that
  	at most one opportunity attack can be made against him.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Note that the Juggernaut ability may only be used against opponents of
  	similar or smaller size and strength.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Parry</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>parry</abilityid>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="6"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <name>Defend</name>
      <actiontype><reaction/></actiontype>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><defend/><save/></keywords>
      <dc>Opponent's Attack DC</dc>      
      <effect>Zero damage from attack</effect>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank></prereqabilityrank>	
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	<label>ability:parry</label>
        When a character is attacked they may attempt to parry the blow when using a mace or sword
	instead of making an armour roll.   If the parry result fails and a boon is rolled the attack
	deals half damage.  If the parry result fails and a bane is rolled the attack deals
	double damage.  It may not be possible to parry certain types of attack, for example
	breath weapons cannot be parried.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>   


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Retribution</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>retribution</abilityid>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="4"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>pool_cost_1</defaults>
      <name>Check</name>
      <actiontype><reaction/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <!-- <boon></boon> -->
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <!-- <bane></bane> -->
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <dc>7</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	When the characters hit points drop to 0 they can instantly make a Retribution
	check and if successful the character may immediately perform a Charge or an Attack.
      </p>

      <p>
	In the event of an overcharge the character gains the Unconscious condition at the
	end of their action.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>  
</abilitygroup>
