<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- -*-xml-*- -->
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Necromancy</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>necromancy</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><magical/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        The art of communing with the unquiet dead is at best the province of shysters 
	and charlatans and at worst an art that plays with things that no man ought.  
	It's practice is viewed with disdain by all right thinking peoples.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Commune with the Dead</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.commune_with_the_dead</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="2"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="11" effect="Talk with a corpse" overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	While holding part of the deceased's body the necromancer may ask questions of the 
	dead person.  If the spell succeeds the dead person will respond to questions 
	telepathically.  After each question roll a D4, on a 1 the link with the spirit has 
	been broken and no more questions can be asked.
      </p>

      <p>
	Answers will be heard only by the necromancer and will be heard 
	as a voice in the head.  The necromancer must ask the question in a language 
	understood by the spirit and the spirit will respond in a language they understood 
	during their lifetime.  The spirit that is contacted is under no compulsion to 
	reply and may ignore the character, lie in its responses or answer how it pleases.  
      </p>

      <p>
	The newly dead are often disorientated by their experience and may not realize that 
	they are in fact dead.  If death is sudden or traumatic a spirit may not remember 
	it.
      </p>

      <p>
	Characters may only attempt to commune with a particular dead person once.  
	Whether they succeed or fail in their first attempt they will never be 
	able to successfully commune with that person again as the things that keep the 
	gates between life and death are vigillant and fearsome.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        summoned might attack (need to exert will over them?)
        handle failure of magic
      </p>	  
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Eye for an Eye</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.eye_for_an_eye</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="5" effect="Melee dmg dealt to caster is also dealt to attacker"
		  overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>	
    <spline><p x="30" y="95"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The caster is warded.  Any attacker doing damage in melee to the caster
	also suffers the same amount of damage.  This spell lasts for the length
	of combat.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Graft Flesh</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.graft_flesh</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="11" effect="Replace amputated limbs and heal" overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>	
    <spline><p x="30" y="75"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The caster grafts the fresh flesh of one creature onto another.
	Without the appropriate skeletal, vascular and muscular support the new
	flesh will not be usable by the subject, <eg/> you can graft
	an extra arm to a subject but they will not be able to use it.
	You can however replace an existing limb with another or
	restore a previously amputated limb.  Note that you cannot
	use this spell to replace the head of a creature.  Once decapitated
	the creature is dead.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Forbidden Psalm</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.forbidden_psalm</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/><accurate/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="5" overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Perception" range="sight" effect="Save or cannot hit">Std+3ﾃ由ank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>	
    <spline><p x="30" y="75"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	If successfully cast, chanting this psalm makes it hard for the undead to see and hear the
	caster.   After an attack is made against the character by an undead creature, the caster can
	make a save against that attack by making a Std+3ﾃ由ank	check against the undeads perception.
	If successful the undead creature cannot make the attack and loses their attack for that round.
	This save is a free action that happens before any defensive ability, <eg/> dodge, made by the
	caster.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Necromancy</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.necromancy</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13" effect="Answer questions about necromancy.">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline></spline>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p noindent="true">
	The school of necromancy is concerned with the use of death or blood magic, 
	the legends of the dread necromancers and the unquiet dead.  Characters may provide
	useful information about these topics on occasion: identifying undead, and or
	their weaknesses, and providing the relevant mythology around these creatures.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>    
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Stay Death</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.stay_death</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="7" effect="Reroll one Near-Death roll." overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="15"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character holds death at bay for a moment.  The target
	can reroll a single near-death roll.  This spell may be cast
	once per character per day.  If successful the target may
	reroll a death roll.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Offering for the Blood Soucriant</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.blood_soucriant</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="11" effect="In the presence of blood, summon a demon to fight." overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="90" y="15"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	In the presence of a lot of blood the character can summon
	a Blood Soucriant.  A female demon, temptress and drinker of blood.
	The demon will not tarry long and once summoned will drink of the
	blood of the living.   If the Blood Sucreant does not drink she
	will attack the caster.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
  </ability>  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Pall of Darkness</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.pall_of_darkness</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="7" effect="Defensive checks against missile attacks made at +3ﾃ由ank"  overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>	
    <spline><p x="30" y="75"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	If successfully cast, chanting this psalm creates a dark cloud
	surrounding the caster with a radius of <measurement><imperial>20'</imperial><metric>6m</metric></measurement>.
	This cloud gives +3ﾃ由ank to defensive rolls against missile attacks.  It is clearly visible during
	the day, but may not be noticeable at night depending on the lighting.    The cloud also provides
	+Rank against area-of-effect attacks.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Veil of Corruption</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.veil_of_corruption</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><magical/><necromancy/><magicpool/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="5" effect="Resembles a corpse." overcharge="2">Magic+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>necromancy.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="90" y="15"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character appears as if dead.  This is not an illusion.  They
	look, smell, and feel like a corpse.  They may also adopt a preternatural
	stillness.  At rank 1 the character can appear as a fresh corpse, dead for
	a few hours, at rank 3 they can appear as a corpse that has been rotting
	in the weather for a few weeks.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
  </ability>  
</abilitygroup>
