<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- -*-xml-*- -->
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Necromancy</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>necromancy</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily>Magic</abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        The art of communing with the unquiet dead is at best the province of shysters 
	and charlatans and at worst an art that plays with things that no man ought.  
	It's practice is viewed with disdain by all right thinking peoples.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>      
  </abilitygroupinfo>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Commune with the Dead</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.commune</abilityid>
    <abilityclass>Non-Combat</abilityclass>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	While holding part of the deceased's body the necromancer may ask questions of the 
	dead person.  If the spell succeeds the dead person will respond to questions 
	telepathically.  After each question roll a D4, on a 1 the link with the spirit has 
	been broken and no more questions can be asked.
      </p>

      <p>
	Answers will be heard only by the necromancer and will be heard 
	as a voice in the head.  The necromancer must ask the question in a language 
	understood by the spirit and the spirit will respond in a language they understood 
	during their lifetime.  The spirit that is contacted is under no compulsion to 
	reply and may ignore the character, lie in its responses or answer how it pleases.  
      </p>

      <p>
	The newly dead are often disorientated by their experience and may not realize that 
	they are in fact dead.  If death is sudden or traumatic a spirit may not remember 
	it.
      </p>

      <p>
	Characters may only attempt to commune with a particular dead person once.  
	Whether they succeed or fail in their first attempt they will never be 
	able to successfully commune with that person again as the things that keep the 
	gates between life and death are vigillant and fearsome.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        summoned might attack (need to exert will over them?)
        handle failure of magic
      </p>	  
    </abilitydescription>

    <abilitylevels>
      <abilitylevel>
        <levelnumber>1</levelnumber>
        <defaultmartial>0</defaultmartial>
        <defaultlore>5</defaultlore>
        <defaultgeneral>0</defaultgeneral>
        <defaultmagical>5</defaultmagical>
        <successes>3</successes>
        <attempts>1</attempts>
	<check>Magic Pool vs DDC 8</check>
	<overcharge>DC + 6</overcharge>
        <prereqabilitylevel>magic_school.necromancy_1</prereqabilitylevel>	
      </abilitylevel>

      <!-- <abilitylevel> -->
      <!--   <levelnumber>1</levelnumber> -->
      <!--   <defaultcombat>8</defaultcombat> -->
      <!--   <defaulttraining>3</defaulttraining> -->
      <!--   <defaultlearning>3</defaultlearning> -->
      <!--   <successes>3</successes> -->
      <!--   <attempts>3</attempts> -->
      <!-- </abilitylevel> -->
      
      <!-- <abilitylevel> -->
      <!--   <levelnumber>2</levelnumber> -->
      <!--   <defaultcombat>8</defaultcombat> -->
      <!--   <defaulttraining>2</defaulttraining> -->
      <!--   <defaultlearning>2</defaultlearning> -->
      <!--   <attr>Str + 8</attr> -->
      <!-- </abilitylevel>       -->
    </abilitylevels>
    
  </ability>
    
</abilitygroup>
