<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- -*-xml-*- -->
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Necromancy</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>necromancy</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><magical/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        The art of communing with the unquiet dead is at best the province of shysters 
	and charlatans and at worst an art that plays with things that no man ought.  
	It's practice is viewed with disdain by all right thinking peoples.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Commune with the Dead</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>necromancy.commune</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><necromancy/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	While holding part of the deceased's body the necromancer may ask questions of the 
	dead person.  If the spell succeeds the dead person will respond to questions 
	telepathically.  After each question roll a D4, on a 1 the link with the spirit has 
	been broken and no more questions can be asked.
      </p>

      <p>
	Answers will be heard only by the necromancer and will be heard 
	as a voice in the head.  The necromancer must ask the question in a language 
	understood by the spirit and the spirit will respond in a language they understood 
	during their lifetime.  The spirit that is contacted is under no compulsion to 
	reply and may ignore the character, lie in its responses or answer how it pleases.  
      </p>

      <p>
	The newly dead are often disorientated by their experience and may not realize that 
	they are in fact dead.  If death is sudden or traumatic a spirit may not remember 
	it.
      </p>

      <p>
	Characters may only attempt to commune with a particular dead person once.  
	Whether they succeed or fail in their first attempt they will never be 
	able to successfully commune with that person again as the things that keep the 
	gates between life and death are vigillant and fearsome.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        summoned might attack (need to exert will over them?)
        handle failure of magic
      </p>	  
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="60"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>magic_school.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilitycheck dc="9" overcharge="14+Level"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="2"/>
  </ability>



  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Graft Flesh</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.graft_flesh</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><necromancy/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The caster grafts the fresh flesh of one creature onto another.
	Without the appropriate skeletal, vascular and muscular support the new
	flesh will not be usable by the subject, <eg/> you can graft
	an extra arm to a subject but they will not be able to use it.
	You can however replace an existing limb with another or
	restore a previously amputated limb.  Note that you cannot
	use this spell to replace a head on a creature.  Once decapitated
	the creature is dead.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="30" y="75"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>magic_school.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>	
    <abilitycheck dc="9" overcharge="5+Level" />
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Necromancy</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic_school.necromancy</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><necromancy/><lore/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p noindent="true">
	The school of necromancy is concerned with the use of death or blood magic.
	Necromantic lore is the study of the legends of the dread necromancers
	and the unquiet dead.  Characters may provide useful information about these
	topics on occasion: identifying undead, and or their weaknesses, and providing
	the relevant mythology around these creatures.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>    
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <spline></spline>    
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Stay Death</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.stay_death</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><necromancy/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character holds death at bay for a moment.  The target
	can reroll a single near-death roll.  This spell may be cast
	once per character per day.  If successful the target may
	reroll a death roll.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="-90" y="15"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>magic_school.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilitycheck dc="6" overcharge="10+Level"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Offering for the Blood Soucriant</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>magic.blood_soucriant</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><necromancy/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	In the presence of a lot of blood the character can summon
	a Blood Soucriant.  A female demon, temptress and drinker of blood.
	The demon will not tarry long and once summoned will drink of the
	blood of the living.   If the Blood Sucreant does not drink she
	will attack the caster.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="90" y="15"/></spline>
    <prereqabilityrank>magic_school.necromancy_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <abilitycheck dc="9" overcharge="5+Level"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Magic</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>  
</abilitygroup>
