<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Physical Abilities</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>physical</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><general/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        Represents general physical abilities and common non-weapon-specific fighting
        abilities, including boxing, wrestling and other bare handed martial
        arts.
      </p>      
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <dontdrawskilltree/>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Armour</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.armour</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><martial/><core/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	<label>ability:armour</label>
        <indexentry>Armour Check</indexentry>	
	After the character gets attacked they make an <defn>armour check</defn> to see if that attack
	was successfully defeated by the characters armour. If successful the character takes no damage
	from the attack.  This can be interpreted as the either the armour taking the force of the blow
	and protecting the character, or the character moving in such a way that the
	the character is struck a glancing blow leaving them uninjured.
      </p>

      <p>	
	Instead of making an armour check the character may
	choose to dodge, shield block, parry or use some
	other attack-reaction ability.   Armour is not a reaction and does not use the characters
	reaction for the current turn unlike many other defence check abilities.  
      </p>

      <p>
	To make an Armour Check the modifier is calculated as follows.  First calculate the bonus
	for the type of armour worn by the character, <eg/>Plate provides +4, No armour provides +0.
	The Armour Modifier is then this Armour Level, plus the Armour Bonus minus, +1 if a shield
	is used, minus three.	
      </p>

      <p>
	If the armour result fails and a boon is rolled the attack deals half damage.  If
	the armour result fails and a bane is rolled the attack deals double damage.
	If the armour check succeeds the attack does no damage.  If it fails the attack does
	normal damage.
      </p>

      <p>
	Some attacks cannot be defended with armour, <eg/> a dragons breath weapon.  If no other
	attack-reaction ability is used the attack automatically does normal damage.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitycheck dc="Attack DC" />
    <abilitychecktype>Armour+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="3"/>
  </ability>
  
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Charge</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.charge</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><martial/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="3" overcharge="9+Level"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Mettle</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
        The Charge ability allows the character to test their mettle.  If sucessful they
	may move their movement rate +1d6 in the direction of an enemy and then make an
	additional melee attack.  A character cannot Charge an enemy who is within their
	movement range as there is not enough distance to build up speed, (in that case they
	should just move and attack). If the character fails to reach their attacker
	then they must move at their full movement plus extra charge moment towards
	their foe and finish their turn in the open without attacking.  
      </p>

      <p>
	Attacks made with this ability gain the Charge tag and any rules that apply to
	such tags, such as Brace for Charge, can be used against the Charger.  Charging may
	provoke a break test in opponents at the GM's discretion.  On overcharge the character
	becomes Enraged.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="3"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Climb</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.climb</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents the characters ability to Climb.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="150"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="6"/>
  </ability>

  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Dodge</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.dodge</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><martial/><core/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="Attack DC"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	<label>ability:dodge</label>
	The character may attempt to dodge <emph>instead</emph> of making an armour roll.
	Doing so uses the characters reaction for the round.
	If successful the attack is dodged and the character takes no damage.
	If the dodge fails and a bane is rolled the attack does double damage.
	If the dodge fails and a boon is rolled the attack does half damage.	
      </p>

      <p>
	Some types of attack cannot be dodged, e.g. surprise attacks or
	poisonous gas attacks.  Other types of attack <eg/> the acid or 
	fire attacks of dragons may be dodgeable depending on the context
	and deal half or no damage (at the GM's discretion).
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="120"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="6"/>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Flee</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.flee</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
        The Flee ability allows the character to move more than twice their movement rate
	away from an enemy, fear has given them wings.  Characters who are fleeing must
	make a Rally check in the End Stage to stop fleeing.  Characters may voluntarily
	flee if there exists a credible threat, or they may be forced to flee if they
	fail a break test.  For the purposes of game play fleeing is considered to be a
	double movement <emph>+d6</emph>.  Fleeing is successful if the character is not
	damaged in the following round.  Fleeing does <emph>not</emph> trigger an attack of
	opportunity.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="30"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="6"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Grapple</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.grapple</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><nonlethal/><untrained/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Grappling involves grabbing, tackling or wrestling an opponent and holding 
	them without harming them.  Other attacks against a grappled opponent
	are hindered by the grappler being close to the opponent and the opponents
	struggling.
      </p>

      <p>
	Every round that an opponent is grappled they may make an opposed Str test 
	against their grappler to escape.  Once grappled it takes a round for 
	a second character to tie-up, or otherwise constrain, the opponent.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="90"/></spline> 
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Str or Grapple"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels untrained="-3" from="0" to="3"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Head Butt</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.head_butt</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><nonlethal/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Defence"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg>2 + Str</abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	A head butt involves the attacker driving the top of their head into the bridge 
	of the defenders nose.  Head butting is mainly used as an attack of last resort or 
	as a surprise attack.  An attacker may only head butt someone immediately in 
	front or behind them.  An character may head butt when grappled.
      </p>

      <p>
	Head butts do +1 damage if the attacker is wearing a helmet and -1 damage
	if the defender is wearing a helmet.  
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="0" y="90"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="3"/>
  </ability>  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Jump</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.jump</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents the characters ability to Jump.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline></spline>
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="6"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Juggernaut</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.juggernaut</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><nonlethal/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="Opposed Targets Strength + 1 per opponent"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The attacker uses his mass and strength to brush aside those who
	stand in his way.  Such is the force of his unstoppable charge that
	at most one opportunity attack can be made against him.
      </p>

      <p>
	Note that the Juggernaut ability may only be used against opponents of
	similar or smaller size and strength.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="90"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Knockout</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.knockout</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><nonlethal/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Knockout</indexentry>
	After a character reduces an opponents hit points to zero
	the character may make an attempt to knock the opponent
	out instead of killing them.  The opponent must be humanoid and of the same
	size as the attacker or smaller.  If the character succeeds in
	their Knockout Check the opponent becomes Unconscious.  If
	the check fails then the opponent is killed.   Note that Lethal and Nonlethal
	tagged weapons modify this check.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="180"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="3"/>
  </ability>  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Kick</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.kick</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><nonlethal/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The attacker kicks an opponent potentially pushing the opponent back
	at higher levels. The opponent must be approximately the same sized
	or smaller as the attacker in order to be pushed.
      </p>

      <p>
	A successful kick at level 3 and above pushes the defender back (provided
	the defender is the same size as the attacker or smaller).
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Defence"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg>2 + Speed|Strength</abilitydmg>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="120"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>



  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Listen</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.listen</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This is the characters ability to hear faint noise.
	<indexentry>Hear Noise<subentry>see Listen</subentry></indexentry>    
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>      
    <spline><p x="0" y="120"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Move</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.move</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><move/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><core/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
        The Move ability describes movement within combat.  It allows the character to move
	up to their movement rate during combat or pursuit.  This ability automatically
	succeeds if the character is not incapacicated in some way.  Characters should check if
	they are suffering some kind of leg injury, or carrying a fallen companion etc.
      </p>

      <p>
	Characters who fail to Move.. still move an amount determined by the GM, they just do
	not move their full movement rate. During a pursuit the character increases their
	rank by two if they fail and three if they succeed.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="0" y="180"/></spline> 
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Notice</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.notice</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents the characters attention to detail,
	alertness, and their ability to notice subtle things in urban
	environments that are not as they should be.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Detect Traps<subentry>see Notice (Urban)</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Traps<subentry>see Notice (Urban)</subentry></indexentry>
	This ability is used to detect traps.  In the wilderness use the
	Scout ability and use a Perception Check elsewhere.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>      
    <spline><p x="0" y="150"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>


  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Punch</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.punch</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><nonlethal/></tags>    
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Defence"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg>d4</abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The attacker attempts to hit their opponent using their fists. 
	Does +2 damage if the attacker is wearing gauntlets, -2 damage
	if the attacker is wearing a helmet.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="60"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Rest</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.rest</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Healing<subentry>Rest</subentry></indexentry>		
        The character takes a moment to catch their breath
        and collect themselves.  This takes five to ten minutes.
        Given time the character succeeds automatically. 
        If the character only has a few minutes to rest or they
	are interupted then they must check to see if they are successful.
      </p>

      <p>
        Characters only benefit from up to two Rests between Sleeps.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="0" y="60"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Run</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.run</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><move/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
        The Run ability describes extra movement within combat.  It allows the character
	to move	twice their movement rate during combat or pursuit.  This ability
	automatically succeeds if the character is not incapacicated in some way.
      </p>

      <p>
	In addition, the character may make a check to go for it, and move a bit further in
	addition to their double move.  This ability represents the characters fleet
	footedness.  During combat this is represented by moving an extra 1-3 squares when
	playing on a grid, or some other narrative effect during TOTM combat.  If the character
	fails their check they need to make an Agility check or suffer a bane.
      </p>

      <p>
	During a pursuit the character increases their rank by two if they fail and three
	if they succeed.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="30"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Sixth Sense</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.sixth_sense</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><special/></tags>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	If the character makes a successful check they may reroll their
	surpriseor initiative rolls, or rolls for saving against speed related
	traps and other similar checks.  
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <abilitycheck dc="15"/>
    <spline><p x="0" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitylevels from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Sleep</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.sleep</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Healing<subentry>Sleep</subentry></indexentry>	
        The character sleeps for six or more hours.  If the characters
        sleep is uninterrupted then no check is required.  If the characters
        are attacked or disturbed they may need to make a check to see whether
	they are fully rested.  
      </p>

      <p>
        If the character sleeps then they receive two refreshes, if they
        are required to check and they fail then they only receive one refresh.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="60"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Sure Feet</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.sure_feet</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	When the attacker would be knocked prone they can check to resist being
	knocked over.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Swim</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.swim</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="9"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents the characters ability to swim (if at all).  Everyone
	is assumed to be able to dog paddle instinctively.  Failure of this check
	means that the character is unable to make any progress.  Repeated failures
	might result in the characters having to make exhaustion or resolve checks
	as they start to panic.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="180"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>
  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Throw</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.throw</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><standard/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><martial/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Level</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This character attempts to thrown something.  If unsuccessful, and a bane occurs
	and they are under some form of pressure the character drops the item at their feet.
	Otherwise unsuccessful throws scatter one random square five times.  If sucessful the
	throw is accurate.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="-90" y="150"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Witness Me</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>physical.witness_me</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="3" overcharge="9+Level" />
    <abilitychecktype>Mettle</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	When the characters hit points drop to 0 they can instantly make a "Witness Me"
	check and if successful the character may perform a Charge or an Attack.  If
	a Charge is performed no roll for successfully charging is required.  Default
	weapon damage is doubled.
      </p>

      <p>
	In the event of an overcharge the character gains the Unconscious condition at the
	end of their action.
      </p>
      
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline> 
    <abilitylevels from="0" to="4"/>
  </ability>  
</abilitygroup>
