<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>
  <!--
      
      Note this is not a document format.
      Docs get generated from this.
      
  -->

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Social Abilities</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>social</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><general/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
	Social abilities are used to represent the characters
	ability and knowledge with interacting with parts of
	society to achieve their goals.
      </p>

      <p>
	There are a number of Social Abilities that the GM
	should feel to give to players based on their background
	or interaction with people or time spent in a locale.
	In particular Fame/Infamy, Etiquette and Contacts can
	be used to represent a characters knowledge or reputation
	of various social groups.
      </p>	
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <dontdrawskilltree/>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Adversary</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.adversary</abilityid>
    <abilitytemplate>monster-type</abilitytemplate>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="70" y="90"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character bear an animosity towards, and/or have been trained
	to fight opponents of type [monster-class].  At the start of
	combat and every following round until they succeeed, characters
	make an adversary check.  If successful their training kicks in and
	for the rest of the combat they the characters gains a bonus equal to
	their adversary rank for combat checks against monsters of the given
	monster-class (the bonus is to the check only and not to damage).
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Contacts</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.contacts</abilityid>
    <abilitytemplate>society</abilitytemplate>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="6"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="9">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="0" y="30"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <indexentry>High Contacts</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Low Contacts</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Middleh Contacts</indexentry>

      <p>
	The Contacts ability can best be described by the phrase: ``I know a guy...''.
	It represents the characters knowledge of people who have useful abilities or
	information within part of society.  For example a character who has
	Contacts (Thieves Guild) might know a guy who is a fence and can sell
	stolen goods.  The Contacts abilility does not effect any existing
	relationships the character has with NPCs.
      </p>

      <p>	
	Contacts is a ability template.  That is when you learn
	the ability you learn it for a particular society.  When
	you do this replace [society] with an actual campaign
	specific society, talk to your GM about it, <eg/>
	Contacts[The Cult of the Black Hand].  You can have multiple
	different instances of this ability at different ranks for any number of
	societies.
      </p>      

      <p>
	If your character has high contacts they know certain people
	in high places.  These people may be a useful source of
	information or work.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	If your character has contacts they know many people
	in the middle classes.  Business men, religious types,
	book keepers, wise men, artists and scholars.
      </p>

      <p>
	If your character has low contacts they know many people
	in the lower classes in some town or city.  Thieves, smugglers,
	stand-over men, beggars, bandits and lepers.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>



  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Deceive</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.deceive</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="Targets Perception">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="30" y="75"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Lying convincingly can be difficult.  This ability represents
	how good a liar the character is.  Typically you check against the
	opponents Perceive.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Etiquette</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.etiquette</abilityid>
    <abilitytemplate>society</abilitytemplate>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="0" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <indexentry>High Etiquette</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Low Etiquette</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Middle Etiquette</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Persuasion</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Diplomacy</indexentry>
      <p>
	Etiquette represents knowledge of the code of behaviour and
	the social norms of a particular group or part of society.
	Etiquette is required to pass as a member of that society
	during extended conversations and or periods of time.  Using the
	wrong dining implements or not knowing the meaning of 
	common slang words betray the characters true origins.
      </p>
	 
      <p>
	Etiquette is a templated ability.
	A character may simultaneously have multiple Etiquette abilities at
	different ranks, one for each society which they have studied.
	Each instantiation of the Etiquette ability is annotated with that abilities
	particular society and rank.  For example, a spy type archetype might
	have Etiquette[Nobility of Verungia] II, Etiquette[The Black Hand] I,
	and Etiquette[Midheim Docks] I.
	Characters can train new abilities in Etiquette for new societies, provided
	that they access to some source of learning that allows the character to
	learn the social norms of the new social group.  
      </p>

      <p>
	For new characters we make a distinction between High, Middle
	and Low ettiquette.   This is just a short-hand that allows new players
	to choose an initial campaign-specific Etiquette ability that is from a
	restricted set of societies congruent with that characters upbringing.
      </p>

      <p>
	Etiquette[High] is the knowledge of the social behaviours of 
	the upper classes.  This might be the Nobility of the Kingdom of Churia,
	the Church of Bromion, the Dwarven High Council or the Guild of Mages.
	The player has to choose a specific high society.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	Etiquette[Middle] is the knowledge of the social behaviours of the middle
	classes.  Examples might include The Merchants Guild of the City
	of Verburg, The Artisans of Iron Mountain, Merchant Ship Officers of the North
	Seas and so on.
      </p>

      <p>
	Etiquette[Low] is the knowledge of the social behaviours and
	norms of the lower classes.  You need to know low ettiquette
	if you don't want to be noticed when amongst the hoi polloi.
      </p>      

      <p>
	Every character also has an implicit Etiquette ability for their own
	society.  They never need to check on this ability, they automatically
	succeeed.
      </p>

      <p>
	Societies are related to one another, and some societies are more
	closely related than others.  Societies that are related by class
	or purpose, for example, nobles or merchants are more closely related
	than societies that are not.  Societies that are closer geographically
	are more closely related than societies that are located far apart.
	The GM should allow players to use Etiquette in one society to
	make checks for Etiquette in other, closely related societies.  These
	checks should be made at a higher DC than usual.
      </p>	      
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Fame</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.fame</abilityid>
    <abilitytemplate>society</abilitytemplate>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <indexentry>Renown</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Fame</indexentry>
      <indexentry>Infamy</indexentry>
      <p>
	Fame is a measure of a characters (or parties) Renown or Infamy
	within some society.  It represents how well known the characters are within
	that society.  Within that society the character may be respected or despised
	or somewhere in between depending on the actions that led to their fame.
	Renown may be used during social interactions at the GMs discretion.  It is
	possible to be both famous and infamous within a society. 
      </p>

      <p>
	Unlike other abilities the rank of Fame increases when the GM dictates.  Usually this
	should happen immediately after the current rank is mastered.  It is a narrative
	driven ability.  Note that to become famous people within the society need to know of
	the characters exploits. It is up to the GM to decide when characters receive their
	first rank of Fame for a given society.
      </p>

      <playexample>
	<p>
	  For example Dourli has been helping out the local Dwarven smugglers with some
	  of their problems. Dourli has Fame IV [Smugglers].  Fame might help Dourli to get
	  favours from the Smugglers.  In contrast, When Dourli is caught up in a raid
	  after some fisticuffs in a tavern brawl one of the city guards might recognize
	  him.  To determine if this is so Dourli rolls a Std 2d12 and tries to roll under
	  his Fame.  If he rolls over perhaps one of the guards recognizes him.  In this
	  case that is not the desired option but it does increase his notoriety within
	  the town marginally (it counts as a success in terms of mastery).
	</p>

	<p>
	  Either way, Fame can help to establish ones bona fides.  Later when
	  Dourli turns up to warn the castellan of the existance of a death cult
	  based near the docks, the fact that he is recognized by some of the guards
	  may help confirm parts of his story and his identity.
	</p>	
      </playexample>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Infamy</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.infamy</abilityid>
    <abilitytemplate>society</abilitytemplate>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="-90" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>
      <indexentry>Infamy</indexentry>
      <p>
	Infamy .. see Fame above.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Interrogate</abilitytitle> 
    <abilityid>social.interrogate</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/><untrained/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="None">Std+Rank</abilitycheck> <!-- FIXME -->
    <spline><p x="90" y="105"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character can make a Std check against an opponent.
  	The target opposes the check by making a hidden roll with one of
  	Fortitude, Endurance, Deceive or Willpower.
      </p>

      <p>
  	If successful the character can determine if the target is answered a question
  	truthfully.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Interrogating a subject involves asking them a barrage of questions
  	and sifting through what they say to find the truth, a process which might
  	take days.  Torture involves hurting the target until they answer
  	questions.  Torture is a deeply disturbing process that may well have
  	a lasting effect on the characters personality.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Intimidate</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.intimidate</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/><untrained/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="None">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>  <!-- FIXME -->
    <spline><p x="0" y="105"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character can make an check against an opponent
  	using strength.  The target opposes the check with
  	one of Strength, Fortitude, Endurance, Speed or Willpower.
  	If successful the character can boss the target around,
  	extract information from them and so on.  The target
  	will not perform actions that they are strongly morally
  	opposed to, or that are highly detrimental to them.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>



  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Leadership</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.leadership</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="0" y="165"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>    
      <p>
	The character is a leader.  They may
	yell some encouraging words to an associate who has
	just failed a morale check, <eg/> ``Fight you Scum''.  If successful the target
	may reroll their morale check.  Only one such reroll is	permitted per character
	per encounter.
      </p>

      <p>
	Leadership can be used to
	try and momentarilly stop a combat so that some form of
	negotiation can occur: "Yield you scum, you are clearly beat".
	The GM will specify a difficulty based on the morale of the
	opponents and their nature.  If successful combat stops
	and negotiation begins (note this does not mean that the
	opponents are bound to a peaceful resolution).
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Negotiate</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.negotiate</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="None">Std+Rank</abilitycheck> <!-- FIXME Opponents Negotiate -->
    <spline><p x="-90" y="105"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	Negotiation is the art of the deal, persuasion and diplomacy.
  	When some arrangement is in both parties favour and one party
  	wants to extend the terms one more time, that is when the
  	negotiate ability comes into play.
      </p>
      
      <p>
  	<indexentry>negotiation</indexentry>
  	Negotiation during combat is difficult but a quickly yelled
  	proposition or plea for pax is a free action.  In such cases
  	there is a brief lull in fighting while the character yells out
  	a proposition.  This may be handy when characters need to
  	negotiate a more favourable outcome when combat is going badly
  	for them.  Negotiation cannot occur during a surprise round.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Negotiation requires the consent of both parties involved.
  	After negotiations have commenced either party can break off
  	negotiation at any time at which point combat recommenses.
  	The GM should generally encourage negotiation and give the
  	players a chance to talk their way out of situations.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Unintelligent creatures will never participate in negotiation.
  	There is no point arguing with a charging wild boar.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Negotiation need not be limited to verbal communication.
  	It may be possible to negotiate using signs, mimes, charades,
  	mimicking sounds etc.
      </p>
      
      <p>
  	Both monsters and players are free to use negotiation in
  	an attempt to play for time - waiting for the cavalry to arrive.
  	However, if the opponent guesses this is what they are up to
  	they simply ignore the negotiation and continue their attack
  	instantaneously.
      </p>

      <p>
  	It is possible for there to be barriers to negotiation: loud
  	noises, distance, etc.  If that is the case the GM can require
  	an appropriate check be made before negotiation can commence.
      </p>

      <p>
  	The negotiation check is opposed by negotiation or the GM can
  	pick a DC for an NPC opponent.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Rally</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.rally</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/><mettlepool/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="3">Mettle+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="165"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>    
      <p>
        When characters starts to flee they need to Rally before they can stop.
	On overcharge the character becomes enraged.
      </p>	
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Yield</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>social.yield</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><social/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="0" from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="9">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <spline><p x="60" y="165"/></spline> 
    <abilitydescription>    
      <p>
	Vanquished characters may <defn>Yield</defn>.  When characters yield 
	they acknowledge their defeat and throw their fate at the mercy of their 
	opponent.  The effectiveness of this strategy depends on the opponent, but 
	most humans will spare a foe who has yielded.  Orcs will keep the downfallen 
	until they run out of other meat.  Even a bear (protecting its family) may 
	lose interest if you play dead.
      </p>	
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>  
</abilitygroup>
