<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>
  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Special Abilities</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>special</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><general/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
	Special abilities are extraordinary abilities or racial abilities not available 
	to most characters in the usual course of events.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <dontdrawskilltree/>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Blindsight</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>special.blindsight</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><immediate/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><physical/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="12"/>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character has heightened senses when fighting unseen
	opponents.  They are atuned to slight noises and minor
	air movements that give away the location of unseen attackers.
      </p>

      <p>
	When a character with Blindsight is fighting an unseen opponent
	each time they try and attack the opponent, before they roll to attack,
	they roll a Blindsight check.   If the Blindsight check is successful
	the character only suffers a -3 modifier for the rest of the encounter
	instead of the usual -6.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="90" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitychecktype>Std+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Sixth Sense</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>special.sixth_sense</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><reaction/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><special/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="3"/>    
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	If the character makes a successful Luck check they may reroll their surprise
	roll.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
    <spline><p x="0" y="0"/></spline> 
    <abilitychecktype>Luck+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Natural Sprinter</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>special.natural_sprinter</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><free/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><special/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="3"/>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Dwarves are natural sprinters.  While slow to get moving,
	and not the most agile when it comes to dodging and
	quick changes of direction, Dwarves can build up a fair
	amount of speed in a straight line over time.	
      </p>

      <p>
	Each round when sprinting or fleeing Dwarves may a mettle checkto attempt to increase
	to sprint.  If successful their speed increases by +1, to maximum speed of 7.  This
	increase in speed is cumulative as long as the Dwarf continues to Sprint/Flee.  If
	for any reason they stop running/fleeing their speed returns to normal.  In the event
	of overcharge the Dwarf loses a mettle die, they've run too fast and are winded.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <abilitychecktype>Mettle+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilitydmg></abilitydmg>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Fey Immunity/Vulnerability</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>special.fey_resilience</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><minor/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><special/><pool/></tags>
    <abilitycheck dc="3"/>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The fey are resistant to damage from non-magically conductive sources.
	They reduce damage from non-ferrous metal weapons by their ability rank for each hit.
	They are also vulnerable to cold iron/ferrous attacks.  Suffering an extra
	+rank damage per hit from iron weapons.
      </p>

      <p>
	Fey creatures may make a mettle check to magically heal +d6 health.  In the event of
	an overcharge the Fey creature loses a mettle die.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    
    <spline><p x="0" y="60"/></spline> 
    <abilitychecktype>Mettle+Rank</abilitychecktype>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="4"/>
  </ability> 
</abilitygroup>
