<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>

  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Wilderness Abilities</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid>wilderness</abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><general/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        Represents those abilities used to live in the wilderness: hunting, tracking,
	wayfinding, survivalism and woodcraft.
      </p>

      <p>
	The biomes for these abilities include: Deserts, Plains/Woodlands, Marshes, Hills, Forests, Mountains, Tundra, Jungles, and the Seas.
	Plains and Woodlands are sparsely wooded, often due to logging.  This land is more common in ``civilized'' areas.  Forests tend to be 
	deeper, darker, and larger bodies, often never before logged, woodlands.
      </p>

      <p>
	There is some overlap between biomes so a character with an ability for one biome may make checks for a "related" biome at a
	higher DC than normal.  For example suppose a character with ✱survivalism[Hills]_1 wants to make a check while in a Forests
	biome, the GM may allow them to make the check at a harder DC than usual, because of the similarity between these biomes (they
	may share flora and fauna).
      </p>
      
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>


  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Dungeoneering</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>wilderness.dungeoneering</abilityid>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><general/><wilderness/><untrained/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="4"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wilderness.lore_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Skills used for living under the ground: detect slope, detect depth,
	find direction.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Survivalism</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>wilderness.survivalism</abilityid>
    <abilitytemplate>terrain-type</abilitytemplate>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><general/><wilderness/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="4"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wilderness.lore_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Survivalism encompasses a range of skills used to survive in the
	wilds, this includes wayfinding, living off the land, trapping,
	scavenging for berries and other edible plants, and knowledge of
	what can and cannot be eaten.
      </p>

      <p>
	This ability includes constructing make-shift shelters, starting fires in
	challenging conditions, finding water, trapping and the use of snares.  Normally this is not an issue 
	for characters.  However, when the cold north winds start to howl and the 
	snow falls, when food runs low, or when alone in the burning deserts survival
	becomes	difficult and someone should test against this ability.
        <indexentry>Traps<subentry>create Survivalism (Wilderness)</subentry></indexentry>	
      </p>
           
      <p>
	Wayfinding is the art of finding paths through 
	the wilderness to a destination.  Along major roads
	no check is required.  Along tracks and side paths
	this should be a fairly straight-forward test.  
	When walking through deep forest or jungle or foggy marshes
	this should be a hard test.  Possession of a map 
	or being in view of landmarks should also make the 
	test much easier.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Hunting, Scouting and Tracking</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>wilderness.hunting</abilityid>
    <abilitytemplate>terrain-type</abilitytemplate>
    <abilityactiontype><non-combat/></abilityactiontype>
    <tags><general/><wilderness/></tags>
    <abilityranks untrained="-3" from="1" to="4"/>
    <abilitycheck dc="13">Std+Rank</abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wilderness.lore_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	Tracking involves following trails left by others.
  	It applies mainly to the wilderness but given the right
  	circumstances may be used in cities or beneath the earths
  	surface.  The tracker observes changes in the
  	environment caused by the individuals being tracked.
  	For example, it might be impossible to track someone
  	who had moved down a corridor unless they had just walked
  	through mud or water, or were wounded and leaving
  	a trail of blood.
      </p>

      <p>
  	This ability encompases the use of stealth to move silently in
	the wilderness, avoiding detection, while not leaving a trace
	of the characters passage in the wilderness.  This ability can
	be used to avoid being tracked. It can also be used for
	evading pursuit in the wilderness.
      </p>

      <p>
	Hunting involves finding and killing animals with a bow
	or spear.
      </p>

      <p>
	Scouting is the ability to notice things that are out of
	place in the wilderness.  The character becomes aware of
	any subtle but strange changes in the environment.  
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Detect Traps<subentry>see Hunting (Wilderness)</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Traps<subentry>see Hunting (Wilderness)</subentry></indexentry>
	Scout can be used to detect traps, snares, lures etc in the wilderness.
	In urban environments use the Notice ability, and use a
	Perception Check in other cases.
      </p>	            
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  
</abilitygroup>
