<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<abilitygroup>
  <abilitygroupinfo>
    <abilitygrouptitle>Wyrd Science Abilities</abilitygrouptitle>
    <abilitygroupid><wyrdscience/></abilitygroupid>
    <abilitygroupfamily><wyrdscience/></abilitygroupfamily>
    <abilitygroupdescription>
      <p>
        Wyrd Science is based on five sacred pillars: Biology,
	Electrochemistry, Blaylock Valves, Humoural Theory, and Leeches.
	Upon this foundation great minds strive to create a brave new world.
      </p>
    </abilitygroupdescription>
    <enabled/>
  </abilitygroupinfo>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Feign Death</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>feign_death</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <righteoussuccess>The feigned death is extremely convincing.</righteoussuccess>
      <fail></fail>
      <grimfail>You twitch or sneeze at an unfortunate time.</grimfail>
      <critfail>You succeed in entering the trance but remain in a death like state for longer than you intended.</critfail>
      <boon>Your example assists any companions in doing the same .. they gain a +2 to Feign Death or using Deception to pretend
      to be dead.</boon>
      <dc>7</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wyrdscience_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character can enter a death-like state through a special meditative trance.
	This state should convince people that the character is dead under cursory examination.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Flesh Golem</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>flesh_golem</abilityid>
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_3</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <grimfail></grimfail>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <!-- <indifferent></indifferent> -->
      <dc>11</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>homunculus_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character has worked out how to control reanimated humans using wyrd science and brain implants.
  	In order to create a Flesh Golem the character needs access to a laboratory.  Flesh Golems behave
  	like Homonculi but are much much larger.
      </p>

      <p>
  	When assisting in combat a flesh golem has 20 hit points, 10 stamina, an armour of +2.  They attack
  	using their bare hands with +3 to hit and do damage of 2d10 (they are not very coordinated but quite strong).
  	Flesh Golems love fighting and their master must make a Mettle DC2 check to control them when any physical
  	combat begins or the flesh golem will automatically attack.  A similar check may be made to control the
  	Flseh Golem when they get excited for other reasons.
      </p>

      <p>
  	In all other ways Flesh Golems behave as if they were homunculi.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Homunculus</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>homunculus</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_3</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <dc>11</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wyrdscience_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character is able to create a
  	<measurement><metric>50cm</metric><imperial>20"</imperial></measurement> tall humanoid
  	servitor from flesh.  The homunculus has a mental link with its creator but has
  	limited intelligence.  The homonculus always knows where its master is and will be able
  	to find its master when it pleases.  It is capable of running errands and assisting in combat.
  	Homunculi must do what their creator tells them, unless they get really excited.  Homunculi are
  	very hard to contain.  They often escape from enclosures through unknown devious means.
      </p>

      <p>
  	When creating an homunculus a character gathers the requisite material, off-cuts from a fresh corpse,
  	a variety of alchemical reagents and a manual for the binding,  They make the check to create the
  	homoculus.  If they fail the ingredients are wasted and must be destroyed.  If successful the
  	creation will rise within a few hours.  An homunculus can have only one master.  It will only
  	do as directed by others if it feels its master	would want that.  If someone creates two homuculi
  	they will both try and destroy the other.  This never ends well.
      </p>

      <p>
  	When assisting in combat the homunculus has 3 hit points, no stamina, an armour of +2 (they're small
  	and nasty) and provides a +1 to hit and damage bonus to one character fighting in melee hand to hand.
  	That character need not be its master.  Homunculi love fighting and their master must make a
  	Mettle DC2 check to control them when any physical combat begins or the homuculus will automatically
  	attack.  A similar check may be made to control the homunculus when they get excited for other reasons.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Homonculi are basically an ambulatory fetish, possessed by some minor demon from beyond.  Their
  	actions are strongly curtailed by the rigourous, standardized and very lengthy binding that is part
  	of their creation ritual.  However, homoculi frequently resort to type, eating the flesh of humans
  	or excrement when they can, laughing loudly at the misfortune of others, and if left on their own the
  	might resort to theft, or the mutilation of animals. They have been known to murder small children or
  	light fires, but it is believed that all such loopholes	have now been covered in their binding ritual.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Homoculi attract a certain amount of attention.  Clothes should be made for them so as not to attract
  	more attention than is absolutely necessary as their bodies are hideous.  Alternatively they may be
  	carried around in a box.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Thankfully, homonculi do not talk a great deal. When they do they usually being sycophantic, or sarcastic.
  	They delight in the misfortune of others which really excites them.  They may get jealous if their master
  	pays too much attention to others.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Homunculi do not really die unless their body is destroyed beyond recognition, is burned or eaten <etc/>.
  	They can be healed by simply sewing them back together.  If someone chooses to do this they will regain
  	all health after a long rest.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Wyrd Rats</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>wyrd_rat</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_1</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <dc>15</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wyrdscience_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
  	The character has worked out how to control rats using wyrd
  	science and brain implants.  In order to create a Wyrd Rat the character needs access
  	to a laboratory. Wyrd Rats have a telepathic bond with their master, they can perform minor
  	tasks and can attack on command.   Wyrd Rats have HP:1, AC:13+Rank, Bite DC:13+Rank, Dmg:1.
  	They can try to create a Wyrd Rat once per day.  If they fail, the rat survives but it is impossible
  	to make a telepathic link with the creature.  Each day spent in preparation gives the character +1 to
  	their check, up to a maximum of +3.  They get an additional +1 for naming the rat, which strengthens
  	the chance that the telepathic bond will hold.  The character can have and control up to Rank Wyrd Rats
  	after this it is impossible for the character to maintain the telepathic link with the rats.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Splice Flesh</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>splice_flesh</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_2</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <dc>11</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wyrdscience_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	FIXME
	Make the check and you can graft a limb from something to replace
	an existing limb.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Meld Flesh</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>meld_flesh</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_2</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <dc>13</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>splice_flesh_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Make the check and you can graft an arm from something onto a 
	subject.  Maximum one per subject.  No character in their right mind
	will voluntarily allow themselves to be subject to this surgery, though
	for the purposes of this ability the plague doctor is not considered to
	be in their right mind.  
      </p>

      <p>
	If the extra limb is an arm it grants an extra hand to the character
	not an extra action.  So for example, they might be able to use a
	two handed weapon and a shield, or hold a bomb and a sword and a torch.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	Each time the character increases the level of
	this ability they can add extra abilities to their wyrd-limb.
	FIXME: extra abilities here, e.g. retractable, extendable, stronger,
	claws, ...
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Inner Eye</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>inner_eye</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_2</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <dc>13</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>splice_flesh_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Make the check and you can graft an eye from something onto a 
	subject.  Maximum one per subject.  No character in their right mind
	will voluntarily allow themselves to be subject to this surgery, though
	for the purposes of this ability the plague doctor is not considered to
	be in their right mind.  <!-- Each time the character increases the level of -->
	<!-- this ability they can add extra abilities to their wyrd-limb. -->
      </p>

      <p>
	FIXME: extra abilities here.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Reanimation</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>reanimation</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_3</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <dc>11</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wyrdscience_3</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="90" y="120"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	FIXME: like a zombie.. but doesn't last and isn't necromantic.
	The character gains +1 to their roll if they proclaim "It's Alive!" while
	making this check.

	FIXME SEE FLESH GOLEM ABOVE?!
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>


  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Revivify</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>revivify</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="3"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults> 
      <defaults>pool_cost_1</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent>1</indifferent> -->
      <dc>11</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>splice_flesh_2</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-30" y="60"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	Make the check and if successful the character can aid a character who is rolling on the near-death table.
	Revivify negates the negative modifiers from the Bleeding Out and Bleeding Out Fast resuts, and converts the
	Maimed effect to Unconscious.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
  
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Wyrd Hand</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>wyrd_hand</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>wyrd_science_defaults</defaults>
      <defaults>pool_cost_1</defaults>
      <actiontype><noncombat/></actiontype>
      <critsuccess></critsuccess>
      <critfail></critfail>
      <boon></boon>
      <bane></bane>
      <range><na/></range>
      <keywords><mettlepool/></keywords>
      <!-- <indifferent></indifferent> -->
      <dc>15</dc>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank>wyrdscience_1</prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="-60" y="30"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	FIXME: disembodied hand.. like the Thing,
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>

  
  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Wyrd Science</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>wyrdscience</abilityid>    
    <abilityranks from="1" to="5"/>
    <abilitycheck>
      <defaults>lore_defaults</defaults>
      <keywords><lore/><wyrdscience/></keywords>
    </abilitycheck>
    <prereqabilityrank></prereqabilityrank>
    <spline><p x="0" y="0"/></spline>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This ability represents general theoretical knowledge of the foundational principles of Wyrd Science.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>
  </ability>
</abilitygroup>
