<table>
    <tablecategory>FullWidth</tablecategory>
    <tablespec><fixed>0.07</fixed><fixed>0.87</fixed></tablespec>
    <tabletitle>Temporary Insanities</tabletitle>
    <tablelabel>fig:insanities</tablelabel>

    <tableheaderrow>
      <td>Roll d8</td>
      <td>Aspect</td>
    </tableheaderrow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>1</td><td><bold>No effect.</bold></td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>2</td><td><bold>Amnesia</bold>
      <p>
	The character gains the Amnesia aspect.  They must compell the aspect
	against themselves in order to recall things.. including casting spells.
      </p>
    </td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>3</td><td><bold>Multiple Personality Disorder</bold>
      <p>
	The character gains a "Mulitple Personality Disorder" aspect and then also
	gets a whole new set of aspects for their second personality.
	The second set of aspects is kept distinct from the characters normal aspects.
	Have the party determine the new personalities persona and aspects.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	When the multiple personality order is compelled the character switches to
	the alternate set of aspects.  When the multiple personality disorder aspect is
	diminished the character returns to their original set of aspects and their
	second persona and all its associated aspects are removed from the character.
      </p>
    </td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>4</td><td><bold>Paranoia</bold>
      <p>
	The character gains the Paranoia aspect.  It should be compelled on occasions
	when the character needs to trust others.  Two of the symptoms of paranoia are
	not trusting party members, or gang-stalking, that is, believing there's some
	shady group that are following the character trying to destroy their lives (maybe
	they are right).
      </p>      
    </td>    
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>5</td><td><bold>Phobia</bold>
      <p>
	The character gains the a phobia aspect.  The GM chooses the object of
	their phobia based on the casters surrounds or what they were thinking of
	when casting.
      </p>
    </td>
    </tablerow>


    <tablerow>
      <td>6</td><td><bold>Mania</bold>
      <p>
	The character gains a Mania aspect for some person or thing, GM determines based
	on the context.  Mania is exhibited by unusual excitement or interest in a subjet.
      </p>
    </td>
    </tablerow>


    <tablerow>
      <td>7</td><td><bold>Schizophrenia</bold>
      <p>
	They gain the Schizophenic aspect.  This aspect may be compelled to force the
	character to see visions and hear voices.  In addition the character has the
	Distracted Condition while they have the Schizophrenic aspect.
      </p>
    </td>  
    </tablerow>

    
    <tablerow>
      <td>8</td><td><bold>Catatonia</bold>
      <p>
	The character gains the Unconscious Condition for a short period, minutes or hours,
	at the discretion of the GM.
      </p>
    </td>
    </tablerow>
</table>
