<!-- included from the tables/near-death-banes file -->
<table>
    <tablecategory>Figure</tablecategory>
    <tablespec>
      <fixed>0.1</fixed>
      <fixed>0.8</fixed>
    </tablespec>    
    <tabletitle>Near Death Table</tabletitle>
    <tablelabel>table:near-death-table</tablelabel>

    <tableheaderrow>
      <td>Roll 2d12</td>
      <td>Result</td>
    </tableheaderrow>
    
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>≤1</td>
      <td><emph>Dying</emph>.  They will be dead at the end of the next
      round unless someone intervenes.  If all else fails they can make a final
      Std 2d12 roll for divine intervention, if they gain a Boon or Bane then
      some god spares them for reasons that the god will make known to the character at
      some time in the near future.  If successful the character gains an aspect reflecting
      their obligation to this deity.  In the case of a Bane the divine intervention
      is from a malicious source seeking to use the character as a pawn in their nefarious
      plans.  The character may reject the intervention in this case.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>2</td>
      <td><emph>Maimed</emph>.  Suffers some permanent disability, <eg/>They have lost
      an eye or a hand, their face has been badly burned etc.  Gain the Checked condition
      and 1d3 hit points.</td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>3-5</td>
      <td><emph>Bleeding Out Fast</emph>. Roll again next round with a -5 cummulative modifier.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>6-8</td>
      <td><emph>Bleeding Out</emph>. Roll again next round with a -3 cummulative modifier.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>9-13</td>
      <td><emph>It doesn't look good</emph>.  Roll again next round.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>14-15</td>
      <td><emph>Out Cold</emph>.  The character gets the Unconscious condition and 1 health.</td>
    </tablerow>
     
    <tablerow>
      <td>16-17</td>
      <td><emph>Coming To</emph>.  Roll again next round with a +3 cummulative modifier.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>18</td>
      <td><emph>Waking Up</emph>.  Roll again next round with a +5 cummulative modifier.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>19-20</td>
      <td><emph>Where am I?</emph>.  Character gains the Dazed condition, the Checked condition and 1 health.</td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>21-22</td>
      <td><emph>A Flesh Wound</emph>.  Heals to 1 health and gains the Dazed condition.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>23</td>
      <td><emph>I'm Fine</emph>.  Heals 3 health.</td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>≥24</td>
      <td><emph>Never Been Better</emph>.  Heals 5 health and gets an additional 10 temporary health.</td>
    </tablerow>
</table>
