<table>
    <tablecategory>FullWidth</tablecategory>
    <tablespec><fixed>0.08</fixed><fixed>0.87</fixed></tablespec>
    <tabletitle>Overcharge Effects Table Part 1</tabletitle>
    <tablelabel>table:{{ doc_name }}-overcharge-effects</tablelabel>

    <tableheaderrow>
      <td>Roll d49</td>
      <td>Overcharge Effect</td>
    </tableheaderrow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>10</td><td>No overcharge effect.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>11</td><td>The caster is sickened by the thaumic energies they have been using.
      Gain the Sick Condition.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>12</td><td>The spell fizzles and material components, if any are destroyed.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>13</td><td>Their is a loud thunderclap.  Any character within <measurement><metric>20m</metric><imperial>60'</imperial></measurement> gains the Deaf condition.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>14</td><td>A weaker version of the spell is cast.  The GM dictates the effects.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>15</td><td>The caster is temporarily possessed by a being from beyond.  They gain the Enraged Condition for 1-3 turns.  They cannot cast spells and must make melee attacks against an enemy.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>16-17</td><td>The GM picks something very strange but which is related to the spells context.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>18</td><td>The caster is thrown <measurement><metric>5m</metric><imperial>15'</imperial></measurement> in a random direction.  Make an Agilty save vs DC 10 or caster is Prone.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>19</td><td>The caster is so effected by the miscast that they speak with a speech impediemnt (lisp or stutter).</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>20</td><td>A creature reaches into this world to try and grab the caster.  The caster is Dazed.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>21</td><td>A sudden and extremely dramatic change in air pressure causes a thunderstorm
      to immediately start.  Remember the effect of rain on spell castering if the caster is
      outside.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>22</td><td>Very effective.  The spell works exceptionally well.  The exact effect is up to the GM but if the spell does damage then it should do maximum damage or double damage.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>23</td><td>The caster slips between the veil that separates this plane and the next.  They are see persistant visions from the other plane.  The caster gains the Distracted condition.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>24</td><td>There is a minor earthquake.  Unstable structures might be destroyed.  Tiles may fall from rooves.  Nearby spell-casters will suspect something may be afoot.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>25</td><td>The caster sees visions too terrible to relate.  They are temporarily blinded.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>26</td><td>The caster glimpses of a hideous creature from beyond.  Roll a Break Check.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>27</td><td>The caster gets a quick look at a hideous creature from beyond.  Roll two Break Checks.  If the character fails these they gain an insanity condition, roll on the insanity table.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>28</td><td>The caster hears disembodied screaming.  Roll a Break Check</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>29</td><td>The caster loses control of the spell and some of their life force is drained.  Any magic die with a face value of 3 or less is exhausted.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>30</td><td>The spell goes badly wrong.  All magic dice used in the spell are exhausted.  The caster gains the Exhausted Condition.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>31</td><td>The casters personality is changed.  They drop a personality based aspect
      and gain a new one.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>32</td><td>Explosion!  All characters adjacent to the caster, but not the caster, suffer 2d6 damage.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>33</td><td>The character is poisoned by the thaumic energies used in their spell.  They gain the Poisoned Condition.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>34</td><td>All the heat is sucked from the area.  Frost and ice form on all surfaces
      making the ground difficult terrain in a radius of <measurement><metric>20m</metric><imperial>60'</imperial></measurement>.  All characters in this radius suffer 1d6 cold damage.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>35</td><td>The caster catches fire!  They must spend an fast action putting out the fire.  They suffer d6 damage.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>36</td><td>Any trees or shrubs in the area become animated by spirits from beyond and
      start attacking those nearby.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>37</td><td>Some piece of the casters equipment is transformed into something unexpected or disappears into a different plane.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>38</td><td>The caster is sucked into a different plane.  They return 1-3 turns later
      near where they disappeared.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>39</td><td>The magical energies prove hard to control.  The effects of the spell are delayed till the end of the round</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>40</td><td>Reroll on this table twice.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>41</td><td>Evil spirits play with peoples minds.  Everyone within <measurement><metric>10m</metric><imperial>30'</imperial></measurement> gains the Paranoia condition.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>42</td><td>Vision.  The caster sees a vision of an important event of the future, or the past, or one of the possible futures.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>43</td><td>The character is transformed by the winds of magic.
      Roll 1d8: 1-3 gain a bulls tail, 4-6 gain a rats tail, 7 gain a wolves tail,
      8 the character gains a set of small horns that sprout from the top of their
      forehead. This will be seen as a sign of malevolent sorcery by witch-hunters
      and peasants.</td>
    </tablerow>
</table>       
