<table compact="true">
    <tablecategory>FullWidth</tablecategory>
    <tablespec><fixed>0.08</fixed><fixed>0.87</fixed></tablespec>
    <tabletitle>Overcharge Effects Table Part 2</tabletitle>

    <tableheaderrow>
      <td>Roll d49</td>
      <td>Aspect</td>
    </tableheaderrow>


    <tablerow>
      <td>44</td><td>One of the characters hands is transformed by the winds of magic.
      Roll 1d8: 1-2 into a bird-like claw, 3-4 a rat-like claw, 5 a crabs pincer, 6-8 a
      suckered tentacle.  This will be seen as a sign of malevolent sorcery by witch-hunters
      and peasants.</td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>45</td><td>One of the characters legs is transformed by the winds of magic.
      Roll 1d8: 1 into a bird-like claw, 2 into a rats claw, 3-4 a goats leg, 5 a wolves leg,
      6-8 a suckered tentacle.  This will be seen as a sign of malevolent sorcery by witch-hunters
      and peasants.</td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>46</td><td>The spell causes a disruption in the barrier between the plans and a minor demon or thing from another plane manages to project itself onto this plane.</td>
    </tablerow>

    <tablerow>
      <td>47</td><td>A cloud of green mephitic vapours roils from the caster in a <measurement><metric>20m</metric><imperial>60'</imperial></measurement> radius.  All characters in that radius must make an endurance check or suffer d6 damage.</td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>48</td><td>
      The GM picks something very strange that is not related to the spells context: flowers
      sprout on the site, the caster temporarily switches bodies with someone nearby,     
    </td>
    </tablerow>
    
    <tablerow>
      <td>49</td><td>A giant rent in space-time appears.  A being of demi-god level power begins
      to work their way into this world.  Hurricane like winds occur due to the sudden dramatic
      air pressure differential.  The caster exhausts all the dice used to cast the spell, the
      caster is transfixed and cannot move their feet.  Take their spell dice without changing
      the face up value of the dice amd put them aside.  They are all exhausted from the casters
      magic pool.  The caster may attempt to ground out a die, if they possess suitable
      equipement, each turn until they are dead or the spells magic pool result drops below its
      overcharge.  In the second a thunderstorms starts.  Hurricane winds make it hard to move.
      and lightning rains down in the area. At the end of the third term the spell drains the
      casters animus magic and the caster is dead.  At the end of the fourth term the creature
      from beyond walks this earth, shutting the portal behind it lest greater creatures follow.
    </td>
    </tablerow>
    <tablelabel>table:{{ doc_name }}-overcharge-effects</tablelabel>
</table>       
