<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<patron>
  <patrontitle>Klazyabolus - Lord of the Fens</patrontitle>
  <patronid>klazyabolus</patronid>
  <patrondescription>           
    <p>
      Klazyabolus sits atop his throne of skulls in the stygian fens of the
      Wyld and plots the downfall of his foes.  A being of great power, banished
      in past eons to the mires of that plane for a transgression
      long since forgotten by most.  
    </p>

    <p>
      His lair is a fetid and ramshackle motte and bailey steading, where he is
      defended and served by the fey denizens of the area who hail him ``Y'cklar
      Y'cklar! Masharal'' - Ruler of all.  Klazyabolus spends his time involving himself
      in political intrigue from afar in an attempt to broker enough power to petition
      the queens of the Wyld to have his banishment lifted.  To this end he frequently
      patrons humans as pawns in the inscrutable machiovellian games he plays.
    </p>


    <p>
      Overtime his powerful magic has warped his form and his mind, through a process
      of thaumic osmosis, he has become in likeness of both mind and body, to resemble
      the inhabitants of his land, with a definite batracian visage: green slimy skin,
      and nictitating eyelids.
    </p>

    
    <figure>
      <img src="./resources/patrons/klazyabolous/the_death_by_erik_blaster-d6oiu1e.png"
	   scale="2.0"/>
    </figure>        

    
    <table>
      <tablecategory>Figure</tablecategory>
      <tablespec>
	<fixed>0.2</fixed>
	<fixed>0.7</fixed>
      </tablespec>
      <tabletitle>Klazyabolous Patron Taint Table</tabletitle>
      
      <tableheaderrow>
	<td>Roll d49</td>
	<td>Overcharge Effect</td>
      </tableheaderrow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>11</td>
	<td>Klazyabolous is displeased at the casters impertinance, disturbing him while eating.  The spell fails.</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>12</td>
	<td>The character gains a Miasmatic Aura that, although undetectable to humans,
	will make dogs, cats and other animals, who are not used to it, extremely uneasy.</td>
      </tablerow>
      
      <tablerow>
	<td>13</td>
	<td>The characters skin is constantly, visibly moist.</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>14-18</td>
	<td>One or two flies constantly circle the caster.</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>21-24</td>
	<td>Skin turns a greenish hue, particularly around the eyes</td>
      </tablerow>
      
      <tablerow>
	<td>25</td>
	<td>Eyes get nictitating membranes.  Character can see well underwater.
	People who observe the character are distinctly uneasy.</td>
      </tablerow>
      
      <tablerow>
	<td>26-27</td>
	<td>The character gains a level of Leap.</td>
      </tablerow>
      
      <tablerow>
	<td>28-29</td>
	<td>The character gains the Prehensile Tongue I monster ability.</td>
      </tablerow>
      
      <tablerow>
	<td>30-49</td>
	<td>Reroll on the overcharge effects table - no patron taint.  Klazyabolous
	is not paying attention.</td>
      </tablerow>
      <tablelabel>table:{{ doc_name }}-awareness</tablelabel>
    </table>
    
  </patrondescription>

  <!--

Commune .. vs Invoke??
More flavourful to have a per patron thing?

-->

  <abilitygroup>

    <abilitygroupinfo>
      <abilitygrouptitle>Patron Abilities</abilitygrouptitle>
      <abilitygroupid>klazyabolous</abilitygroupid>
      <abilitygroupfamily>Magic</abilitygroupfamily>
      <abilitygroupdescription>
	<p>
	  Klazyabolous is a virtuous and generous master, only punishing his
	  servants when the whim takes him.  He bestows his gifts
	  to his servants with magnanimity.
	</p>
      </abilitygroupdescription>
    </abilitygroupinfo>
    

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Invoke Klazyabolous</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>klazyabolous.invoke</abilityid>
    <abilityclass>Non-Combat</abilityclass>
    <keywords><klazyabolus/></keywords>
    <abilityattrmodifiers><attr>Willpower</attr></abilityattrmodifiers>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This first time this spell is cast it must be used to forge
	a pact with Klazyabolous.  If Klazyabolous is not satisfied with the
	result of the pact then he will end the invocation and the caster must
	roll on the miscast table.  If Klazyabolous is pleased with the deal then
	a written pact is formed and signed in blood.  The caster gains a
	Servant of Klazyabolous aspect and the Speak with Amphibians I magic
	ability.
      </p>

      <p>
	Subsequent invocations may be used to ask questions of Klazyabolous.
	However, his patience is limited and he acts in his own
	interests.  He will seldom answer unless he can see a way of furthering
	his own needs.  One way to indicate this is to increase the level of
	subjugation of the character to Klazyabolous by increasing the difficulty
	of the casters Servant of Klazyabolous aspect.
      </p>	
    </abilitydescription>    

    <abilitylevels>
      <abilitylevel>
        <levelnumber>1</levelnumber>
        <successes>3</successes>
        <attempts>1</attempts>
        <check>Magic Pool vs DDC 10</check>
	<overcharge>DC + 4</overcharge>
	<effect>See above</effect> 
        <prereqabilitylevel>magic_school.evocation_1</prereqabilitylevel>	
      </abilitylevel>

      <abilitylevel>
        <levelnumber>2</levelnumber>
        <check>Magic Pool + 2 vs DDC 10</check>
	<overcharge>DC + 5</overcharge>
      </abilitylevel>      
    </abilitylevels>
  </ability>  
  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Batracian Leap</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>klazyabolous.leap</abilityid>
    <abilityclass>Reaction</abilityclass>
    <keywords><klazyabolus/></keywords>
    <abilityattrmodifiers><attr>Willpower</attr></abilityattrmodifiers>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	This magical leap allows the character to jump
	up to <measurement><metric>20m</metric><imperial>60'</imperial></measurement>.
      </p>      
    </abilitydescription>    

    <abilitylevels>
      <abilitylevel>
        <levelnumber>1</levelnumber>
        <successes>3</successes>
        <attempts>1</attempts>
        <check>Magic Pool vs DDC 8</check>
	<overcharge>DC + 4</overcharge>	
      </abilitylevel>

      <abilitylevel>
        <levelnumber>2</levelnumber>
        <check>Magic Pool + 2 vs DDC 7</check>
	<overcharge>DC + 5</overcharge>
      </abilitylevel>      
    </abilitylevels>
  </ability>  

  <ability>
    <abilitytitle>Incorporal Mist</abilitytitle>
    <abilityid>klazyabolous.incorporal_mist</abilityid>
    <abilityclass>Non-Combat</abilityclass>
    <keywords><klazyabolus/></keywords>
    <abilityattrmodifiers><attr>Willpower</attr></abilityattrmodifiers>
    <abilitydescription>
      <p>
	The character transforms into a cloud of green mist.  Their clothes
	and possessions are left behind when this happens.   They can stay in this
	form for up to half an hour.
      </p>
    </abilitydescription>    

    <abilitylevels>
      <abilitylevel>
        <levelnumber>1</levelnumber>
        <successes>3</successes>
        <attempts>1</attempts>
        <check>Magic Pool vs DDC 20</check>
	<overcharge>DC + 6</overcharge>
        <prereqabilitylevel>magic_school.evocation_1</prereqabilitylevel>	
      </abilitylevel>

      <abilitylevel>
        <levelnumber>2</levelnumber>
        <check>Magic Pool + 2 vs DDC 20</check>
	<overcharge>DC + 7</overcharge>
      </abilitylevel>      
    </abilitylevels>
  </ability>  
</abilitygroup>
</patron>
