<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>

  {% from "docs/macro_npcs.xml" import build_npcs with context %}
  
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>The Trial</chaptertitle>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Setup</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	The characters are taken to the courthouse before <bold>Magister Heinz Adelman</bold>.
	(old, fat, bouffant, rosacae).   The court is run by <bold>Scribe Ernst
	Hoffman</bold>, (old, wise, bald, pince nez) constantly making suggestions to the
	magister in sotto voce.  There's a jury
	sitting in a box to one side and a crowd of onlookers ready to cheer any pithy comments.
	There's very few young men as they're mostly off to war or working.  Courts try half
	a dozen cases a day.

	<!--
	Advocate for the Witchhunters Guild, Wigand Lange	
	with the captain of the guard.
	-->
      </p>


      <olist>

	<li>Magister asks for Initial Accusations.  <emph>Shall we get this going then?</emph>
	<olist>
	  <li>Public Prosecutor Otlar Neidhart introduces himself and takes a cheap shot at
	  the characters.  Thin humourless sycophantic
	  man.</li>
	  <li>Establish the identies of the individuals.</li>	
	  <li>Magister <emph>Can we hurry this along.. I am feeling a bit peckish and would
	  like to pot these contemptible rascals before lunch</emph></li>	
	  <li>Ernst Hoffman.. <emph>yes sire .. but first some necessary preliminaries..</emph>
	  The reading of the charges:
	  <list>
	    <li>Disturbing the Peace</li>	          
	    <li>Assault and Battery</li>	          
	    <li>the Murder of Hans Hunolt, Witch Hunter and associates</li>	
	  </list>
	  the penalities are: a fine of 5 silver pieces per for disturbing the piece and
	  death by hanging for the assault and battery and the murders.
	  </li>	
	</olist>
	</li>

	<li>Defendents Plea Guilty or Not Guilty.	
	For people who remain silent .. trial by the weight of his sins (weights placed
	on their chest until they confess).</li>
	
	<li>Prosecutor presents his case..
	Various witnesses..  Characters are allowed to question the witnesses.

	<olist>
          <li>Berthilda Brummer (very old, thick glasses) - "I saw them with my own two eyes." +/-1</li>
	  <li>Hanke Jost - an Affidavit Men in the hire of Yacob Sprenger +/-1  possibly known to the rogue types</li>
	  <li>Ronyon - youth and affadavit man.  Will change sides.  "I came to report
	this incident to your lordship as part of my civic duty, like you majesty."
          +/-1</li>	  
	  <li>Prosecutor will put one of them on the stand and try and get them to turn on the others... +/-?</li>
	  <li>Luther Leonardus (Witch Hunter militia man)- will lie through his teeth (see if the characters can catch him in a contradiction in his story) +/-1</li>
	  <li>Mathias Erdich, the Guard Captain. +/-1</li>
	</olist>
	</li>
		
	<li>Summary remarks... keep it short please.  Remember my lunch.</li>	
	<li>Jury adjourns..  if found guilty
        check is 2d8 with a difficulty of 10 modified by their cross examination performance.

	If found guilty..
	Thrown into prison. <emph>Have them hanged with the rest on St Mael the Elders day.
        (thinking) except of course the young lady.  I can't bear the thought
	of the noose around her young neck .. (pause) In our mercy we will
	have her drowned as an adulteress.. Ernst could you amend the
	record accordingly please.. Right I'm off to lunch, Grundewald
	has a roasting partridge and some fine Aquilonian red waiting for
	me I believe.</emph>
	</li>	
      </olist>

      {{ build_npcs("the_trial.guards") }}

      <p>XXX
      </p>
    </section>
    
  </chapter>  
</book>
