<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  {% set MODULE_NAME = "The Summoning" %}
  {% set MODULE_FNAME = "the_summoning" %}
  {% set GANG_NAME = "" %}
  {% set DEVIL_NAME = "El'Azabat" %}
  {% set DEVIL_ALIAS = "Elizabeth" %}
  {% set DEVIL_ALIAS_SLOW = "El-iz-a-beth" %}
  {% set TOUGH1_NAME = "" %}
  {% set APOTHECARY_NAME = "" %}

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>{{ MODULE_NAME }}</chaptertitle>
    <section>        
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Overview</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Dramatis Personae</subsectiontitle>        

	<descriptions>
	  <term>{{ DEVIL_NAME }}</term>
	  <description>
	    A minor devil
	  </description>

	  <term>{{ APOTHECARY_NAME }}</term>
	  <description>
	    An apothecary.
	  </description>

	</descriptions>
      </subsection>



      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Intro</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  The characters attempt to summon a devil to interogate them for information.
	  The hook the characters receive a document fragment with the devils true name.
	  The paper may contain the 
	  Casters will know that using the devils name they can bind it.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Devils are better to summon than demons.  Demons are not bound by the words or contracts, they are fundamentally untrustworthy.
	  Devils, like the fey, are bound to any words or contracts they sign.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>The Prelude</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Devils are very old, very devious and very cunning.  The first thing the GM should do is determine what information the characters
	  are trying to find, then stall the characters till the next session to allow the GM time to think about what the devil might do.
	  What information the devil might know and be willing to trade.
	</p>	
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Prelude - The Apothecary</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Send the player characters off to the apothecary to buy some ritual spell components (to buy time to think).
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>The Summoning</subsectiontitle>        
	<p>
	  The characters should summon the devil and use a protective circle to contain it.
	</p>

	<p>
	  {{ DEVIL_NAME }} is a minor devil.  The hellplane from which she comes is bitterly cold and empty.  She is driven by
	  two goals, first to feed and second to gather enough souls to open a gate to allow her to physically escape from her 
	  plane of existance.  	She is a collector of souls.  Souls are a form of life magic.  When she has collected
	  enough 
	</p>
      </subsection>

      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Innocence</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  The devils first gambit will be to try and dupe the characters.  The devil will appear as an attractive, buxom, semi-naked
	  young woman (think Frank Frazetta illustraions).   The devil will act surprised and disconcerted to be transported to this place.
	  Saying things like: "Who are you?", "Where am I?", "How did I get here?", and "it's very Cold".  The "girl" should initially
	  project innocence and vulnerability.  As the characters "calm her down" she will start to be suggestive, now projecting 
	  conscious, but subtle sensuality and suggestiveness.  The role now is one of an attractive woman who knows she can often use her
	  looks to get what she wants.
	</p>

	<p>
	  This is of course an act,  The devil is trying to beguile the characters into letting her out.  She speaks with a local accent.
	  If the characters ask her what her name is she'll say {{ DEVIL_NAME_ALIAS }}.  If they tell her name is {{ DEVIL_NAME }} she will
	  explain to them slowly, as if they are simple, that her name is {{ DEVIL_NAME_ALIAS_SLOW }}.  If they ask her about herself she'll
	  say her parents have a farm, but she left to come to the city to make money, and she's working as a dancer.  
	  She'll ask if she can go home.  If the characters offer to banish her she'll say "No, I don't want to go through that again".	  
	  She'll ask if it's safe to leave the circle.  If they say yes she will look at them disbelievingly.  She's trying to get them
	  to break the protective circle.
	</p>

	<p>
	  At some point the characters will break the circle, or the devil will give up on the charade and change to her next strategy.
	</p>	
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Jocular Helpfulness</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  What's the aim here?  See if she can talk them into sit down and 
	  
	  Sure thing what can I do for you?  That's an interesting accent.. is that Hibernian? etc.. trying to get information.
	  How about we make a deal?
	</p>	
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Pleading</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	</p>	
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Gathering Information</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	</p>	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Attacking</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	</p>	
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Bargaining</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Offer something your players desire or need
	  What does the devil want?
	  Agree to the Terms and Conditions
	  State Consequences
	  State Punishments
	  Sign the Deal	  
	</p>	
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>The Contract</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
         up for grabs..	 
         franchise offer
         soul
         information
	 item
	 needful things

	 book 

      attacking
      contract
          - overstate time required .. will use that time for nefarious purposes. (buying peoples souls, eating people)
          - fineprint
          - two copies
             "It's lucky you saw that.. I wonder how that snuck in"
	     - strike through the wrong clause
	     - invisible ink
	     - https://www.reddit.com/r/d100/comments/erqo1t/d100_devils_contract_fine_print/

level 1
Sveenkie
·
4 yr. ago
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
