<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
<chapter>
<chaptertitle>Cold Keep</chaptertitle>
<section>        
<sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>


<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>OverviewX</subsectiontitle>

<p>

Blutburg.. a large, walled and well fortifed northern town.. with a population of 30,000 or so.. with that many again in the surrounding countryside.

  
Saergant Metzger
- retired..
- runs provisions from Blutburg->Cold Keep  (Kalt Halten)
- used to work at cold keep.
- on retainer for Johann Schnee, feeds him information.  Wont let the characters know this though.
- is the source of reports.. but as a commoner his word isnt worth much and he doesnt have any hard evidence.

Cold Keeps
- situated on a hill in a large alluvial river valley.
- Mountainous wooded terrain.
  
  
Manegold Fulcade. 
- hes a raging alcoholic.  Will be drunk at 10am in the morning.
- hes very shrewd politically though.
- running cold keep unmanned to pocket the extra wages. (perception check.. there arent that many soldiers here).
- if the PCs ask about the small number of garrisoned men he will explain that they are manning the watchtower or
on patrol.
- has a small separate force of his own toughs that are pushing people around.
- highly suspicious of newcomers.. if the characters dont take the bait he will ship the pcs off to see
  the frontier and report back.  ``Go tell them that theres nothing to 
  Everyone knows the Orcs dont come into our lands this ealy in the year (flooding rivers?).''
- terrible coward.. will deny the orcs are coming up until the last minute, while his servants are loading
chests of coin onto horses, then will depart.
- PCs might be able to convince the mercenaries to stay and fight.



Quartermaster Volkwin
- toady of Manegold Fulcade.
- if anyone asks suspicious questions of him he will report to Manegold.  Manegold will then have them shipped out of town so he can plan their ambush and murder as they leave the town.


Sergeant Henningh
- Old Detleff (half crazy, trapper) - came back with tales of Orc hordes.  A bunch of cowards cleared off in the night.  Its the talk of the town.
- knows what Manegold Fulcade is up to.
- reticent to speak.
- but hes not happy about it.
- More than happy to show the PCs so they can draw the correct conclusions.
- ``So what made you fresh meat decide to volunteer for border patrol?''


The watchtower.
Theres a more frontier watch post.  Called the watchtower.
Its a four story tower on top of a knoll.  On the top floor theres a signal fire.  
It has a pretty good view of the surrounding countryside.
Theres a sally port on one side of the tower.. it is approachable via a wooden bridge over a gully.  The sally port opens to the tower.. the door has been stoved in.


Jaspar, Bertr창dis and Amalie.
- Encounter Bertr창dis and Amalie. Bertr창dis is the lumberjacks wife, Amalieis the young daughter (1 year) they
are camped.. big tent, fireplace, some tools, chains etc.
- Sergeant Henningh will ask where Jaspar is .. she will direct them nearby.
- Northerner, blonde hair, blue eyes, big as a bear, lumberjack, hes about 22.
- Has two huge draught horses.. named Mercy and Grace.
- Jaspar cuts wood thats used to build stuff for Cold Keep.  There are a few other lumberjacks but they work south of the river.  Jaspar, believes that if the orcs come he will know in time to leave, or that if he cant thats what the gods will.  The horses are used to drag felled trees to the river.  Someone comes along weekly and floats them down the river to cold keep.  Theres a woodmill in cold keep.
- Jaspar will say hes not seen anything himself.  There was a murder of crows rise up to the north.  Its an ill omen.  But he the feeling in the forest has changed.  Hes going to cross the river and work southside tomorrow.  Maybe hes just spooked himself.



orcs and the pass ..
- cross to the watchtower .. its almost empty.
- go on patrol
- meet Jaspar and family.
- orc scouts (Sergeant Henningh will help and might get injured as a damage soak, if hes hurt but not killed maybe Jaspar will carry him to safety).
- EXTRA Rescue - homesteaders, warn Jaspar?
- bridge fight to the sally port for the watchtower.
- the tower part of the watchtower has been overrun.  The guards are trying to take it back and light the fire.. but theyre being over run on the walls.  
- light the signal fire.
- watchtower overrun
- get across the river to cold keep  ... strength 15  (basically wading chest deep) or swimming 9 (must have the skill).
- Manegold will dis them and claim that they are agents from his enemies in the south (hes drunk).  The PCs are only trying to frighten people they should.  All the while his servants will be loading his pack horses with chests.
- Jaspar turns up if he was notified and backs up the characters
- Once the Orcs turn up Manegold will attempt to flee.  He will command his mercenaries to ride out and protect him.
- The PCs might attempt to convince the mercenaries.. appealing to their bravado or accusing them of cowardice is the best approach.. other approaches (like appealing to their humanity wont have a high probability of succeeeding).
- hold the gates of cold keep against the coming orcs
- repel the orcs from the walls.
Get back to Cold Keep (they need to light a signal fire)



Repelling the orcs is a dice pool check...
They start with 2 dice.
+2 for lighting the signal fires
+1 if someone gets across the river
+1 if everyone gets across the river quickly
+1 for saving Jaspar and family.. he turns up on Mercy and backs up the PCs.  Bertr창dis and Amalie are heading south on Grace.   Jaspar has come to warn Cold Keep and to fight.  Jaspar is a mean fighter.
+1 for convincing the mercenaries to stay and fight.


Wnat the PCs to start with 6 - 9 dice
3-4 attempts to storm the walls.

want to lose 2 dice per attack
means we need 6 dice per !
DC 18.

With six dice per roll they have a 50% chance of succeeding.. 
With seven they have an 83% chance of succeeding.
every time they fail do an orcs on walls encounter.  If its the last wave do a Rodgrimm on the walls encounter.

If they fail the orcs over run the walls the townsfolk stream out of the town heading south .. many are killed. 
The PCs can fight to save some more.


</p>


<p>
  manegold flees
  followed by quartermaster
  wave of first attackers... fight on the walls for a bit.
    the outer walls won't hold... evacuate to the inner walls.

    second wave of attackers.. 
  
  orc chief and priest
  jentiliak
  - lantern oil from whaling in the northern ocean.
  - falconet
       need to get it out of storage..
  
</p>

{% set encounter=encounters.get('cold_keep.orc_scouts') %}
{% include "docs/encounter_template.xml" %}

</subsection>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>
