<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  {% set MODULE_NAME = "Lonely Road" %}
  {% set MODULE_FNAME = "lonely_road" %}
  {% set GANG_NAME = "" %}
  {% set LEADER_NAME = "" %}
  {% set TOUGH1_NAME = "" %}
  {% set COWARD_NAME = "Timo" %}

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>{{ MODULE_NAME }}</chaptertitle>
    <section>        
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Overview</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  Witch in the woods.  Will attempt to drug the players, take them
	  into the basement and torture them before killing them and turning
	  them into sausages and jerky.
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Dramatis Personae</subsectiontitle>        

	<descriptions>
	  <term>{{ LEADER_NAME }}</term>
	  <description>
	    Leader of the {{ GANG_NAME }}.  He carries a demon-mark carved on his chest
	    by devil worshippers and is trying to work out how to save his soul before it
	    is too late.
	  </description>

	  <term>{{ TOUGH1_NAME }}</term>
	  <description>
	    Tough psycopath who's looking for a fight.  Plays the bad-cop
	    in any negotiation.
	  </description>

	  <term>{{ COWARD_NAME }}</term>
	  <description>
	    This guy is looking out for his own skin.  Plays the good-cop
	    in any negotiation.
 	  </description>
	</descriptions>
      </subsection>



      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Intro</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  {{ LEADER_NAME }} approaches the party on a deserted road.  He is a big man
	  but he seems down on his luck and as he talks he will give off an air of
	  despair and despondency.  At first he is friendly and helpful.  Providing
	  information if he knows it and warning the group that there are
	  devil-worshippers and robbers in the area, and that there rumours of accurse'd
	  creatures in the woods.  Finally he asks them for food.  If they give him food
	  he will be better disposed towards them should the robbers be victorious.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>The Negotiation</subsectiontitle>
	<p>	  
	  After {{ LEADER_NAME }} has finished appraising the characters threat
	  he calls his men out of the bushes.  The thieves will begin asking for
	  all the characters stuff and will negotiate down to food and some decent
	  amount of money.
	</p>	
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>The Fight</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  The robbers will put up a half hearted fight and flee into the woods in a
	  number of directions if they feel they are losing.  {{ COWARD_NAME }} will be
	  the first to flee if he is still alive.
	</p>

	{% set encounter=encounters.get('lonely_road.robbers') %}
	{% include "docs/encounter_template.xml" %}	
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Resolution</subsectiontitle>        
	<p>
	  If the robbers are victorious they will take the characters weapons, money
	  and food.  If anyone is wearing man-sized light armour they will take that as
	  well.  If the players gave {{ LEADER_NAME }} food at the start then he will
	  let them keep their weapons. 
	</p>

	<p>
	  If the PCs look like winning and the robbers start to flee then {{ LEADER_NAME }}
	  will start his transformation.
	</p>
      </subsection>



      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Transformation</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  {{ LEADER_NAME }} once dropped will clutch at his chest and tear at his shirt
	  revealing the demon mark which will start to bleed profusely.

	  transform into a demonic creature.
	</p>
	
	{% set encounter=encounters.get('lonely_road.accursed_man') %}
	{% include "docs/encounter_template.xml" %}
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Reward</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  The robbers are carrying a small amount of money and food and some second
	  rate weapons: clubs, short-bows.  {{ LEADER_NAME }} has a small bound manuscript
	  of prayers that he has found - he seeks redemption - from which a clerical type
	  might gain a spell of the GM's choosing.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
