<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>The Church of Mithras</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	The Church of Mithras Invictus dominates the empire and the numbers of its followers dwarf those
	of other Gods in Westenreich.   It is the largest bureaucracy in the west and is one of
	the dominant powers there, arguably being second in political power to the nobility.
	The church is currently lead by Hochbischof St Benno Beichtvater I, Protector of the People. It encompasses
	many supplicant orders including: The Ordo Sacredos, the priesthood; The High Polity,
	the bureaucratic, operational and governance order of the Church; The Champions of Mithras, the military
	wing of the church; and The Order of Witch Hunters.   Related organizations, not officially controlled
	by the Church include The Lesser Brothers of Saint Ansgar, commonly known as the Black Coats, and the
	Penitent Brotherhood.  
      </p>

      <p>
	The teachings of the church are collected in the Book of Light.  It is a collection of writings
	with a long introduction that describes the history of the church, nine Great Chapters that
	detail in depth the Great Ideals a follower of Mithras should aspire to, and a number of other
	minor chapters whose inclusion or exclusion from the Book are the matter of often heated discussion
	amongst the clergy, and sometime heretical uprisings.
      </p>

      <p>
	The Church uses as its holy symbol a pictograph of the Sun, or the Sun rising behind a lion,
	or an enneagon, that is, a nine sided polygon, or any of the stellations of that polygon, <ie/>
	nine pointed geometric stars.
      </p>

      <p>
	The nine great virtues or Mithras are:
	<olist>
	  <li>Justice or Fairness,</li>
	  <li>Abnegation, Moderation or Self-Denial,</li>
	  <li>Purity of Spirit</li>
	  <li>Vigilance or Watchfulness for Enemies</li>
	  <li>Concustodio, or Protection</li>
	  <li>Faithfulness</li>
	  <li>Entelechy, Arete or Excellence</li>
	  <li>Prudence, Acumen or Wisdom</li>
	  <li>Humility</li>
	</olist>
      </p>

      <p>
	Followers of Mithras celebrate a number of holy days in the year, including Candlemass,
	when thanks is given to Mithras for showing the way, the solstices: Sommertag and Kaltertag,
	and the equinoxes.  There are a large number of Saint's days that are less universally
	celebrated, chief amongst these is St Ansgars Day or Ansgarstag.	
      </p>
      
      <p>
	The church has released a large number of dictates, holy instructions, to its clergy.  Different
	orders within the church decide as a group whether the dictates should apply to their order based on
	near endless theological debate, and then usually tempered with a dose of pragmatism.
	There are currently fifty three lesser dictates, such as Hare Sunday, which specifies that lagomorphs
	must not be eaten on Mithras' Day, <ie/> Sundays, as Rabbits are beloved unto Mithras.
	The minor dictates are more honoured in the breach than the observance  The three great dictates are
	the Mendicant Dictat, the Asanguineous Dictat and the  Fides Dictat.
      </p>
          
      <p>
	The <defn>Asanguineous Dictat</defn> states that its members are <emph>forbidden from causing blood
	to flow</emph>.  After much internal debate between esteemed hagiographic scholars it has been decreed
	that the emphatic nature of the word <emph>flow</emph> in the dictat was intentional, and therefore
	causing some blood to spatter or drip would be acceptable in the service of the church.
	In addition, it is an important prerequisite of a breach of the Dictat that the flow of blood occur as
	the result of direct action by the church member, or Recta Actio.  In practice, <emph>adherence to
	this dictat is considered be honoured if the church member does not use edged weapons, any weapons
	tagged as Asanguineous comply</emph>.
      </p>

      <p>	
	The <defn>Mendicant Dictat</defn> states that <emph>thou shalt go among the people as an equal and
	be as one with the poor</emph>.  This is widely taken to mean that followers of the church
	should own very little.   The broader priesthood follows this dictat, though there has been an
	amendment pushed through by a number of the bishops that allows church members to <emph>hold wealth
	in the people's stead</emph>.
      </p>
      
      <p>	
	The <defn>Fides Dictat</defn> hinges on an obscure passage in the Book of Light in the chapter
	on faithfulness that states that <emph>thous shall trust in Mithras to protect thee</emph>.
	This is interpreted by the Penitent Brotherhood to mean that armour cannot be worn, as doing so
	would be to demonstrate a lack of faith in Mithras.  The rest of the church fairly unanimously
	regards this to be madness of the highest order.
      </p>      
    </section>    
  </chapter>
</book>

