<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  { % set MODULE_FNAME = "reichs_pferdemeister" % }
  { % set MODULE_NAME = "Reichs Pferdemeister" % }
  
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Reichs Pferdemeister</chaptertitle>
    <section>        
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>


      <subsection>
      	<subsectiontitle>Original</subsectiontitle>

	<list>
	  <li>Situated in Aschburg</li>
	  <li>Back taxes and Ottmar Fulcade</li>
	  <li>Weather damage</li>
	</list>

      </subsection>



      <subsection>
      	<subsectiontitle>Current</subsectiontitle>


	<p>
	  Over the last six months nothing of great note has happened.  You have gone on goose chases, and dead end investigations,
	  spent some time fixing the Reichs, and some time in study.
	</p>
	
	<list>
	  <li>The place is largely run by Yohann (looks like Jürgen Prochnow, Manager) and Apollonia Pflüger (Cook and Manager) and their
	  three teenage children Salomea, Ottilie and Caspar.</li>
	  <li>Adalfrit .. blonde hayley mills type,  is the bar maid, and deals with customers</li>
	  <li>The orphans Matilde, Holda, Noldil, and Baltzer do odd jobs, are provided room and board, and get reading and writing
	  lessons on Sundays from Apollonia (who is quite devout)</li>
	  <li>Roof is mostly fixed (replaced), there's a tarpaulin over a small section of old thatching that's functional but will be replaced.</li>
	  <li>Floors 1-3 of the main building are habitable, but only half of the third floor is furnished and whitewashed.</li>	  
	  <li>The mews is completely operational and functional</li>
	  <li>Occupancy rate has picked up a little.</li>
	  <li>The kitchen and beerhaus are running</li>
	  <li>A local brewer Ulf Reininghaus and his son Dietrich visits to manage the beer brewing</li>
	  <li>A young farrier Ernestus (Ern) Steinner runs a business and pays rent out of the smithy</li>
	  <li>Yosh and Shtan Shmenge visit to pick up the night soil around breakfast time.</li>
	</list>			
      </subsection>
	



      <subsection>
      	<subsectiontitle>Future Problems</subsectiontitle>

	<list>
	  <li>Accusations of prostitution</li>
	  <li>Pressure from the local thieves guild for protection money.</li>
	</list>	
      </subsection>	
      
      <!-- Reichs Pferdemeister -->
      <!-- Inherits Muse -->
      <!-- Orphanage -->
      <!--    Heidi. -->



      <!--  Map of the Reichs Pfedermeister. -->
      <!--  Buttery -->
      <!--  Larder -->
      <!--  Chambers -->
      <!--  Stables -->
      <!--     - Farrier -->
      <!--  Brewery -->


      <!-- baby -->
      <!--   = needs a wet nurse. -->

      <!-- Gunter -->
      <!--    - Old Priest of Mithras -->
      <!--    - Blinded -->
      <!--    - Has the vision -->

      <!-- Ernko -->
      <!--   - fey touched -->
      <!--   - lives in the sewers -->
      <!--   - big hairy man-beast -->
      <!--   - gentle and empathetic. -->

      <!--   plenty of low price accomodation,... plague means houses are empty. -->
            
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
