<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<book>
  <titlepage>
    <vspace>2</vspace>
    <title>Malleus Deum</title>
    <vspace>10</vspace>
    <img src="./resources/dragon_title.png" scale="0.3"/>
    <vspace>20</vspace>
    <!-- <subtitle>Igitur qui desiderat pacem, praeparet bellum.</subtitle> -->
    <vspace>2</vspace>
    <author>Blaize A. Rhodes, and</author>
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <author>William F. Rhodes</author>
  </titlepage>
  
  <tableofcontents/>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Introduction</chaptertitle>

    <section>    
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>GM</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>NPC</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Player Character</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Non-Player Character</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Character</indexentry>
        Malleus~Deum is a fantasy pen and paper, tabletop, role-playing game (RPG).
        In Malleus Deum one player assumes the role of Game Master or <defn>GM</defn>
        and plays the part of a narrator in a collaborative story.  Other 
        players adopt the role of individual people within the story, called
        Player Characters.  All the other people, and any monsters within the story
        are controlled by the GM and are referred to as Non-Player Characters or 
        <defn>NPCs</defn>.  We  use the term  
        <defn>Character</defn> to denote the set of both player characters and non-player
        characters.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Difficulty</subentry></indexentry>
        Each player character is described by a Character Sheet. Any narrative decisions 
        of moment within the game are made by <emph>Making Checks</emph> which involves 
        rolling dice, adding any bonuses from the character sheet, and comparing the result
        to a <defn>Difficulty</defn> level
        <equation>
          <line>Check:</line>
          <line>Dice + Bonus <geqqsymbol/> Difficulty</line>
        </equation>
        The details of how this all fits together, how to make a character sheet, how to 
        make checks, and more is covered in the next few chapters.
      </p>

      <figure position="!b">
        <img src="./resources/albrecht_durer_nativity.png" scale="0.4"/>
      </figure>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Motivation and Design</sectiontitle>      
      <p>
        This game has the following design goals:
      </p>

      <olist>
        <li>
          <p>
            The authors believe that the big name RPGs are showing their age.  Dungeons
            and Dragons is now 40 years old.  While there are a large number of indie rpgs
            that have explored interesting new rpg design elements, Dungeons and Dragons
            has remained relatively static, its development ossified by negative feedback
            to changes from its large existing fan-base.  These rules represent a response
            to this state of affairs.  
          </p>    
          
          <p>
            Malleus Deum is an attempt at a <emph>modern</emph> rule set.  It  
            tries to integrate advances in RPG rule design into an otherwise traditional RPG 
            rules system.  Specifically we try to include an Aspect-like mechanic from FATE, 
            linear magic-users like 13th age and Dnd5e, a strategic initiative phase from Dr 
            Who to encourage non-combat resolutions, simple unified resolutions, morale,
            and adding benefits and complications to dice results.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            In this game we are trying to deemphasize combat.  Not remove it.  But
            take an opportunity to try and provide rules that will allow the GM
            to shine the light on other parts of the game: negotiation, morale,
            fleeing and pursuit, investigation and personal development.
          </p>

          <p>
            It's nice to have a change in pace and scenery.  We have tried to design a
            game where combat plays a major role, but other aspects of the game, such
            as role-playing, negotiation, non-lethal combat, and investigation, are also
            a possibility.
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <p>
            We feel it is important for users of the game that the game license allow people
            to contribute to the game on their own terms and have, therefore, released the
            game under the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0, which is available 
            online.  In a nutshell, you are free, to: 
            <list>
              <li>Share — to copy, distribute and transmit the work, to</li>
              <li>Remix — to adapt the work, and to</li>
              <li>Make commercial use of the work</li>
            </list>
            
            Under the following conditions:
            <list>
              <li>Attribution — You must attribute the work in the manner specified by 
              the author, but not in any way that suggests that they endorse you 
              or your use of the work.  
              </li>
            </list>
          </p>

	  <p>
	    All creative commons licenses require attribution.  We suspect it may have
	    something to do with establishing the provenance of the license.
	  </p>	    
        </li>      
        

        <li>
          <p>
            Modular and Customizable: Our goal is that you should be able to include the bits 
            you want, exclude the bits you do not, customize whatever you like, add whatever 
            house rules you like, then build your own set of rule books and modules and
            print them.
          </p>

          <p>
            Modularity also makes maintaining balance in an evolving game easier
            as some parts of the system can be tweaked without effecting other parts.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Moderately heavy-weight rules complexity means that the rules are a little more 
            complicated than, for example, FATE, FUDGE, Basic Dnd, or Call of Cthulhu and a 
            little less complicated than say DnD4e.   Combat needs to be easy enough that 
            GMs can throw challenging encounters together on the fly.  But the rules for 
            character progression need to be rich enough to capture and keep the imagination
            of the players.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Geared to a low magic setting.  At high level magic becomes difficult to GM
            with a myriad of unforeseen interactions and unintended consequences.  In the
            authors opinion, there are also problems with game balance in high fantasy
            settings.  As George Martin said: ``If you look at The Lord of the Rings, what
            strikes you, it certainly struck me, is that although the world is infused with
            this great sense of magic, there is very little onstage magic. So you have a
            sense of magic, but it's kept under very tight control.''.  We also refer the
            interested reader to Sandersons Rules of Magic.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Malleus Deum is designed specifically for fantasy settings.  We feel that generic
	    role playing systems do not fit any milieu particularly well - they are the jacks
	    of all trades and masters of none.
          </p>
        </li>
	
        <li>
          <p>
            We hope to develop this game via a process of gradual incremental improvement.
	    There is a constraint on the corporate model of RPG development where each new
	    version of the rules has to be significantly different from previous versions
	    otherwise they cannot justify the prices they charge for the new books or resell
	    you the same modules.  An open source model has no such constraints.  We hope
	    that an open approach will allow a slow process of identifying problem areas with
	    the rules and fine-tuning those rules in a slow and incremental process.
          </p>	  
        </li>


        <li>
          <p>
	    The default milleau for the game draws elements from the standard fantasy sources:
	    Lord of the Rings, Conan the Barbarian, Dungeons and Dragons, and Warhammer and
	    also some slightly unusual sources: Jim Butchers Dresden Files, Charles Strosses
	    Laundry Files and Lovecraft.  
          </p>
        </li>
        
      </olist>

      <p>
	We hope you enjoy the game.
      </p>

      <!--
          <figure position="!b">
          <img src="./resources/werewolf2.jpg" scale="0.7"/>
          </figure>
      -->
    </section> 
    
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Character Generation</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:character_generation</label>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Character Overview</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Character</indexentry> 
        Player Characters are described by:
        <list>
          <li>
            <indexentry>Primary Attributes</indexentry>
            A set of <defn>Primary Attributes</defn>: Strength, Endurance, Agility, Speed,  
            Luck, Willpower, and Perception.
          </li>
          <li>
            <indexentry>Secondary Attributes</indexentry>
            A set of <defn>Secondary Attributes</defn>: Armour Class, Movement, Initiative,
            and Experience
          </li>
          <li>Two Hit Point stats: Stamina and Health.</li>
          <li>Three Dice Pool stats: Magic, Resolve and Fate.</li>
          <li>An Archetype and a Level.  The Archetype describes the characters race 
          and their class or type.  The Level describes how advanced, how powerful, 
          the character is.</li>
          <li>A set of Aspects. Aspects are statements that describe the characters 
          personality, relationships, philosophy or appearance.   They 
          have effects within the game, e.g: Silent Outcast, Naive Appeaser, Dipsomaniac,
          Hairy Bastard, Declared vengeance against Elogh King of the Goblins.</li>
          <li>A set of Abilities, e.g: Sweeping Blow, Arcane Lore, Pick Locks, 
          and</li>
          <li>Some optional description about the character. A back-story for the character, 
          and any tertiary statistics the player might want to include: 
          Height, Weight, Age, Hair Colour and so on.</li>
        </list>
        The characters attributes and aspects are used to determine whether the player 
        can successfully perform certain actions within the world.  Checks are described
        further in Section<ref>sec:checks</ref> on page<pageref>sec:checks</pageref>. 
        Steps to create a character can be found in Section<ref>sec:character_creation</ref> 
        on page<pageref>sec:character_creation</pageref>.
      </p>

      <playexample>
        <img src="./resources/dwarf_portrait.png" scale="0.6">
          Young Dourli, Dwarven Shield Guard
        </img>
      </playexample>
    </section>

    
    <section>      
      <sectiontitle>Primary Attributes</sectiontitle>      
      <p>
        Every character shares a set of primary attributes.  Attributes are 
        numeric descriptions of a characters capabilities.  Initially they are values 
        between six and twelve inclusive.
      </p>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Strength</subsectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Strength</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Athletics<see>Strength</see></indexentry>
        <p>Represents the characters brute physical strength.  Strength checks are used to 
        bend bars, open doors and to lift heavy objects.  Strength modifies melee damage and 
        the characters Stamina.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Endurance</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          The characters ability to handle physical stress.  If a character has a high 
          Endurance it indicates that they are healthy and tough.
          Endurance is used to oppose poisons, resist exhaustion, diseases, the cold, and 
          modifies the characters Health.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Agility</subsectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Agility</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Acrobatics<see>Agility</see></indexentry>
        <p>
          The characters ability to move easily; their nimbleness, athleticism and dexterity.
          Agility modifies the characters Armour Class.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Speed</subsectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Speed</indexentry>
        <p>
          Speed represents how physically fast the character is.  Speed effects the 
          character's Initiative Modifier and their movement rate.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Luck</subsectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Luck</indexentry>
        <p>
          A measure of how fortunate a player is.  Luck modifies a character's initial Fate
          Pool.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Willpower</subsectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Willpower</indexentry>
        <p>Willpower is the characters intestinal fortitude, their strength of character,
        commitment and firmness of mind.  Willpower contributes to a character's Resolve
        which is used to determine if the character breaks and flees from an encounter.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Perception</subsectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Searching<see>Perception</see></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Spot Hidden<see>Perception</see></indexentry>

        <p>
          The character's awareness, acumen and insight.  Perception represents your 
          attentiveness to detail and your unflagging vigilance.  In game this value is used 
          socially, for reading people and detecting underhanded motives.  Perception modifies
          the character's Awareness which is used both for surveying the surrounds for 
          potential avenues of attack, and reduces the likelihood of being surprised.
          Perception is used for searching.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <figure position="b">
        <img src="./resources/footer2.png" scale="1.4"/>
      </figure>

    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Secondary Statistics</sectiontitle>
      <descriptions>
        
        <term>Armour Class:</term>
        <description>
          A representation of how difficult a character is to hit.  A character may be harder 
          to hit because they are wearing armour or carrying a shield or even because of the
          use of misdirection and guile.
        </description>

        <term>Initiative:</term>      
        <description>
          Initiative effects turn order during combat.
        </description>

        <term>Experience:</term>
        <description>
          Is a numeric value that represents the development of the characters abilities
          due to the conflicts, trials and tribulations the character has had to face.
        </description>

        <term>Movement:</term>
        <description>
          Determines the number of squares a character can move when playing 
          on a grid.  GMs should use this value as an indication of the characters
          speed across the ground during narrative play.
        </description>        
      </descriptions>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Dice Pool Statistics</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        There are three dice pool statistics: Resolve, Magic and Fate which we discuss
        here.  But first we will briefly mention the dice notation used in this game.
      </p>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Dice Notation</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          All the non-dice pool mechanics use the standard RPG dice mechanics, <eg/>
          3d6 + 2 means roll three six sided dice add two to the dice total to get a
          number.
        </p>

        <p>
          For dice pools, denoted <dpool/>, the character adds and removes dice to
          their dice pool during the course of the game and during character creation.
          The characters initial dice pool statistics are specified by the characters
          archetype, <eg/> 3<d6/>, and may be modified by character ability bonuses,
          <eg/> +1<d4/>.  Refresh rates for dice pool are the rate at which the character
          recouperates dice back into their dice pool and are specified as some number of
          dice of any type, <eg/> +2<dany/> means that the character recovers two dice into
          their dice pool.  These dice may be of any type that was already in the dice pool,
          <eg/> if a character has a dice pool of 2<d6/> + 1<d4/> and they exhaust their
          <d4/> when they rest they can only recover +1<d4/> taking them back up to their
          starting pool size.

          <indexentry>Dice Pool Notation</indexentry>      
        </p>

        <p>
          So attributes like Strength and statistics like Stamina, will appear as a
          number on character sheets, while Dice Pool statistics, like Resolve, will
          appear on as a set of dice, <eg/> 3<d6/> + 1<d4/>.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>The Dice Pool Statistics</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  Characters have three dice pool statistics.  They start the game with a full pool.
	  During the game they may lose dice from those pools by making dice pool checks,
	  and they may return dice to the pools by resting.  We describe how to
          use dice pools to make checks in Section<ref>sec:dice_pool</ref> on
          page<pageref>sec:dice_pool</pageref>.
	</p>
	
        <descriptions>
          <term>Resolve:</term>
          <description>
            <p>
              Resolve is a dice pool used during combat that measures the characters will to 
              stand and fight, their mental well-being, morale, fear, shock, sanity and 
              determination.
            </p>
          </description>

          <term>Magic:</term>
          <description>
            Casting magic uses a dice pool and many special rules described in
            Section<ref>ch:magic</ref> on page<pageref>ch:magic</pageref>.
          </description>

          <term>Fate:</term>
          <description>
            <indexentry>Fate Pool</indexentry>       
            Characters have a <defn>Fate Pool</defn> that represents the players
	    manifest destiny.  
          </description>
        </descriptions>
      </subsection>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Hit Points</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        A characters physical well-being is represented by two sets of 
        statistics: Stamina and Health.  Characters can take damage to either of
        these stats as the result of a single attack, however it is 
        more usual that attacks cause one type of damage.  Usually the character will
        take damage to stamina first and then health.  Stamina represents minor wounds
        and exhaustion, and heals quickly.  Health represents the actual physical status
        of the character and heals slowly.   Both of these hit point stats have a
	minimum value of zero, they cannot be negative numbers.
      </p>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Stamina</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Stamina</indexentry>
          Stamina is the characters ability to take superficial damage, bruising, 
          flesh wounds, scratches, glancing blows, near misses and their aerobic fitness.  
        </p>

        <p>
          The first time damage reduces Stamina below zero during an encounter the character
          becomes Bloodied <emph>and</emph> any remaining damage is removed from the characters
	  health.  See Section<ref>sec:non-lethal-combat</ref> on
	  page<pageref>sec:non-lethal-combat</pageref> for more information on non-lethal
	  combat and becoming bloodied.
        </p>

        <p>
          <indexentry>Healing <subentry>Stamina</subentry></indexentry>
          Damage to stamina leaves the character breathless, a little stunned, bruised and 
          battered but not physically too badly hurt.  Characters regain Stamina at their
          Stamina Rest Rate every short rest.
        </p>    
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Health</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          <indexentry>Health</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Zero Health</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Healing<subentry>Health</subentry></indexentry>
          Health is the characters brawn, their physical capacity to take damage.
          When a character reaches zero health they are effectively too hurt and too weak 
          to defend themselves or do anything and are in danger of dying.  Character death
	  is covered in Section<ref>sec:death</ref> on
	  page<pageref>sec:death</pageref>.  It takes time to restore health. The character
	  gains Health back at their Rest Rate when they Sleep.
        </p>        
      </subsection>
      

      <playexample>
        <p>
          Dourli, our amiable dwarven friend has somehow managed to find himself
          in a brawl with some of the town's thugs.  He punches one of the thugs in the face
          and rolls 7 Stamina Damage.  The thug has only 5 Stamina remaining so his Stamina 
          is reduced to 0, his Health is reduced by 2 and the thug has to make a break check.
          He rolls poorly and flees the fight.
        </p>
      </playexample>
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Abilities</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Skill Points</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Abilities</indexentry>     
        Each character has a set of <defn>Abilities</defn> that 
        allow them to perform actions within the game.  Abilities are bought 
        using skill points as part of character creation and when the characters level 
        increases.  There are four types of <defn>Skill Points</defn>:
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        <term>Lore<lore/></term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Skill Points<subentry>Lore</subentry></indexentry> 
          represents the ``book-learning'' a character has received, how much knowledge
          they have accumulated.  Lore is used to purchase skills like Antiquarian,
	  Natural History, Alchemy, and the like.  
        </description>

        <term>Martial<martial/></term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Skill Points<subentry>Martial</subentry></indexentry> 
          represents combat related physical skills, e.g. Axe Strike, Shield Block.
        </description>

        <term>General<general/></term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Skill Points<subentry>General</subentry></indexentry> 
          represents physical skills learned, or trade-craft: Smith, 
          Animal Handling, Hunting and so on.
        </description>

        <term>Magical<magical/></term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Skill Points<subentry>Magical</subentry></indexentry> 
          represents occult and theological related skills and spells.
        </description>
      </descriptions>     

      <p>
        A characters initial skills are determined by his or her archetype and by using a 
        point-buy system.  The characters archetype assigns a number of skill points 
        for each of the four different skill point types.  During character creation the 
        player chooses which skills or abilities they would like their character to have 
        and pays the purchase price for that skill in skill points.  Skills and 
        abilities are discussed further in Chapter<ref>ch:abilities</ref> on 
        page<pageref>ch:abilities</pageref>.
      </p>

    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Archetypes</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Archetype</indexentry>     
        Each character has an archetype.  An <defn>Archetype</defn> is a combination of a 
        race and a class, for example a character might choose to be a Dwarven Shield 
        Warrior or a Halfling Rover.  Archetypes define which abilities and skills 
        a character may have or learn and how hard it is for them to acquire that ability.  
      </p>
      
      <design>
        Archetypes are indivisible because it makes them more modular and allows us to balance 
        one archetype without effecting existing archetypes.
      </design>
      
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Level</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Level</indexentry>     
        Each character has a level which represents how much experience the characters has.
        The character's level usually starts at one and increases when the 
        character has accumulated enough experience. 
      </p>

      <p>
        Experience is measured using experience points (XP) which are awarded when the
        character achieves goals within the narrative.  The number of XP required to
        increase in level is determined by the character's archetype.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Aspects</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        Aspects are descriptions about a characters personality, their relationships or 
        their appearance that tie those descriptions to the game mechanics and allow checks 
        to be made against them.  Aspects are defined in great detail in chapter 
        Chapter<ref>ch:aspects</ref> on page<pageref>ch:aspects</pageref>.  We describe the 
        process by which aspects are assigned to new characters in
        Section<ref>sec:character_creation</ref> on character creation.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Background</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        Players may create a background or back-story for their character.  At least 
        some of the players background should be fleshed out at character creation time.  The 
        background helps to tie characters to one another and to give them a purpose and a 
        feeling for how they fit in the world.
      </p>
    </section>


    {% include "fragment_character_creation.xml" %}

  </chapter>



  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Checks</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Making Checks <label>sec:checks</label></sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Check</indexentry>     
        In this chapter we describe <emph>Checks</emph>.  Checks are the core mechanic of
        the game.  Checks are used to determine whether a character
        can do things, like climbing a wall, closing a protective circle, or jumping a
        horse over a fence.   

        In order for a player's character to perform a challenging action they
        must make a <defn>Check</defn> which involves rolling some dice, possibly adding a
        modifier and determining whether the total of the roll and modifier is greater than
        some difficulty, if so the check succeeds, otherwise it fails.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        There are two varieties of check: Std 2d8 Checks, and Dice Pool Checks.
        These determine what dice are used in the check.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Standard Checks</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Standard Check</indexentry>     
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Standard</subentry></indexentry>
        Standard Checks are the simplest and most common check.
        In order to make a <defn>Standard Check</defn> or <defn>Std 2d8</defn> the player
        rolls 2d8, adds any relevant bonus, and the check succeeds if the total dice result
        rolled is greater than or equal to the task's difficulty.  The <defn>Difficulty</defn>
        is a number that represents how hard it is to perform the task at hand. 
        <equation>
          <line>Standard Check aka Std 2d8:</line>
          <line>2d8 + Bonus <geqqsymbol/> Difficulty</line>
        </equation>
      </p>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Doubles Are Special</subsectiontitle>        
        <p>
          <indexentry>Benefit</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Consequence</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Standard Check<subentry>Benefit</subentry></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Standard Check<subentry>Consequence</subentry></indexentry>       
          There are certain special results that, when rolled on the Std 2d8 Checks, 
          trigger unusual effects, granting  either a <defn>Benefit</defn> or 
          a <defn>Consequence</defn> to the character, as follows:
        </p>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Double 1s</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            Is always an automatic failure.  In addition the character
            receives a significant consequence.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Double 3s, 5s and 7s</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            If the player rolls any other odd double result then their character
            receives a consequence.  
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Double 8s</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            Is always an automatic success.  In addition the character
            receives a significant benefit.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Double 2s, 4s and 6s</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            If the player rolls any other even double result then their 
            character receives a benefit.  
          </p>
        </subsubsection>


	<p>
	  In short, doubles are special, double odds are bad, double evens are good.	  
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Benefits and Consequences</subsectiontitle>
        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Benefits</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            Whether the check succeeds or not, through skill or luck, the character 
            has gained some advantage in the check.  When the character gains a benefit
            the GM may describe the benefit or may allow the player to call the result, 
            describing the result of the check to the rest of the table.  The player is 
            allowed to add some minor advantageous secondary effect to the result.  For 
            example, the opponent could be pushed back, drop the scroll they are carrying, or 
            be forced to make a break check.  As always the GM is the final arbiter of 
            whether a players call is reasonable and he may temper the results of the success, 
            as he chooses.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Consequences</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            Something has gone wrong.  The GM should describe some additional bad 
            outcome for the check or roll on one of the failure tables for inspiration.  
            For example, the character may have struck with the flat of the blade 
            (requiring the weapon to make a save), they may have lost their footing, 
            left themselves open to attack or dropped some item they were carrying.
            In other words, some adverse affect applies.  The GM should decide 
            on an appropriate consequence for the character, or roll on
            one of the blunder tables for inspiration.  
          </p>

	  
        </subsubsection>

        <playexample>
          <p>
            Dourli has to make a quick getaway from a burning stable surrounded by 
            a crossbow wielding gang.  The one horse inside the stable is panicking
            because of the fire.  The GM decides that the task has a difficulty of 14, so 
            Dourli must roll a 14 or more in order to get the horse under control.  Dourli 
            doesn't have Horsemanship or Animal Husbandry but he does have a fairly high 
            strength.  Dourli attempts to control the horse using strength.  Dourli 
            has a strength of 12 and so gets a bonus to his role of +3.  Dourli rolls a 
            pair of fives on his 2d8 for a total of 10 and adds the 3 to get 13 which isn't 
            enough to make the 14 required to control the horse.   In addition, because he 
            rolled double odds he suffers a consequence.  The GM declares that the horse 
            bolts, smashing through the burning stable doors and running into the night.
          </p>
        </playexample>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Dice Pool Check<label>sec:dice_pool</label></sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Dice Pool Check</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Dice Pool</subentry></indexentry>
        Dice pools  represent some finite resource that will run out if overused,
        <eg/> Magic, Fate and Resolve.  When the player has to make a dice pool check
        they choose <emph>however many dice they want</emph> from their dice pool and
        roll them to try and get a result within a certain range.
        <equation>
          <line>A Dice Pool Check succeeds if:</line>
          <line>Difficulty <leqqsymbol/> Dice Result &lt; Over-Charge</line>
        </equation>
      </p>

      <p>
        Some Dice Pool Checks may not have an Over-Charge value.  But if the check has an
        overcharge and the player rolls greater than or equal to the overcharge then they
        succeed, but some bad over-charge effect occurs.  If they roll under the Difficulty
        then they fail.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <indexentry>Dice Pool Check<subentry>Exhaustion</subentry></indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Dice Pool Exhaustion</subentry></indexentry>
        None of the special Benefit/Consequence rules for Std Checks apply to dice pool
        checks.  However, when a dice rolls a one, that dice that dice is said to be
        <defn>Exhausted</defn> and is remove from the dice pool.  For character dice pools
        like Fate, Magic and Resolve the dice pools will have a rest rate which allows
        the player to return dice to his dice pool over time or when certain events occur.
        For magical items and other dice pool checks the loss might be permanent.  Exhaustion
        only applies to Dice Pool Checks, not Std 2d8 Checks.
      </p>

      <p>
        A characters dice pools are defined by their archetype, level and skills.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Types of Check</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        There are many different types of Check.  When choosing which one to use
        the rule of thumb is use the check most specific to the task at hand.  We describe
        the types of check here in decreasing order of specificity; so another apporach
        is to pick the first check that applies from the following list.
      </p>     

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Ability Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          The most common type of check is an ability check (or skill check).  Combat
          to-hit rolls are ability checks using the appropriate weapon skill, as are
          spell casting checks using the appropriate magic skill.  For these checks the
          dice used, the modifier and a suggested default difficulty are provided in the
          ability description.  Note that the difficulty is a suggestion for the GM who
          may override it as they desire.
          <indexentry>To Hit Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>To Hit</subentry></indexentry>
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
            Dourli attempts to strike a thug with his axe using the Axe Strike ability
            which he has at Level 1.  He rolls Std2d8 + 2 and the difficulty is the thugs
            armour class.  The +2 bonus is provided by his 1st level Axe Strike ability.
          </p>
        </playexample>      
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Opposed Ability Checks</subsectiontitle>    

        <p>
          <indexentry>Check<subentry>Opposed</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Opposed Check</indexentry> 
          An <defn>Opposed Check</defn> tests one characters ability against another.
          Instead of checking against a difficulty the character checks against their
          opponents check result for the same ability.  In case of ties no-one wins.
          <equation>
            <line>Opposed Ability Check</line>
            <line>
              Std2d8 + Mod. &gt; Std2d8 + Opponents Mod.
            </line>
          </equation>    
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
            Dourli wants to sell some information to the thieves guild.  One of his
            party members opposes the idea.  Dourli tries to negotiate to get his way.
            As Negotiate is an Opposed Ability Check both Dourli and his opponent roll.
            Whoevers modified roll is higher wins.
          </p>
        </playexample>

        <p>
          When making an opposed ability check against an NPC the GM can state
          a difficulty for the player to beat (converting the opposed ability check
          into a normal ability check).
        </p>
      </subsection>
      

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Aspect Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Aspect checks are standard checks against the aspects difficulty.
          They are discussed further in Chapter<ref>ch:aspects</ref> on 
          page<pageref>ch:aspects</pageref>.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Attribute Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Ability</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Ability Check</indexentry>        
          Attribute checks are checks made using one of the characters
          attributes, when no more specific check applies, <eg/> a character
          might check their speed when running from an avalanche.
        </p>

        <p>
          For Attribute Checks the character rolls a Std 2d8 modified by the
          characters Attribute modifier, see Table<ref>table:core_attribute_modifiers</ref>
          on page<pageref>table:core_attribute_modifiers</pageref> for a list of
          attribute modifers.
        </p>

        <p>
          The difficulty for these attribute checks is chosen by the GM, see
          Table<ref>table:std_check_difficulties</ref> on
          page<pageref>table:std_check_difficulties</pageref> for a list of
          suggested difficulties.
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
            Dourli tries to shift a large wine barrel that is sitting on a trap door 
            in a cellar.  The GM declares that in order to do so Dourli must make a strength 
            check with a difficulty of 12.  The player rolls a 3 and a 5 on their 2d8.
            Dourli has a Strength of 12, and so gets a bonus of +3 for a total of 11.  Dourli 
            fails to move the wine barrel. 
          </p>
        </playexample>      

        {% include "tables/std_check_difficulties.xml" %}
        {% include "tables/attribute_modifiers.xml" %}
      </subsection>

      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Opposed Attribute Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Opposed attribute checks involve two sides making an attribute check against
          each other.  The difficulty for the check is the other sides check result.        
          <equation>
            <line>Opposed Attribute Check vs Difficulty:</line>
            <line>Std2d8 + Mod. &gt; Std 2d8 + Opponents Mod.</line>
          </equation>
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
            Consider the intrepid Dourli holding a door shut while two thugs try to
            open the door.  This could be played as an opposed Str attribute check
            or the GM could just make Dourli make a regular Str Check against some
            stated difficulty chosen by the GM.
          </p>
        </playexample>      
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Break Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Morale</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Break</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Break Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Morale Check</indexentry>
          Break Checks occur when the characters are loosing a fight when fear takes
          a hold on them, panic can set in and they may flee from the fight.  This
	  process is described further in Section<ref>sec:break</ref> on
	  page<pageref>sec:break</pageref>.
        </p>        
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Encumbrance Checks (Optional)</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Encumbrance</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Encumbrance Check</indexentry>
          Encumbrance is an optional rule.  When the characters are doing something
          where the weight of their pack could be problematic then the GM can make the
          player roll against encumbrance.  This check is discussed further in
          Section<ref>sec:encumbrance</ref> on page<pageref>sec:encumbrance</pageref>.
        </p>        
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Generic Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Generic checks are a catch-all check for when nothing else applies.  The player
          rolls a Std 2d8 against a difficulty chosen by the GM.        
        </p>      
      </subsection>      
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Other Check Details</sectiontitle>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>How often can you Check?</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Skills<subentry>Check Once</subentry></indexentry>
          Each character can perform a check once.  For example, Dourli might
          try opening a box by picking locks.  If he fails he can try opening the box
          with his axe but he can't try picking the lock again.  In addition, someone 
          else can try and pick the lock.
        </p>      
      </subsection>

      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>When to Check?</subsectiontitle>
        <p>      
          As a GM when should you require that your players make a check?  Make sure that 
          you only require players to check when: <emph>the outcome is uncertain and failure 
          makes the game more interesting</emph>.  Many tasks are easy enough that they can be 
          completed automatically.  In this case no check is required to perform the action. 
          Harder variants of the task might require a check though.  For example, opening a 
          door might be considered an easy task that automatically succeeds, while opening a 
          door quietly might require a check.  Similarly breaking down a door might require 
          a check to perform quickly but can be done automatically given enough time and 
          given that one of the characters has an axe.  
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Party Checks</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          Sometimes checks have to be made by more than one character in the party.  In this
          section we discuss the different party checks.
        </p>

        
        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Everyone Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            <indexentry>Everyone Checks</indexentry> 
            <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Everyone</subentry></indexentry> 
            Sometimes everyone in a group has to make a check.  For example, if the party is 
            attacked using poisonous gas everyone in the party has to save.  When 
            <defn>Everyone Checks</defn>, each group member makes a separate check
            independent of the rest of the group and each individual suffers any
            repercussions separately if they fail.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>


        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Proxy Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            In a proxy check <emph>someone</emph> makes a check to represent the efforts
            of the whole group.  If the check fails everyone in the party suffers any
            effects. There are three types of Proxy Checks: <emph>Lowest Checks</emph>,
            <emph>Anyone Checks</emph> and <emph>Highest Checks</emph>.
          </p>

          <p>
            <indexentry>Lowest Checks</indexentry> 
            <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Lowest</subentry></indexentry>       
            <indexentry>Anyone Checks</indexentry> 
            <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Anyone</subentry></indexentry>       
            <indexentry>Highest Checks</indexentry> 
            <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Highest</subentry></indexentry>       
            When the <defn>Lowest Checks</defn> the player whose character has the lowest 
            bonus makes the check <eg/> when sneaking.  Conversely, when the
            <defn>Highest Checks</defn> the player whose character has the highest bonus
            makes the check, <eg/> for perception checks.
          </p>

          <p>
            In the interest of game pace we suggest the GM chooses a character that is the 
            approximate highest or lowest to perform the check.  It may not be completely 
            accurate but it is fast and it helps to share the dice rolling load around.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>


        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Chained Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            <indexentry>Chained Checks</indexentry> 
            <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Chained</subentry></indexentry>       
            <indexentry>Ascending Chained Checks</indexentry> 
            <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Ascending Chained</subentry></indexentry>       
            In a <defn>Chained Check</defn> members of the group check in rough order of 
            their relevant ability.  Chained group checks come in two flavours: Ascending
            and Descending.
          </p>

          <p>
            In an <defn>Ascending Chained Check</defn> the character in the group with
            the lowest relevant bonus checks first, then the second-lowest and so on until
            someone succeeds.  Usually there are repercussions for characters who fail 
            an ascending chained check.  For example checking to see who breaks and 
            flees from battle uses an ascending chained check using Resolve.
          </p>

          <p>
            Again, the GM should feel free to use an approximate ordering of the characters to 
            save time and spread the action, <eg/> just choose a character that is likely to
            have a low bonus for the descending check.  Any effect that this approximate
            ordering has on the outcome should be considered due to the fickle winds of fate.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            <indexentry>Descending Chained Checks</indexentry> 
            <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Descending Chained</subentry></indexentry>       
            A <defn>Descending Chained Check</defn> starts with the character with the highest 
            bonus checking first and then the second highest and so on until a player
            succeeds.  For example if the party are trying to run off a rope bridge
            that is being cut by some goblins.
          </p>

          <p>
            Difficult chained checks may require more than one success at the GMs discretion,
            that is multiple party members have to succeed before the check is successful.
            So, for example, we might write this as <emph>Ascending Resolve Chained Check 
            x2</emph> for a check that requires two resolve based successes with the characters 
            with the lowest bonuses going first.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

      </subsection>      

      
      <!--
          <subsection>
          <subsectiontitle>Assisting Checks</subsectiontitle>

<p>
Chained checks and group checks can be assisted.  Players declare that they will 
assist after the initial check has been rolled.  In order to assist a player's 
character must have some logical way of assisting in the check and the player 
of the assisting character then has to roll and pass the check themselves.  If they 
do this the initial check is modified by +2.
</p>
</subsection>

      -->
    </section>
  </chapter>


  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Tags, Aspects and Conditions</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:aspects</label>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Tags</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Tag</indexentry> 
        A <emph>Tag</emph> is a label or signifier attached to something  in the world.
	A cellar might be <emph>dark</emph> and <emph>musty</emph>, or a monsters attack
	might be <emph>necrotic</emph> <indexentry>damage type</indexentry>.
        If the GM describes a cellar as being dark then we say it is tagged dark, a dwarven 
        character is tagged dwarf.
      </p>

      
      <p>
        Characters may use tags to gain an advantage in a check.  They may also be prerequisites
        for using abilities, describe weapon damage types, properties that effect magic use,
        monster classes <etc/>
      </p>

      <playexample>
        <p>
          Dourli hides from a local gang of thugs in a cellar.  The GM describes the 
          cellar as dark and dank and storing old barrels.  The thugs enter the cellar 
          and look around.   Dourli invokes the dark tag of the cellar saying ``They'll 
          have trouble seeing me in the dark''.  The GM agrees the difficulty of the 
          thugs search is increased and the thug's.
        </p>
      </playexample>
    </section>    

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Aspects</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Aspect</indexentry> 
        Aspects are special tags that describe some facet of a characters personality, 
        their system of beliefs, personality traits, or their appearance.  Each aspect has
        a difficulty and the player can be forced to make checks against the aspects
        difficulty.  The higher the difficulty the harder it is for the character to resist
        the aspect. For example Dourli might have the following aspects: <emph>Gold is my
        Lodestone 8</emph>, and <emph>My Word as a Dwarf 10</emph>.
      </p>

      <p>
        Role-playing is shared story-telling.  Conflict and struggle are central to a 
        good story.  Aspects are the mechanic that we use to represent facets of the 
        characters personality that can be used to create interesting, non-physical,
        conflict and character development within the game.
      </p>

      <p>
        There are many types of aspects.  They fall loosely into the following categories:
      </p>
      

      <descriptions>
        <term>Personality Aspects</term>
        <description>
          <p>
            describe some part of a characters personality or demeanor, their flaws and
	    foibles, their short-comings, their weaknesses and sometimes their strengths,
	    <eg/> Mama's Boy, As Exciting as Cold Oatmeal, Plagued by Self-Doubt.
          </p>
        </description>

        <term>Philosophy Aspects</term>
        <description>
          <p>
            encode a character's beliefs and their moral compass: Defender of the 
            Downtrodden, Man of the Book, Death before Dishonour.
          </p>
        </description>

        <term>Relationship Aspects</term>
        <description>
          <p>
            Relationship aspects can be used to describe a close bond between the
            character and an individual, or a small group or even a large population.
            In the last case it comes in the form of fame, or infamy, with aspects
            like The Heroes of Izenholme, or The Scourge of the Serpent People.
          </p>

          <p>
            Discuss the role playing milieu with the GM.  Get a feel for the colour of 
            the world and the NPCs and organizations within it.  Choose 
            an aspect with the GM that ties your character to one of these 
            NPCs or organizations: Chosen of the Elvin Council, Beholden to the 
            Black Hand.  Alternatively choose a relationship with one of the player 
            characters.
          </p>
        </description>
        
        <term>Appearance Aspect</term>
        <description>
          <p>
            If you have an appearance aspect then there is something about your character 
            that is visibly notable, <eg/> Eyes of Midnight Black.  Dourli might pick
            <emph>A Beard To Die For</emph>.  Town criers might call out a
            wanted description for payment regarding information leading to the apprehension
            of a dwarf with a particularly fine beard.  Girl dwarves might find Dourli
            particularly irresistible.  Evil fiends might threaten to cut his beard short!
          </p>
        </description>
      </descriptions>



      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Compelling and Resisting Aspects</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          <indexentry>Compelling an Aspect</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Compel</subentry></indexentry> 
          The GM and players may attempt to <defn>Compel</defn> any characters aspect at 
          any time.  Compelling involves suggesting to a player that their character should 
          follow a course of action in keeping with one of their aspects.  The player who 
          controls the character may then choose to <bold>accept</bold> or <bold>resist</bold> 
          the compel.  
        </p>

        <p>
          If the player <emph>accepts a compel</emph> for an aspect then they should have 
          their character behave in accordance with that aspect.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          <indexentry>Resisting an Aspect</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Resist</subentry></indexentry> 
          Alternatively, players may have their characters try to <emph>resist the 
          compel</emph>.  They may perform a standard check against that Aspects difficulty.  
          If they fail the check their character must perform an action that is congruous 
          with the aspect in question, <emph>and</emph> increase the difficulty of the 
          aspect by one up to a maximum of 13.  See Figure<ref>figure:compel_aspect_table</ref>.
        </p>

	<figure position="!t" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./resources/compelling_aspects/aspects" scale="0.75"/>
	  <caption>Compelling Aspects</caption>
	  <label>figure:compel_aspect_table</label>
	</figure>

        <playexample>
          <p>
            Dourli hears that someone has offered 20gp for information 
            about one of Dourli's colleagues.  The GM might decide to try to compel Dourli as 
            he has an aspect <emph>Gold is my Lodestone</emph>.  The player then decides 
            whether he will accept the compel and provide the information about his associate
            or resist the compel.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            He decides to resist.  So he has to check against the 
            difficulty of that aspect, which is 8.  He rolls 
            2d8 (as aspect checks are standard checks) and rolls a total of 7.  He fails 
            as his dice result, 7, is lower than the aspects difficulty, 8.  So now Dourli has 
            to provide the information about his associate in order to garner his well earned 
            cash.  In addition, because he failed the aspect check he increases 
            the difficulty of the aspect by one, to 9.
          </p>
          
          <p>
            Dourli now  decides that he cannot, 
            just hand over the information about his associate, like a despicable cad, and 
            instead resolves to try and give them bogus information.  This action satisfies 
            the compel as, if he succeeds, he still gets his gold.
          </p>
        </playexample>

        <p>
          Conversely, a player can compel their own aspect in order to gain an  
          advantage, provided the GM agrees to the compel.  When a player compels one of 
          their own aspects they roll the check as normal.  If they fail the aspect 
          binds the character.   If they succeed the check the aspect does not apply
          and no advantage is gained.  However, the character must now reduce the 
          difficulty of that aspect by one. 
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Aspect Difficulty and Lifetime</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          Aspects need not last the lifetime of the character.  
          There are a limited number of aspects a character may have at any one time.
          Characters grow and over time the beliefs that shape them change and aspects 
          they once described them may no longer apply.  For example, a character might 
          hold certain beliefs very strongly and, overtime, the strengths of those beliefs 
          may wane.  After some period, the character may become disenchanted with their 
          former philosophy and move on.   Perhaps they grow and realize the error of their 
          ways, or maybe the continue to believe but the passion in them has gone.  
        </p>

        <p>
          The difficulty of an Aspect always lies in the range 5 to 13.
          Aspects acquired during character creation have an initial difficulty of $d4 + 4$. 
          Aspects whose difficulty falls below five are said to be <bold>diminished</bold> 
          and no longer apply to the character.  They may be removed from the character 
          sheet or demoted to a tag.
        </p>


        <p>
          Alternatively, the GM may at any time declare that a character loses an existing 
          aspect, gains a new one, or he may reword an existing aspect.  The GM should take
          care when doing this to keep the players vision of their character intact.
          You should consider modifying the characters aspects for one of the following
          reasons:
          <list>
            <li>Manageability: if the character has too many aspects consider removing 
            some, preferably starting with those with the lowest difficulties.</li>
            <li>To satisfy the narrative imperative: if adding the aspect to the 
            character would drive the story forward in interesting ways.  This might 
            happen as the result of some traumatic event or epiphany.</li>
            <li>To tweak an existing Aspect: if the aspect is constantly being exploited 
            by the player then the aspect should be changed.  Remember a good aspect 
            has to cause problems for the character occasionally</li>
          </list>
        </p>

        <p>
          Other aspects, such as physical aspects, are usually held for the lifetime of the 
          character.  For example, suppose Dourli loses a hand in a tragic, yet potentially 
          foreseeable, drunken axe juggling attempt.  He gains the <emph>Missing Left 
          Hand</emph> aspect.   Over time this may become much less problematic for him as 
          he adapts to his new condition however he will very likely retain that aspect until 
          his death.  Alternatively, the GM can rule that aspect can be diminished and 
          if Dourli manages to get the aspects difficulty down to 5 then it no longer 
          affects him in the usual course of play.  That aspect would then become a tag
          on the character -- just because it no longer effects him in a significant way.
        </p>
        
      </subsection>



      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Aspect Advantages</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          When a player seeks to compel one of their own characters aspects they do so 
          in the hopes of receiving an <defn>advantage</defn> and or weakening the 
          hold of that aspect upon their character.  An advantage comes in one of two 
          forms.  Often it will be restoring a die to one of their dice pools, or
          bonus to a dice roll.  Alternatively the <emph>player narrates</emph> the 
          result of a subsequent check.
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
            Suppose Dourli is fighting an ogre, and a large amount of treasure is 
            at stake if Dourli can win.  The ogre is nearly defeated but Dourli fails 
            his break check.  Dourli's player might try to compel his 
            <emph>Gold is my Lodestone</emph> aspect to try to get the GM to give 
            Dourli some bonus to his break check in that fight.  He rolls a 3.
            Well under the aspects difficulty and so is bound by the aspect.
            The GM grants him an extra $d6$ for his break check roll.   Dourli also
            decreases the difficulty of this aspect as he successfully compelled his
            own aspect.
          </p>
        </playexample>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Conflicting Aspect</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Sometimes a characters aspects conflict with one another.  In such cases 
          someone can compel one aspect to try and gain an advantage on a second
          aspect check, <eg/> suppose the GM tries to compel Dourli's <emph>Gold is 
          my Lodestone</emph> aspect to make Dourli sell out one of his companions.
          The player may counter that Dourli has claimed his friendship with the 
          companion while imbibing and that the GMs compel conflicts with his other 
          aspect <emph>My word as a Dwarf</emph>.  If Dourli <emph>fails</emph> the 
          check against <emph>My word as a Dwarf</emph> then he is bound by that aspect
          and the GM should grant him an advantage in the check against 
          <emph>Gold is my Lodestone</emph>.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Crafting Good Aspects</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  Aspects are used to drive conflict in the game.  If the character is
	  a <emph>Problem Gambler</emph> have the party visiting gambling dens so
	  the character has to suffer an internal struggle not to gamble and
	  have some thugs lean on the character to pay back his debts.
	</p>

        <p>
          Good aspects are evocative of the characters personality, their belief system 
          or their social status. They should not describe parts of the game already covered 
          by existing game mechanics.  For example, <emph>Greatest Swordsman Ever</emph> is 
          not a good aspect - it interferes with the game rules on combat.  <emph>Thinks He's
          the Greatest Swordsman Ever</emph> is much better because it establishes the 
          character as a braggadocio.  Remember that the Aspects should be chosen to create 
          conflict and problems for the characters to overcome.  If an Aspect does not 
          cause the character to overcome difficulties or make interesting decisions it
          is not a good aspect.  We have included some example Aspects in 
          Table<ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_random_aspects</ref> on
          page<pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_random_aspects</pageref>. 
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      {% include "tables/random_aspect_table.xml" %}

    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Conditions</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Condition</indexentry> 
        A <emph>Condition</emph> is a tag with explicit in-game rules attached to it.
        Like Aspects, Conditions are a special type of Tag.  In this section we present
        a list of some common conditions.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        <term>Blind</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Blind Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Blind</subentry></indexentry>
          The character cannot see.  They make checks Ambush, Surprise, Initiative, 
          and To-Hit at -5.
        </description>

        <term>Bloodied</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Bloodied Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Bloodied</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has suffered damage to their Health.  When a character first
	  suffers health damage in a fight they must make a morale check.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Broken</term>
        <description>
          <label>condition:broken</label>
          <indexentry>Broken Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Broken</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has lost the will to fight and must withdraw from battle.
          On their turn they may attack but must move away from the enemy if they
          can.  This condition occurs after a character has failed two break checks
          in combat.
        </description>
        
        <term>Checked</term>
        <description>
          <label>condition:checked</label>
          <indexentry>Checked Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Checked</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has lost momentum in a fight. They will not Charge and will
          not pursue.  This occurs after the character has failed a break check in combat.
        </description>
        
        <term>Dazed</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Dazed Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Dazed</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has suffered a nasty injury and are suffering a great deal of pain.
          They must make a willpower check or suffer a -2 to all checks except Luck.
        </description>

        <term>Drunk</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Drunk Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Drunk</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has had too much alcohol to drink.  They make Agility and Perception
          checks at -2 and they make Luck checks at +2.
        </description>

        <term>Distracted</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Distracted Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Distracted</subentry></indexentry>       
          Something has caught the characters attention and they are not paying
          attention to their surrounds.  They make checks Ambush, Surprise,
          Initiative at -2.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Deaf</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Deaf Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Deaf</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character cannot hear.  They make checks Ambush, Surprise,
          Initiative at -2 and have some trouble communicating with others.
        </description>

        <term>Enraged</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Enraged Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Enraged</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is wild with rage.  They can't flee or retreat.
        </description>

        <term>Exhausted</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Exhausted Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Exhausted</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is very tired.  Make Strength, Endurance, Speed and Movement
          checks at -4.
        </description>

        <term>Fearless</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Fearless Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Fearless</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has no fear and makes no break checks.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Invisible</term>    
        <description>
          <indexentry>Invisible Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Invisible</subentry></indexentry>       
          same as if others were blinded in actions that include the character.      
        </description>

        <term>Juggernaut</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Juggernaut Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Juggernaut</subentry></indexentry>       
          creature that has trouble turning and changing direction.
          must make a move turn after a charge.      
        </description>
        
        <term>Prone</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Prone Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Prone</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is on the ground.  Perform physical checks at -3.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Poisoned</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Poisoned Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Poisoned</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is suffering from terrible pain in the stomach or some form of
          paralysis.  They must make a willpower check in order to perform any action.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Routed</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Routed Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Routed</subentry></indexentry>
          The character has been defeated in combat.  If they can Flee they do so.
          Otherwise they will Yield or do something desperate.  This occurs
          when the player has failed three break checks in combat.
        </description>

        <term>Sick</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Sick Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Sick</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is feverish and light headed?  They perform a willpower
          check at the start of each turn in combat and if they fail they perform
          checks that turn at -2.
        </description>

        <term>Tired</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Tired Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Tired</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is tired.  Make Strength, Endurance, Speed and Movement checks at -2.
        </description>
        
        <term>Unconscious</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Unconscious Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Unconscious</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has blacked out due to a stunning blow to the head or
          due to too much pain.  They are in no immediate danger to their lives.
          They can perform no actions.
        </description>    
      </descriptions>      
    </section>            
  </chapter>






  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Combat</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:combat</label>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Combat Overview</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Combat<subentry>Rounds</subentry></indexentry>     
        Combat is central to the game and has its own specific set of rules.
        Combat starts with an optional <emph>Ambush</emph> or <emph>Surprise</emph> check,
        an optional <emph>Talk Round</emph>, an Initiative Roll, and then a series of
        <defn>Combat Rounds</defn>.  In each round all the characters involved perform a
        single action.  The order in which actions are performed in the round is determined
        by the type of the action and the characters initiative.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Ambush and Surprise</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        It is possible for some groups within a fight to be unprepared for battle or 
        completely taken off guard.  For game purposes we say that a group of characters can 
        be either ambushed or surprised.  <defn>Ambushing</defn> is a planned attack on a
        hopefully unsuspecting enemy.  <defn>Surprise</defn> represents occasions when two
        unsuspecting groups run into one another with no prior knowledge of the confrontation.
      </p>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Ambush <ambushsymbol/></subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          In order for one party to Ambush another they must be <defn>aware</defn> of that 
          parties presence or approach and the party being ambushed must be unaware of the
          ambushing party.  Ambushing requires that an opposed proxy check to check if the
          party being ambushed detects the ambushers before they are attacked.  The actual
          abilities used in an ambush check depends on the environment in which the ambush
          occurs, see Table<ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_awareness</ref> on
          page<pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_awareness</pageref>.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          If successful the opponents are ambushed and receive a -5 to their initiative rolls
          and any ambushees whose initiative is less than the slowest attackers initiative
          <emph>lose their action for the ambush round</emph>.
        </p>

        <p>          
          If the ambush attempt fails the ambushed group then checks to see if they are surprised.
        </p>

        {% include "tables/awareness.xml" %}
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Surprise <surprisesymbol/></subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          <indexentry>Surprise<subentry>Rounds</subentry></indexentry>
          Surprise occurs when one or more parties arrive at a combat and were unaware of
          the other parties presence, but <emph>were</emph> expecting trouble.  Usually
          surprise happens at the start of combat or when new combatants suddenly arrive
          to an existing fight.  Whenever there is the potential for combatants to be
          surprised then a <defn>surprise round</defn> occurs.  If a surprise round occurs
          mid-combat then initiative is rerolled.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          A surprise check is the same as an ambush check with the following two differences.
          Firstly when two parties meet both parties may be suprised.  This is not the case
          with ambushing.  Secondly, if a party fails a surprise check then they are off-guard
          and suffer a <emph>-2</emph> modifier to initiative.  If a party succeeds in their
          check then they are not surprised and no modifier is applied.
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Talk <talksymbol/></subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          The <defn>Talk Stage</defn> is optional, but can be used by the GM and the players
          for character development, plot development and as a means to achieve strategic
          ends.
        </p>

        <p>
          As a means of character development the Talk Stage provides an opportunity for
          the the NPCs to trash talk the player characters, brag about their achievements
          or reveal their motives.
        </p>

        <p>
          An important role of the Talk Stage is to drive the plot.  It allows the GM
          to provide narrative information to the players, exposition,
          colour and possibly the denoument, ``Luke, I am your Father''.
        </p>

        <p>
          Finally, the Talk Stage can be used as a strategic tool by either the
          players or the NPCs to avoid combat, negotiate a surrender, or forge alliances:
          <eg/> if the guards need to arrest the PCs they can ask them to come quietly.
        </p>

        <p>
          The Talk Stage only occurs if one side is predisposed to talking and the
          other side is capable of understanding the attempt at communication.  The
          Talk phase does not happen after an Ambush (presumably the ambushing side
          is committed to an attack).  Similarly a surprised party cannot initiate
          the Talk phase.  If a surprising party decides to initiate the
          Talk Stage they lose any advantage they gained from Surprise.
        </p>

        <p>
          The party being communicated with needs to understand that an attempt is
          being made to communicate.  For example, a charging bear probably will not
          stop and have a chat with the player characters, while a group of Orcs may or
          may not, depending on how hungry they are.  Usually, rational and intelligent
          characters will talk, if given the opportunity, in an attempt to try and avoid
          combat and reduce the chances of their own death.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      
      <playexample>
        <p>
          The thugs have returned to the cellars.  Dourli and Roslyn have been unable to 
          escape and now a fight looks inevitable.  It's still dark and our heroes have 
          managed to hide from the thugs so far.  Dourli attacks the thugs from his 
          hidden position attempting to ambush them.  The GM notes that the Thugs will
          be expecting trouble and he can only attempt to surprise them.
        </p>

        <p>
          Dourli tries to get advantage from the <emph>dark</emph> tag of the cellars.
          The GM agrees and gives the adventurers a <emph>+1</emph> arguing that the fact that the
          thugs were expecting to find Dourli down here would somewhat negate that advantage.
          Dourli agrees.
        </p>

        <p>
          As this is a proxy check the GM chooses Roslyn to check her Sneak versus one of the
          thugs Notice rolls.  If Roslyn rolls higher then the Thugs are surprised and their
          initiative roll will be reduced by -2.
        </p>
      </playexample>        
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Initiative <initiativesymbol/></sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Turn Order</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Initiative</indexentry>
        The order in which actions occur during combat rounds is
        <emph>partially</emph> determined by initiative.  Before combat starts players
        roll their initiative dice.  Their characters <defn>initiative</defn> for the
        rest of this combat is the total of this roll including any modifiers for
        surprise or ambush.  The GM may choose to add or subtract any other contextual
        modifier as they see fit.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Combat Rounds</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <defn>Combat rounds</defn> represent about six seconds of time in-game and are
        divided into five <defn>Stages</defn>.  Each stage is a set of actions all of
        which happen at roughly the same time.  They are: Start, Fast, Standard, Slow
        and End.  Characters that choose actions in the earlier stages will always go
        before characters who chose actions from the later stages.   In other words,
        if your character chooses to run in the Start stage they will run before anyone
        else has a chance    to attack them.
      </p>

      <p>
        There are four other special combat stages: ambush, surprise, talk and initiative
        which happen before combat starts and have been discussed previously.
        We also define a <defn>Non-Combat Stage</defn> for actions that can only occur
        outside of combat, <eg/> doing research in a library.  Breaking the combat down
        into stages allows us to describe when abilities may be used.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Finally, there are a few extra complications to combat: Reactions, Free Actions,
        Movement, Miscellaneous Actions, and Prepared Actions which we discuss later. 
      </p>

      {% include "tables/turn_order.xml" %}

      <figure position="tb">
        <img src="./resources/footer.png" scale="0.4"/>
      </figure>

      <figure position="!t">
        <img src="./resources/death.png" scale="0.8"/>
      </figure>
    </section>




    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Action Order</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        Within a combat round the order that actions are taken in is determined by an 
        auction.  The character with the <emph>lowest initiative</emph> that has not performed
        an action during the round declares, or bids, the action they would like to perform.
        Any character that has not performed an action yet, this round, may then bid a
        faster action.  No character may bid more than once and bidding is optional.
      </p>

      <p>        
        An action is <defn>faster</defn> if its stage, is faster (<eg/> Start Actions are
        faster than Fast Actions, and Fast Actions are faster than Standard Actions <etc/>),
        or if its stage is the same as the current fastest action and the character has a higher
        initiative.  In other words stage is the most important factor in determining action
        order, initiative is the tie-breaker.
      </p>

      <p>
        When no more bids have been made the auction is over and the fastest action is chosen.
        After an action is chosen the auction process starts again until all characters have
        used their actions.  This may seem like a complicated process but usually there will
        be only one or two bids per auction.
      </p>

      <p>
        Some important notes about the order auction process are:
        <olist>
          <li>
            Lowest initiative goes first.
          </li>
          
          <li>
            Each character can only bid once per auction.
          </li>

          <li>
            Each bid must be faster than the last bid.
          </li>

          <li>
            The fastest action wins.
          </li>

          <li>
            Only one action, the fastest action, gets performed per auction.
          </li>      
        </olist>
      </p>

      <playexample>
        <p>
          Dourli and his ally Roslyn, have been cornered by the local gang leader Fenton 
          One-Eye and two of his thugs.  A fight in the cellar of the Inn has been 
          underway for some number of rounds.  During the fight a few kegs of whiskey 
          have been smashed and there is a shallow pool of whiskey on the ground.  Dourli 
          rolled 7 for his initiative, Roslyn rolled 8, the thugs (as a group) rolled 8
          modified down to 6 because they are surprised.
        </p>

        <p>
	  FIXME:
          The thugs go first, having the lowest initiative, and declare they will charge 
          Dourli, a type of Melee Attack.  Dourli interrupts their turn, as he has a higher 
          initiative and declares he will throw a torch onto the whiskey, a Ranged Attack. 
          Dourli is able to do this because ranged attacks are at a higher stage than
          melee attacks.  Roslyn wants to attack the thugs with her quarter-staff but 
          cannot because Reach Attacks are at a lower stage than Missile Attacks, 
          she decides to wait.  At this point, Fenton can declare any interrupt action in 
          the ranged attack stage or higher.  Not being armed with a missile weapon 
          and having serious misgivings about being caught in an inferno in such 
          confined spaces he declares that he will Run, which occurs in the Run stage.
        </p>

        <p>
          At this point the actions have all been declared, because there is no one left
          to interrupt, and the actions are now executed in this order:  Fenton runs for 
          it, Dourli throws the torch and the Thugs are caught in the flames.  These 
          actions are now regarded as having happened.  Any subsequent actions happen
          after the actions described thus far.
        </p>

        <p>
          Roslyn is the only character who has not performed an action at this stage and 
          since that also makes her the remaining character with the lowest initiative she
          declares whatever action she pleases knowing that she cannot be interrupted.
          After Roslyns action is executed there are no characters with remaining actions
          and so a new turn starts.
        </p>
        
      </playexample>      
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Combat Details</sectiontitle>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Combat Stages and Actions</subsectiontitle>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Start <startsymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            This is the first stage in a combat round.  Characters may use Leadership
            to try and start negotiations, the Run command to perform a double movement,
            Flee to run from the combat, or they may Yield at this stage.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Fast Actions <fastsymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            Fast actions include missile weapon attacks and many Miscellaneous Actions.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>


        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Standard Actions<mediumsymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            Standard actions include Charging, attacking with a Reach weapon in the first
            round, and attacking with a Fast melee weapon.        
          </p>
        </subsubsection>


        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Slow Actions<slowsymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            Slow actions include melee fighting using heavy weapons.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        
        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>End Stage<resolutionsymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
            The GM may determine that one party or another must make a Break Check.
          </p>

          <p>
            <indexentry>Rallying</indexentry>When a character flees they keep fleeing until 
            they rally.  In order to rally the character must want to rally and then have to 
            make the break test they originally failed to cause them to flee in the first place.
            Rallying is a free action.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Free Actions</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Normally characters are allowed a single action during a combat round.
          A <defn>Free Action</defn> is an action that does not count against this limit.
          Only one free action may be performed by a character in any single combat round.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Movement</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Most combat actions also implicitly include some optional movement.  When a
          character attacks it is understood to involve a movement to close the distance to
          their opponent.  On a grid the distance the character may move is up to the
          characters movement.  Note that there is also a Run action that essentially just
          allows the character to move twice in a round, a Charge action for attacking at
          a run, and a Flee action.  In addition, the characters movement options may be
          curtailed if they have failed one or more Break Checks.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Reactions <reactionsymbol/></subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Reactions</indexentry>
          Under certain circumstances a character will be able to perform an additional
          <defn>Reaction</defn> during someone elses action or when a special triggering
          event occurs.  Reactions are miscellaneous actions that the GM allows
          to be performed as a Reaction or specially labelled abilities, such as: Shield Block,
          Sword Parry, Cloak Fighting and Dodge.  A character can only perform a reaction during
          a turn if they have not performed their action yet.  A character may only perform at
          most one reaction per round.   If two or more characters want to react to an action the
          character with the highest initiative decides the reaction order.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>
      Miscellaneous Actions <noncombatsymbol/>/<fastsymbol/>?
    </subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Miscellaneous Actions</indexentry>
          Miscellaneous actions refer to things that characters do during combat
          that are not actually fighting actions: <eg/> reading the runes that close
          a magic portal, releasing a portcullis, mounting a horse, quaffing a potion,
          pushing a load of barrels over and so on.
        </p>

        <p>
          For many miscellaneous actions the GM will just have to make a ruling as
          to the check required and the stage in which the action occurs as it would
          be impossible and infeasible for us to provide rules for the myriad of
          miscellaneous actions that might occur.  When doing this we strongly suggest
          that the GM make most Miscellaneous Actions occur in the Fast Stage.
          This will encourage players to choose these actions and make for more varied
          combat encounters.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Prepared Actions</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          If the character knows that a combat is iminent they may declare that they
          prepare an action.  At that point, at the GMs discretion, the action becomes
          a reaction and occurs at one faster stage than normal, <eg/> a prepared arrow
          shot triggered when someone enters a room would occur in the Start Stage.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Benefits and Consequences</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Some suggested benefits and consequences for use during combat checks
          can be found in Tables <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_to_hit_consequences</ref>
          and <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_to_hit_consequences</ref>.
        </p>
        {% include "tables/to_hit_consequences.xml" %}
        {% include "tables/to_hit_benefits.xml" %}
      </subsection>      
    </section>



    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Movement and Range</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Miniatures vs Theatre of the Mind</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          <indexentry>Movement</indexentry>
          Combat may either be performed on a table with miniatures using a map with a
	  <defn>grid</defn>, 
          or purely narratively using the theatre of the mind <defn>TOTM</defn>.
        </p>

        <p>
          If the combat is taking place on a grid then the map determines 
          the distances for movement, spell area of effect, missile weapon range etc. 
          On a map a run is simply a double movement, a charge is a movement + d6 extra 
          squares then an attack if the enemy is in range.  Fleeing characters move twice 
          their movement rate +d6 extra squares.
        </p>

        <p>
          Movement is halved over <defn>difficult terrain</defn>.  
          Difficult terrain included: muddy ground, terrain with a lot of debris, brambles etc.
        </p>        

        <p>
          <indexentry>Range</indexentry>
          Missile weapons and some spells have a range.  Beyond that range they cannot be 
          effectively used and they automatically miss.  The range may be subdivided into 
          short range and long range.  Attacks at <defn>long range</defn> attract a +2 to-hit 
          difficulty.
        </p>

        {% include "tables/combat_modifiers.xml" %}    

        <p>
          <indexentry>Cover</indexentry>
          Cover provides modifiers to hit for most missile weapons and for melee combat.
          <defn>Light cover</defn> afforded by bushes, the curve of a hill and the like 
          gives a +2 to hit difficulty, <defn>Hard cover</defn>, such as a half wall, 
          provides a +4 to hit for missile weapons, melee weapons and some spells.  
          <defn>Full cover</defn> makes hitting the target impossible.  The GM should feel 
          free to choose a to-hit modifier that fits the cover available to the characters.
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Attacks of Opportunity and Engagement</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          A character in hand-to-hand automatically <defn>engages</defn> their opponent.  
          Typically, characters can engage only one opponent at a time, but may be engaged 
          by many characters simultaneously.  
        </p>

        <p>
          If a character is engaged then any action that causes them to move away
          from the character that has engaged  them; except Flee; triggers an <defn>attack
	  of opportunity</defn> against the moving character.  An attack of opportunity is
	  simply an additional melee attack as a free action.  Recall that characters may
	  only perform one free action per combat round.
        </p>

      </subsection>
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>
	Non-Lethal vs Lethal Combat <label>sec:non-lethal-combat</label>
      </sectiontitle>
      
      <p>
        There are two categories of combat: Lethal and Non-Lethal.  In Non-Lethal 
        combat the participants are not actively trying to kill their opponents, but 
        rather trying to subdue them or drive them off.
      </p>

      <p>
        The difference between non-lethal combat and lethal combat is that non-lethal
        combat ends when someone becomes <defn>Bloodied</defn>, which occurs when their
        Stamina reaches zero.  At this point the combatants have to determine what type
        of combat is taking place.  If fighting continues that involves the bloodied
        character then the combat has become lethal.  Note that when a character becomes
	Bloodied they are forced to make a break check.
      </p>

      <p>      
        Examples of typical non-lethal combat encounters include fights with the local 
        guards, bar-room brawls, fights with gangs of thugs and bandits.  There are 
        many reasons to use non-lethal combat: killing people is often a capital crime 
        in human society, there are severe social implications when an individual 
        becomes known as a killer, potentially the players might wish to interrogate 
        an opponent, and bandits might want to make money selling people into slavery.
      </p>      
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>
	Death <label>sec:death</label>
      </sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Death <see>Zero Health</see></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Zero Hit Points</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Consequences</indexentry>
        Health has a minimum value of zero.  After a characters health is reduced to zero
	they enter a <defn>Near Death</defn> state.  In order to resolve this state the GM may:
        <olist>
          <li>Declare an outcome, or</li>
          <li>Negotiate an outcome with the player and the party, or</li>
          <li>Have the player roll on the Near Death Table, see Table
	  <ref>table:near_death_table</ref> on page <pageref>table:near_death_table</pageref>.
	  </li>
        </olist>
      </p>

      <p>
	The GM should choose the option that is most reasonable and narratively satisfying.
	If a character falls into a pool of lava they are dead.  If they have been knocked
	down by Orcs then roll on the Near Death Table.  
      </p>
      
      {% include "tables/near_death_table.xml" %}            
    </section>
    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Break Checks <label>sec:break</label></sectiontitle>      
      <p>
        <indexentry>Break Checks</indexentry>
        Both player characters and monsters may, from time to time, be forced to make a 
        break check.  In order to make life more manageable, the GM and player characters
        make break tests differently.
      </p>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Player Character Break Check</subsectiontitle>       
        <p>
          <indexentry>Breaking</indexentry>
          <label>sec:breaking</label>
          
          For player characters <defn>Break Checks</defn> are made using the Resolve pool.
          The Break Check is not an action.
          <equation>
            <line>Break if:</line>
            <line>Resolve Pool <leqqsymbol/> Break Difficulty</line>
          </equation>      
        </p>

        <p>
          As characters fail break tests they gain conditions that limit what they can
          do during combat, and subsequent break checks become more difficult, see
          Table<ref>table:break_difficulties</ref> on
          page<pageref>table:break_difficulties</pageref> for a list of break test
          difficulties and conditions.
        </p>

        <p>
          For example, looking at the table, the first time a character makes a break
          test during combat they do so with a difficulty of 8.  If they fail they gain
          the Checked condition and the next break test will be made with a difficulty of
          12.
        </p>

        <p>
          The GM should feel free to modify the break difficulty as he pleases, <eg/>
          to reflect being attacked at night, being vastly outnumbered, the horrible
          visage of the characters opponents, the party being in good spirits etc.
        </p>    

        {% include "tables/break_difficulties.xml" %}    

        <p>
          Break tests for players should be made at the GMs discretion.  But some
      suggested times to make break cheaks are:
          <list>
            <li>When any party member becomes bloodied,</li>
            <li>After all party members have become bloodied,</li>
            <li>When the party enters combat against a fear causing opponent,</li>
            <li>Whenever the party is surprised.</li>
          </list>          
          Ultimately though, it is up to the GM to decide when the players should make a 
          break check and the GM should feel free to make the sooner or later in the combat 
          so that they align with pivotal events in the combat.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Monster and NPC Character Break Tests</subsectiontitle>       

        <p>
          Monster stat blocks include a default break difficulty for the monster as a 
          suggestion to the GM though ultimately it is up to the GM's discretion to choose 
          an appropriate break difficulty for the monsters.    For example, say a party of 
          adventurers attack a kobold temple, the kobold priests are enraged at the desecration 
          of their temple so the GM determines that their break difficulty should be reduced, 
          but the kobold guards have seen some of their compatriots flee already and so their 
          break difficulty should be increased.  
        </p>

        <p>
          Break tests for monsters and opposing NPCs should be made when:
          <list>
            <li>The first time a monster dies during an encounter,</li>
            <li>After a third of the monsters have died,</li>
            <li>After two thirds of the monsters have died,</li>
            <li>Whenever the monsters are surprised.</li>
          </list>          
        </p>

        <p>
          In the interests of keeping the game flowing, if there are more than, say, five 
          monsters then the monsters should be grouped together for the purposes of their 
          break tests.  For example, imagine there are 15 kobold guards in the combat, the 
          GM should group them as three groups of five for the purposes of testing to see 
          if they break.
        </p>

        <p>
      When monsters fail their break tests they should attempt to break off combat,
      yield, negotiate or flee, at the GMs discretion.
        </p>
    
      </subsection>
    </section>


    {% include "fragment_pursuit.xml" %}


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Foreshadowing and Outs</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        For combat to be interesting strategically it is important that there
        be a chance of failure.  However, as combat is highly lethal it may
        result in a total party kill, which is a generally undesirable outcome.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        There are two approaches to solving this problem.  The first is to make
        sure that the characters are able to win the combat by providing deliberately
        easy foes.  While this works, if overused it leads to a dull combat experience.
      </p>               

      <p>
        The second approach to solving this problem is to provide an <defn>Out</defn>
        for the party should things go wrong. For example if the characters are fighting
        slavers and they lose then they can be enslaved and the game continues.  If
        they are fighting Orcs they may be kept for food later.  The city guards might
        throw them in the dungeon if they prevail against the party.
      </p>


      <p>
        A sub-type of the Out is the Deus Ex Machina.  In this case the party is
        saved right at the last minute by some third-party.  This is generally undesirable
        from a narrative perspective as it leads the players to believe that whatever
        they do some third-party will save them at the last minute, thus reducing tension.
      </p>

      <p>
        The trick to making Outs feel less contrived is <defn>Foreshadowing</defn>.
        As a GM, you should provide information to the characters about the Out so that
        if and when you have to use it the development in the narrative is less jarring.
        For example, if characters are trying to contact the elvish border guards in the
        Grey Forest and you, as the GM, know they are just about to run into giant spiders
        have the characters hear the guards trumpets in the distance.  If the players
        are fighting slavers, let them know that there have been slaver raids taking place.
        Also it is a good idea to plant these foreshadowing seeds earlier rather than later.
      </p>

      <p>
        In summary, to avoid combat annihilation try to have an Out for the characters
        before the combat.  Use foreshadowing in order to make the out seem less contrived.
      </p>          
      
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Random Encounters</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        Random encounters are events that happen to the party that are not instigated
        by the party. Random encounters serve two primary purposes in the game:
      </p>

      <list>
        <li>
          Random encounters provide a disincentive for the characters
          to camp and ``turtle''.  The threat of constant danger should
          encourage them to keep moving forward, and to keep the story
          moving forward as well.
        </li>

        <li>
          Random encounters do not all have to be bad.  They can be used to provide
          the characters with useful information.
        </li>
      </list>

      <p>
        In order to determine when a random event occurs determine the threat
        level of the characters locale.  In the wilderness the threat level might
        be in the range 4 to 6.  In an enemy stronghold it might be 8 to 12.  Get
        one of the players to roll a standard check against that difficulty.  If
        they fail a random encounter occurs.
      </p>      
    </section>
    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Healing, Resting and Sleeping</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Refreshes</indexentry>     
        <indexentry>Healing</indexentry>
        Players heal, recover their magic, luck and resolve by Resting and Sleeping
        using the Rest and Heal abilities.  
      </p>

      <p>
        When characters Sleep they regain Stamina at their Stamina Refresh Rate,
        they regain Health at the Health Refresh Rate, and they gain four refreshes
        for dice pool
        refreshes.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        When Resting the character regains Stamina at their Stamina Refresh Rate
        and they gain Refreshes to any two dice pools of their choice.  Characters
        may only benefit from up to two Rests between Sleeps.  Any Rests above
        two have no effect.
      </p>        
    </section>
    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Fighting in Groups</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        It is possible to fight in groups.  While fighting in a group the
        front row provides hard cover to the back row.  The front row must
        have at least as many people in it as the back row.  To make melee
        attacks from the back row you must be using a weapon with reach.
        It is possible for a group to have two front rows, i.e. to be fighting
        on two fronts, provided that the number of people in each front row
        is greater than or equal to the number of people in the back row.
        Furthermore, characters in the back row add a temporary bonus die to
        their break tests.
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>


  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>The Laws of Magic<label>ch:magic</label></chaptertitle>    
    {% include "fragment_magic.xml" %}
  </chapter>




  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Skills and Abilities</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:abilities</label>    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        This chapter describes abilities available to characters in the game.
      </p>     

      <p>
        <indexentry>Abilities</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Skills<see>Abilities</see></indexentry>
        Each character has a set of <defn>Abilities</defn>.
        Some abilties allow the player to perform <defn>Actions</defn> or 
        <defn>Ability Checks</defn> while others provide the player with passive advantages.  
        Skills may be used in a variety of ways depending on the skill in question.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Abilities are tags and like other tags, they may be used by the player 
        to gain an advantage in an appropriate context.  
      </p>

      <p>
        Many abilities have a cost that players must pay in order to acquire the ability.
        As players increase in level they get more points to purchase additional abilities.
        Some abilities are innate - they have zero cost and the character is assumed to
        automatically have the ability at first level.    
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Mastering a Skill</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Skill<subentry>Mastery</subentry></indexentry>
        Some skills have prerequisites.  In order to use one skill as a prerequisite for 
        another the character must first have mastered the skill.  In order to master the skill
        the player must have used the skill and achieved the appropriate number of successes 
        and failures using that skill.
      </p>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Ability Progression</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Ability<subentry>Progression</subentry></indexentry> 
        For a character to increase an ability level they potentially need to satisfy four 
        conditions: Prerequisites, Training, Mastery and Reflection.  Most abilities will
        require some or all of these conditions to be met before the ability can be attained.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Innate Skills<see>Skills Innate</see></indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Skills<subentry>Innate</subentry></indexentry>
        Innate skills are considered to be either instinctive or have been learned in the 
        characters childhood.  Most characters in the game are assumed to have these skills by 
        default. This includes things like jumping, climbing and speaking a language or two.  
      </p>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Prerequisites</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Prerequisites<see>Skills Prerequisites</see></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Skills<subentry>Prerequisites</subentry></indexentry> 
          Some skill levels have prerequisites.  These prerequisites must be met before 
          the new skill level can be attained.  Prerequisites are generally of two types:
          minimum primary attribute requirements, <eg/> Strength > 13, and other skill 
          prerequisites, <eg/> Maths I is a prerequisite for Alchemy I.  An ability does 
          not have to be mastered in order to be used as a prerequisite for another skill.
          But a character cannot attain the next level of an ability without mastering the
          current level, <eg/> you must have mastered Maths I before you can gain Maths II,
          but mastery is not required to satisfy the prerequisite for Alchemy I.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Training</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          <indexentry>Training<see>Skills Training</see></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Skills<subentry>Training</subentry></indexentry> 
          Training represents the time spent studying or practicing a skill and is represented
          using skill points.  When a character goes up a level they receive skill points.  
          Those skill points can be used to learn new skills and abilities.  
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Mastery</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Training<see>Skills Mastery</see></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Skills<subentry>Mastery</subentry></indexentry> 
          In order for a character to attain a higher level of a skill they already have
          they must first have mastered the existing skill level.  Listed beside the 
          skill level in their archetype description will be the number of successes
          <success/>, attempts <attempt/> or failures <fail/> of the ability is required
          before that skill level is mastered.   During the course of a game the player is
          required to keep track of the progress of unmastered abilities.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Reflection</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Finally, the character requires reflection so that they can truly understand 
          the ability that they have learned.  Characters must wait for a long rest which
          allows them the time to contemplate what they have learned.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    {% for ability_group in ability_groups %}
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</sectiontitle>
      
      {{ ability_group.get_description() }}

      {% for ability in ability_group  %}
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>
          {{ ability.get_title() }} {{ ability.get_ability_class_symbol() }}
          <indexentry>{{- ability.get_title() }} Ability</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Ability<subentry>{{- ability.get_title() }}</subentry></indexentry>
        </subsectiontitle>
        
        {% if ability.description is not none %}
        {{ ability.description }}
        {% endif %}

        <table>
          <tablecategory>Standard</tablecategory>

          <tablespec>
            <fixed>0.05</fixed>
            <fixed>0.85</fixed>
          </tablespec>

          <tabletitle>X</tabletitle>

          <!--
              <tablerow>
              <td width="2" align="l">
              <tablesection>{{ ability.get_title() }}</tablesection>
              </td>
              </tablerow>
          -->

          <!--
              {% if loop.index0 == 0 %}   
              <tableheaderrow>
              <th>Level</th>
              <th>Check</th>
              </tableheaderrow>
              {% endif %}
          -->

          {% for ability_level in ability.get_levels()  %}
          <tablerow>
            <td>
              {{- ability_level.get_level_number() | convert_to_roman_numerals }}
              {%- if ability_level.is_innate() %} <innateabilitylevelsymbol/>{% endif -%}
            </td>
            <td>
              {%- if ability_level.has_prerequisites() %}
              <bold>Prereq:</bold>
              {%-     for prereq in ability_level.get_prerequisites()  %}
              {{-         prereq.to_string() }}
              {%-         if not loop.last %}, {% endif %}          
              {%-     endfor %}

              {% endif %}
              {%- if ability_level.check is not none -%}
              <bold>Check:</bold> {{ ability_level.check -}}
              {%- endif %}          
              {%- if ability_level.damage is not none %}          
              <bold>Dmg:</bold> {{- ability_level.damage }}
              {%- endif %}
              {%- if ability_level.effect is not none %}
              
              <bold>Effect:</bold> {{ ability_level.effect -}}
              {%- endif %}              
              {%- if ability_level.description is not none %}
              {{ ability_level.description }}
              {%- endif %}
            </td>
          </tablerow>
          {% endfor %}                
        </table>    
      </subsection>      
      {% endfor %}
    </section>
    {% endfor %}      

  </chapter>
  


  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Equipment</chaptertitle>


    {% include "fragment_equipment_list.xml" %}

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Encumbrance<label>sec:encumbrance</label></sectiontitle>
      
      <p>
        <indexentry>Encumbrance</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Encumbrance</subentry></indexentry>    
        Encumbrance is an optional rule.  The characters total encumbrance is a 
        difficulty level that tests may be made against.  For example, characters 
        climbing a mountain may be made to make an Endurance check against their 
        encumbrance or become exhausted.   A character leaping from one roof 
        to another who gets a consequence in their check may be forced to roll 
        a speed or agility check against their encumbrance or drop some equipment
        into the streets below.  Encumberance does not simply represent weight,
	it also represents the unweildiness of the item; how awkward it is to move
	while carrying the item.
      </p>

      <p>
        In order to use encumbrance you should be using the standard character sheets.
        In the equipment section of the character sheet, marked against the side, are
        encumbrance values for each class of item (small, medium and large) and values
        for armour and coin.  The total of these values is the characters encumbrance.
	Note that you do not count items twice (<eg/> a shield may be a large object in
	practice but its encumberance is counted separately because of the encumberance
	values for armour)
      </p>

      <p>
        If used, it is important that this rule does not become a long-winded exercise in 
        accounting.  First roll the check, then calculate the encumbrance (if required).
        Secondly, don't worry about getting the value exactly right - it will take to long.  
        Just eye-ball it.
      </p>
    </section>    
  </chapter>

  {% if add_index_to_core %}
  <index/>
  {% endif %}
</book>
