
<section>
  <sectiontitle>Fundamental Principles of Magic <label>ch:magic</label></sectiontitle>

  <p>
    <indexentry>magic</indexentry>
    Magic infuses this and all worlds.  It links and binds all things, tying entities 
    together and creating invisible bonds between the planes.  The utilization of magic
    is concerned with controlling the flow of thaumaturgical energies along these paths.
    Magic appears to be goverened by well known principles and is as much a science 
    as physics, mathematics, theosophy astrology, phrenology or even biology.  However,
    due to the chaotic nature of thaumic energies the application of these laws
    is unreliable, and very frequently dangerous.  
  </p>

  <p>
    In this chapter we outline the fundamental laws of transfiguration, channelling,
    ensorcellment, evocation, summoning and the like.  But the reader should beware,
    verily it is said that those who play with the devil's toys will be brought by
    degrees to wield his sword.   The basic principles of magic are as follows:
  </p>

  <descriptions>
    <term>The Principle of Potentials</term>
    <description>
      In order for magic to occur there must be a difference in thaumaturgical 
      potentials.
    </description>

    <term>The Principle of Flux</term>
    <description>
      Magic occurs when thaumaturgical energies flow from a high potential to a 
      low potential along a line of flux.
    </description>

    <term>The Law of Contagion</term>
    <description>
      Magic shapes all things.  Logically it follows that similar things 
      are linked by the lines of flux that created them.
    </description>

    <term>The Law of Conductivity</term>
    <description>
      Lines of flux may be broken or enhanced using a variety of techniques.
      Different materials conduct magic better than others.   Natural and biological 
      materials such as flesh, wood, and water conduct magic very well, as does silver.
      Ferrous metals and rock do not conduct magic well and can interfere with its casting
      in unpredictable ways.
    </description>

    <term>The Corollary of Knowledge</term>
    <description>
      The more you know about a subject the greater your knowledge about the 
      lines of flux that bind them.
    </description>
  </descriptions>

  <p>
    <label>sec:magic_dice</label>
    Mechanically, magical spells are skills.  Casting magic uses a pool of magic dice, and
    magic checks are dice pool checks.  Each character has a different dice pool depending 
    on their archetype, their abilities and their skills. Most non-magical characters will 
    only have animus dice and no way of using them.  Other characters will have greater 
    energy and a variety of ways of using it.
  </p>

  <figure position="h">
    <img src="./resources/demon.png" scale="0.7"/>
  </figure>
  
  <p>
    In order to cast spells the player chooses a set of dice from their pool, rolls them and 
    attempts to roll greater than its difficulty level, and less than its over-charge 
    value if specified.

    <equation>
      <line>Cast:</line>
      <line>Over-Charge <geqqsymbol/> Dice Result <geqqsymbol/> Difficulty</line>
    </equation>
    
    If the sum of the magic dice is less than the difficulty then the spell is 
    under-powered, sputters out and fails.  If the sum of the magic power is greater than 
    the spell difficulty then the extra theurgical energies must be disipated somehow.
  </p>

  <p>
    These magical checks are affected by the complex, chaotic nature of thaumaturgic
    energies.  We now describe how the laws of magic effect the casting of spells
    by increasing or decreasing their power depending on circumstance.
  </p>
</section>



<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Law of Potentials</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    The first law of magic is that <indexentry>rules of magic, the first</indexentry>
    <emph>magic requires a potential difference in magical energy levels as a 
    prerequisite</emph>.  Furthermore, <indexentry>rules of magic, the second</indexentry>
    <emph>the productive use of magic requires the construction of a thaumaturgical 
    conduit between potentialities</emph> through which the magic can flow. 
  </p>

  <p>
    There are many different sources of thaumaturgical potentialities, such as the 
    potential difference between planes of existance, energy from stored thaumaturgical
    sources, the animus (a persons spark of life) and so on.  We examine the most
    important, the most widely used, of these potentialities here.
  </p>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Sources of Magical Potentialities</subsectiontitle>

    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Raw/Planar Magical Sources</subsubsectiontitle>

      <p>
	Planar Magicks are those that use the raw potential differences between planes
	directly, these so-called Protinus magics, are the most powerful and the most
	dangerous to magical sources to use:
      </p>

      <descriptions>
	<term>Planar Potentialities</term> 
	<description>are the most volatile and perhaps the most dangerous means of
	controlling magical energies.  They employ the the potentiality across two
	planes.  That is they harness the flow from planes of higher energy to planes of
	lower energy.  There are two main dangers of 
	using this form of thatumaturgical energy.   The first is its volatility.  
	Casters using this energy source are more likely to over charge their spells.
	The second danger are the lurkers in the dark.  There are a myriad of creatures
	lurking in the frigid abyssal planes who hunger eternally to escape to higher planes
	to feed indiscriminately.  They wait for the opportunity a miscast might provide.
	</description>

	<term>Elemental Magic</term>
	<description>is a subset of planar magic that uses the potential between a particular 
	set of well-known planes of existance, the so-called elementatal planes.  The 
	advantage of this energy source is that these planes are comparatively stable and
	their behaviour is fairly well-understood.  Unfortunately, elemental magic is less
	versatile than, the more general, planar magic.
	</description>
      </descriptions>
    </subsubsection>
    
    {% include "tables/principles_of_magic.xml" %}
    
    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Types of Magic Items</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Magical items use thaumaturgical energies stored  within the device itself.
	Magic by its very natures is evanescent - it has a tendency to dissipate after
	a period of time.  Magical items tend to be made of thaumic insulating materials
	in order to minimize the rate at which magic is dissipated.
      </p>

      <p>
	In game, this stored magical potential is representated by each magical device
	having its own magic pool and refresh rate.  The item used to store magical energies
	may be one use, rechargeable or self recharging.  One use magic items will have no
	refresh rate.  When a one-use items pool is depleted the device is spent.
      </p>

      <p>
	Powerful magical devices may be embued with the residual animus of their
	creators, or tainted with by the nature of their magical source.  In either case,
	this is represented in game by the item having one or more aspects that are applied
	to characters when they interact with the item.  The nature of the interaction
	required to transfer the items aspects to the character depends on the item,
	e.g. the aspects might be applied when they touch the item, or when they have used
	the item a number of times, etc.
      </p>

      <descriptions>

	<term>Scrolls</term>
	<description>
	  Like rune spells, scrolls contain the written incantations that must be entoned
	  to cast a spell.  Unlike runes they do not contain any magical energies with
	  which to automatically trigger or power the spell.  A scroll user must be able to
	  read the language in which the scroll is written, checking to do so if necessary,
	  and must be able to read the scroll aloud.  Furthermore scroll users must power
	  the scroll with their own magic pool.  These requirements make them difficult
	  for non-casters to use.  Scrolls may be reused unless they become damaged, or
	  the creator has built some limit into the scroll (which may be done in order to
	  reduce the danger of misuse or limit competition with the creator).
	</description>

	<term>Potions</term>
	<description>
	  Potions store thaumic energy in liquid form.  The magic is enfused in a liquid
	  solvent, and contained within a glass flask with binding magical inscriptions.
	  Energy stored in a potion begins to escape as soon as the flask is opened.  Potions
	  are generally created by magic users for the use of non magic users as potions
	  are easy to use and moderately easy to create.
	</description>
	
	<term>Wands</term>
	<description>
	  A wand is a slight baton made from a thaumic conducting material that is used to
	  better focus and control raw thaumic energy.  Using a wand allows the caster to
	  reroll one of their spell dice.
	</description>

	<term>Rods</term>
	<description>
	  A rod is a short, <measurement><metric>30-60cm</metric><imperial>1'-2'</imperial></measurement>,
	  heavy staff that is used to store and direct the flow of thaumic energy.  They are
	  constructed from a thaumically conductive core encircled in an outer thaumic insulating
	  shell.  Typically, rods can store an extra two dice worth of thaumic energy.  Magical
	  rods can be used in combat and are equivalent to a club.  Once used the caster needs
	  to recharge the rod.
	</description>

	<term>Staffs and Spears</term>
	<description>
	  Staffs are long sticks, <measurement><metric>150-180cm</metric><imperial>5'-6'</imperial>
	  </measurement>, that can be used in combat.  In addition because they are
	  constructed from a conductive material, typically wood, they can be used to ground
	  out a spell, in order to mitigate the problems associated with over-charging a spell.
	  When using a staff to ground out dice you may remove either the highest or lowest die
	  from the roll.  A spear may also be used for this purpose but its metal tip effects
	  the flow and so when grounding with a spear only the lowest die result may be grounded
	  out.
	</description>      

	<term>Holy Symbol</term>
	<description>
	  Holy symbols use contagion to increase the strength of the conduit between a theurgical
	  caster and their sponsor.  It is assumed that theurgical casters have a magical symbol
	  and there are penalties for casting theurgical magic without a holy symbol of the
	  appropriate type.
	</description>      

	<term>Runic Magic</term>
	<description>
	  <p>
            Magical runes are essentially spells that automatically cast 
	    themselves when a certain triggering event occurs, usually within the vicinity of 
	    the runes.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    The small amount of magic required to cast the runespell is stored in the runes 
	    themselves when they are created.  Overtime this magic will leach from the rune
	    and it will no longer be viable, but may still be replenished by a skilled
	    Runemaster.  For this reason runes are usually carved into materials which are
	    highly thaumaturgically non-conductive such as ferrous metals or rock.  Once the
	    runespell is cast it behaves as any other spell, drawing the energy for the spell
	    itself from some second source.  For runes carved in stone and steel this is almost 
	    always from the elemental planes of earth as the spells powers are enhanced 
	    by the contagious nature of the substrate.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    Magical swords, armour, rings and the like are typically runic in nature.
	  </p>
	</description>	
      </descriptions>
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>The Animus</subsubsectiontitle>

      <p>
	<indexentry>animus</indexentry>
	Every living creature is imbued with a store of thaumic energy within and of
	themselves, their <emph>Animus</emph>.   This energy is used by a number of 
	forms of magic, the most widely know examples are: necromantic draining, blood 
	magic, death curses, human sacrifices, and ingestion.
      </p>

      <p>
	It has been postulated that the phenomenon of life is a trickle of magical power 
	from some higher plane through to some lower plane.  In such a model each creatures
	life can be construed as a conduit through which magical energies flow.  An alternate
	model holds that living creatures are wellsprings of magical energies, i.e.\ that
	they are the sources of magical energies themselves.  A third model holds that both
	of the first two models are holds true.  Which of these models, if any, are correct
	remains an extremely contentious area of debate amongst students of these dark arts.
	In any case, it is widely believed that their exists an animatic flow that replenishes 
	the animus from some source.
      </p>

      <p>
	The rate of the animatic flow is proportional to the strength of emotions that 
	the living creature is feeling.  For this reason many thaumatergical predators 
	will enhance these emotions while feeding.  
      </p>

      <p>
	It has been hypothesized that apparations, ghosts, banshees and other spiritual 
	manifestions are the reminants of powerful residual animatic flow, eddies in the
	animatic flow, if you like.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>The Biome</subsubsectiontitle>

      <p>
	Rather than draw magical power from a particular animus, some animistic casters,
	such as	Druids, are able to draw very small amounts of magic from all surrounding
	living creatures.  While very powerful these magics can be difficult to use if the
	biome is not in balance. The type of biothaumic magic dice changes depending on the
	environmental balance.
      </p>

      <p>
	Biothaumic magic uses different dice depending on the environment the caster is in.
	In biomes with a great deal of balanced animistic energy, forests, swamps etc, each
	dice in biothaumic magic pool use d8s.  In a biome that is out of balance, like a
	city, use d4s.  In biomes that are slightly out of balance, e.g.villages and dungens,
	use d6s.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Channelled Magic</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Theurgic, Channelled, or Sponsored Magic is magic whose power has been channelled 
	from a third party ``god'', demon or celestial agent of some description.  Often
	a shared symbol is used to establish or strengthen the conduit between a caster
	and the third-party source.  In this type of magic the caster typically acts as
	an agent for the third-party, allowing the third-party to project their power and
	their influence.
      </p>

      <p>
	Those with an enquiring mind may be wondering where the third-party gets their
	energy from.  It seems clear that many gain their power from planar magics.
	For the so-called 'gods' it has been surmised that the act of prayer forms a
	conduit with the god through which some small part of the devotees animus travels.
	Thus people pray to a god,  the god gains animus,  the god grants power to clerics
	to project the gods interest, the clerics use this power to protect those of their
	faith and convert new devotees, .. and so on.  Though, this is just a theory and
	such musings are clearly not meant for mere mortals such as ourselves.  Many
	religions have also practiced sacrifice as a faster and simpler way of providing
	animatic energies to their deity.
      </p>

    </subsubsection>

<!--
    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Triggered Conduits</subsubsectiontitle>

      <p>
	Linked things have potential.
      </p>

</subsubsection>

Recharging.. roll a dice. on a 6 you charge the item one dice.  on a one you lose the dice.

      <p>
	Magic has a colour.  The colour is determined by its original source.  Ultimately
	all magic comes from planar 
      </p>
-->
</subsection>



</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Laws of Flux</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    In order for magic to happen thaumic energies must flow.  
    It does not matter in which direction magic flows across a potential difference it 
    may still be harnessed, as a water mill may be located upstream or downstream from a 
    waterfall and still do work, all that is required is that the magic flows.
  </p>

  <p>
    Stopping the flow stops the magic.  Hindering the flow hinders the magic.
    <bold>To use magic there must be a potential and a flow.</bold>  Certain magical
    symbols, chiefly the pentagram and the circle, when carved, drawn or laid out upon
    the ground in salt will stop the flow of magic (salt is used because it is
    non-conductive, granular, common, cheap, and white.. which makes it easier to see
    any discontinuities in the sumbols).
  </p>

  <p>
    An alternate problem happens when there is too much conductivity.  In practice
    this happens when there is too much water around, e.g. when it rains, or when
    the caster is standing in a puddle.  Here the caster is likely to dissipate more
    energy than they otherwise would.
  </p>

  
  
</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Law of Contagion</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    Magic shapes and binds all things.  Objects that share similarities are linked by 
    magical ties.  These ties can be used to strengthen magical spells.  For example, having 
    the blood or hair of a person can be used to strengthen a spell used on that subject.  
  </p>


  <subsubsection>
    <subsubsectiontitle>Blood Magic</subsubsectiontitle>
  
  <p>
    Note that a characters magic dice pool represents the amount of inner magical energy
    the character has available to draw upon when resisting magical effects.
    However, that is only a small fraction of the total creatures life force, their
    <defn>Animus</defn>.
  </p>

  <p>
    The power of <defn>Blood Magic</defn> is derived from thaumaturgical contagion between
    the blood and the animus of the subject.  Blood magic drains the animus from the subject.
    When a caster or monster uses a form of blood magic to drain a targets animus roll the
    targets magic pool.  The caster or monster then receives extra blood magic dice equal to
    the total of the subjects magic roll, e.g. a character with a 2d6 magic pool is drained,
    rolls 7 on their magic pool, then the the caster receives an extra 7 temporary blood
    magic dice.
  </p>    
  

  <p>
    Blood magic is temporary.  Once lost the only way the caster or monster can get more
    dice is to drain more subjects.
  </p>
  </subsubsection>


  <subsubsection>
    <subsubsectiontitle>Symbolic Contagion</subsubsectiontitle>
  
    <p>
      Similar symbols form flux lines connected by contagion.  Ritual use of special
      patterns can form an association to other locations and other realms.  Holy symbols
      form conduits between theurgic source, a deity or demon, and the caster.  Shared
      symbols carved into portals tie one portal end point to another.
    </p>
      
  </subsubsection>


  <subsubsection>
    <subsubsectiontitle>Temporal Contagion</subsubsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Events that occur at the same time are connected by contagion.  This allows
      casters to draw on the power of great celestial and planar events, e.g. the
      alignment of the planets, in order to increase the power of specific spells.
      Similarly, various times of the year are more auspicious for casting
      certain rituals because of the contagion with the previous castings of the
      spell at the same time of the year.      
    </p>
  </subsubsection>




  <subsubsection>
    <subsubsectiontitle>Words of Power</subsubsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Words are the key to magic.  When the first great spell casters,
      monumentally powerful inter-planar beings, cast their spells they
      did so while intoning in Innochian, the language of magic.  Intoning
      the same words forms a contagious link with the original castings
      and other castings of this spell through time.
    </p>

    <p>
      Magic words may also be used to train the invokers thoughts and 
      to gain the attention of other worldly beings, like ringing a bell
      in the dark.      
    </p>
  </subsubsection>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Law of Conductivity</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    Different materials effect the flow of magic differently.  Natural and biological 
    materials such as flesh, wood, and water conduct magic very well.   Ferrous metals 
    glass, and rock do not conduct magic well and can interfere with its casting in
    unpredictable ways.  
  </p>

  <p>
    Iron interferes with the flow of magic.  Magical creatures, particularly the Fey,
    do not like it.  Non-ferrous metals.. Platinum, Gold, Silver, Copper, etc also
    conduct magic well, though scholars are in disagreement as to why these do so,
    given iron does not.  Silver, is a particularly excellent conductor and so
    adversely affects those possessed by extra planar beings such as the undead and
    lycanthropes.
  </p>

  <p>
    Magical circles break conductivity (and therefore also break contagion).
    What the circle is made of generally doesn't matter.  Though there are specialized 
    protective circles for the protection of particular beings that while more 
    powerful require special ingredients, (e.g. salt for vampires).
  </p>

  <p>
    If a spell is over-charged it may be possible to <defn>Ground-Out</defn>
    the spell.  By using a conductive tool, typically a wooden staff, carved 
    appropriately, a character can ground-out a spell by holding it and planting 
    the end on the earth.  This removes either the highest or lowest die from the 
    result, at the characters discretion, and places it back in the characters pool.
  </p>

  <p>
    Ferrous armour disrupts the flow of magical energies and adversly affects 
    grounding.  It is impossible to ground-out magic when wearing armour.
    Similarly, if using a wooden shafted spear with a ferrous head then only the 
    lowest die may be removed as the metal head interferes with the thaumaturgical 
    conductivity of the shaft.
  </p>
  
  <p>
    Water, and particularly running water, is an excellent magical channel.
    Characters casting magic in standing water lose dice from their result 
    when rolling a 1 or 2.  In running water they lose dice on a result of 1-3.
    In addition, running water breaks contagion.
  </p>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Conduits</subsectiontitle>
    
    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Proximal Contagion</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Things that are close to one another are linked by proximal contagion.
	This is why many spells have a range.  Beyond that range it becomes
	difficult to form a decent conduit.  Magic at great distance is very difficult.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>

    
    
    <p>
    WHAT ARE WE SAYING HERE?
    
      Establishing a conduit .
      Evocation

      Blood, Flesh and Indulgence?

      running water.. 

      sunrises

      talking through planes.
    </p>


    <p>
      If a magical act draws upon a flow of energies from this plane to some other lower 
      potential plane then energies are expended from this plane, then the temperature will 
      drop, lights will dim and ice may form.  We call such an action an endothaumic 
      reaction.  In contradistinction, if energy flows to this plane from some higher 
      plane then the magic is of a type named exothaumic and the tell-tale side effects 
      of such practice are smoke of a sulfurous nature, bright lights and heat.  Magic 
      that results from intra-planar sources, that is magic from stored sources has no 
      such side-effects.
    </p>

    <p>
      Name can be used to create a conduit to allow channelling of energy.
    </p>

    <p>
      Possession - conduit from some external entity to a person.
      Gates - opens a door to a different dimension and the creature itself can arrive.
    </p>

    <p>
      gestures, ingredients, verbalization .. a form of contagion.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Portals</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Portals are pathways between or within planes that allow travel or projection 
      through those portals.  There are two types of portal, Lesser and Greater Portals.  
      Lesser portals are pin-hole sized, that are too small for physical travel and only 
      allow communication of for beings to project their will through.  The lesser portal 
      is briefly opened, usually requiring assistance at the destination, and 
      the being uses this channel to create a simulacrum of themselves through the portal.
      The facsimile is created by congealling ectoplasm from the environment.
      When the lesser portal is shut this breaks any link through the portal.  However, 
      the simulacrum remains linked with their parent by contagion.
    </p>

    <p>
      Greater portals require huge amounts of thaumaturgical energy to create and to keep 
      open.  Once open they allow beings to physically pass from one plane to another.
    </p>

    <p>
      Opening portals is extremely dangerous as their are countless beings lying 
      in wait, in a manner not to disimilar to the way the barbarians of the north fish
      for seal through the ice.  Hungrilly waiting through the eons.  
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Corollary of Knowledge</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    Theurgical fluxes bind all things.  The better a caster understands these fluxes 
    for a subject the easier it is for the magic user to cast spells that effect the subject.
    Knowledege is power.  The greater the knowledge the magical practitioner has about 
    his subject the more power they have over that subject <indexentry>rules of magic, 
    knowledge is power</indexentry>.  The GM, at their discretion, should grant one or 
    two extra dice to the magical practitioner, if the practioner can demonstrate 
    special knowledge about the subject. Knowing the true name of a magical being 
    grants an additional dice.  Similarly having an accurate physical or mental model
    or representation of the target of a spell gives you an extra dice.
  </p>
</section>





