


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Scenes</sectiontitle>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Requirements</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A Scene, like a scene in a play,  is a way of breaking up
      the action in a game into bits that the GM can design and share
      and reason about.
    </p>

    <p>
      Some scenes will have to be extemporaneous, ad lib affairs, that
      the GM throws together on the fly.  This chapter is more about
      planned scenes where the GM has the luxury of planning.  Combat
      can also be regarded as a scene, so the points made in this chapter
      may apply.  But it is different enough to warrant its own examination
      in a following chapter.
    </p>

    <p>
      We would suggest that a good scene has the following parts to it:
      <list>
	<li>A Purpose, or a dramatic question</li>
	<li>Conflict which may be combat, but might also be traps, hazards, diplomacy,</li>
	<li>A dilemma, a choice for the players to make</li>
	<li>One or more Time Constraints,</li>
	<li>Stakes or Rewards,</li>
	<li>Multiple outcomes from favourable to unfavourable, and</li>
	<li>Pointers .. where to next in case players get stuck?</li>
      </list>
    </p>

    <p>
      FIXME: brief bit on each part..  purpose could be exposition, increase tension, character development etc.
    </p>
    <p>
      If the game seems to slowed down, go with Raymond Chandlers advice: "When in doubt, have a man come through a door with a crossbow in his hand."
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Other Ideas..</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Embrace episodic game play.  Cut out exploring store-rooms, uneventful travel.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
</section>



<section>
  <sectiontitle>Darkness</sectiontitle>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Darkness</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
darkness
 - crank the chances of a random encounter way up because of omnidirectional torches
 - add occasional rooms where torches won't or shouldn't stay lit (wind, flammable gas)
 - crank up the chances (read: add a chance) of torches going out during combat
I want to improve the effectiveness of darkness as a environmental effect even when there is some light source.
 - any creature moving in the outside the torchlight is invisible
    </p>

  </subsection>
  
</section>
