

<!-- 

FIXME:  monster pool checks how do you deal with it?  Answer pool per monster group.

-->

<section>
  <sectiontitle>Combat</sectiontitle>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Simplified Combat</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Most monsters are simplified.  They get an Attack DC and a Defence DC and
      perhaps an ability or two.  Usually monsters don't get Stamina and their Morale is
      simplified as well.  FIXME: examples and expand.
    </p>	   
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Negotiation</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The GM should encourage intra-combat negotiation as it promotes
      character development, plot development exposition and resolving conflict
      through non-combat means.
    </p>

    <p>
      Negotiation will only occur if one side is predisposed to talking and the
      other side is capable of understanding the attempt at communication.
      For example, a charging bear probably will not
      stop and have a chat with the player characters, while a group of Orcs may or
      may not, depending on how hungry they are.  Usually, rational and intelligent
      characters will talk, if given the opportunity, in an attempt to try and avoid
      combat and reduce the chances of their own death.
    </p>

    <p>          
      Negotiation does not happen after an Ambush.  Similarly a surprised party cannot
      initiate a negotiation.  If a surprising party decides to initiate a negotiation
      they lose any advantage they gained from Surprise.
    </p>
  </subsection>  



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Combat Underwater</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      FIXME: Piercing weapons do full damage, crushing weapons do none, other weapons do half.
    </p>	        
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Action Oriented Encounters</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      FIXME:  Action driven monsters.. Give bosses special abilities on given turns
      and special reactions to make combats unique (Colville)
    </p>	        
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Random Encounters</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Random encounters are events that happen to the party that are not instigated
      by the party. Random encounters serve two primary purposes in the game:
    </p>

    <list>
      <li>
	Random encounters provide a disincentive for the characters
	to camp and ``turtle''.  The threat of constant danger should
	encourage them to keep moving forward, and to keep the story
	moving forward as well.
      </li>

      <li>
	Random encounters do not all have to be bad.  They can be used to provide
	the characters with useful information.
      </li>
    </list>

    <p>
      In order to determine when a random event occurs determine the threat
      level of the characters locale.  In the wilderness the threat level might
      be in the range 4 to 6.  In an enemy stronghold it might be 8 to 12.  Get
      one of the players to roll a standard check against that difficulty.  If
      they fail a random encounter occurs.
    </p>      
  </subsection>

</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Pursuit</sectiontitle>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Stages of a Pursuit</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      At some point the characters are going to want to flee from an opponent or to
      chase a fleeing opponent.  This section descibes rules for fleeing and pursuit.
    </p>

    <p>
      There are four stages of pursuit:
    </p>

    <p>
      FIXME: Do we need a distinction between running down and chasing??
      how is this different from chasing?  Make them the same thing?

      what happens if you run on the plains??  it's not pursuit!!  it's running-down.
      chase versus pursue??  The difference is in what options are available
      long term running down??
      maybe running down is just a limited variant of chase?      
    </p>

    <p>
      FIXME: PURSUIT MODIFIERS?
      Random Chase Roll modifiers.. (rolled by the quarry)
      +1 for streetwise or something??
      -1 for strange city
      +1 for night time.
    </p>


    <p>
      FIXME: ??
      What does Run do?  can you run forever?
      Run .. choose to check to sprint?
      Flee.. choose?

      

      fixed number of turns??
      evade checks get +1 per round??
      What stops everyone running.. stalemate?
      can't pursue in a building??  (not big enough.. get outside then flee)
      special events?

      ... how do you catch up.. some random events (2d8 .. odds bad for runners)
      lookup tables for events.

      Make Run description in ability agree with Tun in pursuit.
      When do you Run?
    </p>
    
    
    <descriptions>
      
      <term>Disengaging</term>
      <description>
	If a group is trying to flee from combat they must first disengage.
	When playing on a grid this means they must make it to the edge of
	the grid and leave the map.  If playing using TOTM the group disengages
	when all members run from the combat.  At this point they are distant 
	enough from the battle that they are considered to be out of combat.
	In order for their attackers to start combat with them again they must
	be successfully pursued.
      </description>

      <term>Decide to Pursue</term>
      <description>
	Pursuit is optional.  Characters with the Checked condition cannot pursue.
      </description>

      <term>Chasing</term>
      <description>
	Chasing is the most complicated of these steps and we cover it in more detail
	in the next section.
      </description>

      <term>Running Down</term>
      <description>
	Running down occurs on plains, deserts and in lightly wooded terrain when
	the quarry has successfully avoided the chase.  Unfortunately in this case
	there is nowhere to hide, the quarry are <measurement><metric>one kilometre</metric>
	<imperial>half a mile</imperial></measurement> ahead of the pursuers and they
	have to outrun their pursuers or get to somewhere where they can evade the pursuit.
      </description>

      <term>Tracking</term>
      <description>
	Occurs when the pursuer can no longer see the quarry.  In forests, or jungles 
	they have to use the Tracking skill vs their opponents Evasion.  In cities
	they might have to question people, possibly using diplomacy, intimidation,
	or bribery.
      </description>
    </descriptions>
    
    <p>
      Of these four steps, Chasing is the only one that is not covered elsewhere so
      we will cover that here.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Chasing</subsectiontitle>
    
    <p>
      Chasing occurs when one group is pursuing another and the pursued group is
      intermittently visible, there is broken ground to slow the pursuers, or
      the quarry is running to some safe location.  The pursuers just need to close
      the distance between them and their quarry.   The quarry just need to get far
      enough ahead that they can slip away or reach safety.
    </p>

    <p>
      Pursuit works as follows.  Assign every member of the pursuit an initial chase
      rank that represents their position in the chase.  Give the lead pursuer a rank
      of 5 and other pursuers lower ranks. Now assign higher ranks to those being pursued
      relative to the lead pursuer.  For example the members of the quarry closest to the
      lead pursuer might get an initial rank of 6 or 7.  If there are members of the
      quarry who started running earlier then they might get an initial rank of 8, or 9.
    </p>

    <p>
      Every turn of the chase each member of the chase takes an action, see below
      for a list of example actions.  Most of these actions will effect their chase
      rank or the rank of other members of the chase.
    </p>

    <descriptions>
      <term>Move</term>
      <description>
	Increase rank by 2.
      </description>

      <term>Run or Flee</term>
      <description>
	Both Run and Flee are double movement actions increasing your rank by 2.  Both these
	abilities also allow you to optionally check versus movement and, if successful,
	increase your rank by 3, if the check fails then you increase your rank by 2 and gain
	the Tired condition.  If the character already has the Tired condition then they
	gain the Exhausted condition instead.  Fleeing is the same as Running except that 
	in addition you need to make a morale check in order to stop fleeing.
      </description>
      
      <term>Ranged Attack</term>
      <description>
	Make a missile attack.  If the weapon is tagged Fast then the character
	can also increase their chase rank by one.  Boons might slow a pursuer down
	as they take cover.
      </description>

      <term>Reload Slow Weapons</term>
      <description>
	Reload slow missile weapons.  The character takes the whole round to reload their
	weapon.
      </description>
      
      <term>Create Obstacle</term>
      <description>
	The character does something that will slow their pursuers.  Characters can only
	perform this action if they can describe a feasible way to slow their pursuers.
	For example they might tip over a cart in a town.  However on a plain there
	might be no way to create an obstacle.
      </description>
      
      <term>Evasion</term>
      <description>
	If successful then the character gains rank +4.  Otherwise they are set to the
	same rank as the lead pursuer.
      </description>
      
      <term>Melee Attacks</term>
      <description>
	When the lead pursuers rank is the same as that of the trailing quarry,
	the pursuer and the quarry may make melee attacks against one another.
	If they do so they increase their chase rank only one.
      </description>      
    </descriptions>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>When does a Chase End?</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Chases end when some predetermined condition is reached.  The three most
      common conditions are: <defn>When the Pursuit is Lost</defn>, 
      <defn>Upon Arrival at a Destination</defn>, and <defn>When the Quarry is Run
      Down</defn>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Pursuit is lost when the lowest ranking quarries rank is greater than the
      highest pursuers rank plus five at the end of the round.  In this case the
      quarry has evaded their pursuers.

      <equation>
	<line>Pursuit is Lost:</line>
	<line>Lowest Quarry Rank <geqqsymbol/> Highest Pursuer Rank + 5</line>
      </equation>      
    </p>

    
    <p>
      In certain scenarios there is some safe place to which the quarry is fleeing,
      for example, imagine a group of Halflings fleeing towards a river ferry while
      pursued by dark horsemen.  In these situations the ferry is represented by its 
      own chase rank.  Any of the quarry that reach the specified rank have arrived
      at their destination.
    </p>

    <p>
      When a pursuers chase rank <emph>exceeds</emph> the rank of the trailing quarry
      that quarry is said to be Run Down.  At this point the quarry can no longer flee
      and is back in combat.
    </p>    
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Random Encounters while Chasing</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Random encounters may occur during a chase.  The chase might run into
      a midnight procession of the worshippers of the gods of bachanalia,
      maybe there is a cart blocking the path, or they run into the night watch.	
      Refer to chase events table for random events.

      FIXME
    </p>	        
  </subsection>  
</section>
