<section>
  <sectiontitle>Introduction</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    This chapter contains information about the various Cults and their nefarious
    doings.
  </p>
</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>Cult of the Black Goat</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    FIXME
  </p>
</section>



<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Children of the Deep</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    A secret cult that 
    FIXME
  </p>
</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Chosen</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    Obsessed with purity of spirit the Chosen are a large
    militant cult 
    FIXME
  </p>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Ghoul Cult</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    FIXME
  </p>
</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Black Seers of Axxum</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    Obsessed with purity of spirit the Chosen are a large
    militant cult 
    FIXME
  </p>
</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>Followers of the Light</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    The followers of the light are a secret cult whose existance remains a rumour.
    This cult is obssessed with gaining knowledge and secrecy.  They have made a terrible
    pact for which they have received the prolonged life and the ability to see the future.  Their
    agents move in the shadows to attempt to shape the future for the benefit of its members.
  </p>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Zwergzaibatsu</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    There are a number of quite large Dwarven conglomerate businesses, such as Iron Hill Mining, and
    Laibstadt Foundries, that own and operate a large number of smaller businesses.  These companies
    are usually owned and run by particular dwarven extended families, they have their own small banks,
    and are their own political entities.  They fund prospecting and the creation of new trade routes and
    industries, bribe politicians and push for legal changes.  Sometimes they strong-arm smaller
    organizations out of business.  The worst are not above arson, smuggling, bribery and other
    illicit activities.
  </p>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Zwergeninvestitionen</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    Dwarves have a large number of money-lending institutions.  Backing many of these is the
    Zwergeninvestitionen, a not-for-profit Dwarven Central Bank.  This institution lends money
    to Dwarven money-lenders, governments and large businesses.  These activities are used to
    fund the Dwarven Grudge Keeping arm of the organization, a band of militant bankers
    encharged with balancing the Book of Grudges or Grollbuch.  Sins of blood are recorded
    in the book of grudges by Grudge Keepers and the Dwarves spend considerable effort ensuring
    that these debts are paid in full.   Entries in the Grollbuch range from Zwerggild for the
    death of an individual to revenge against entire enemy nations (the largest consolidated debt in
    the book is owed to the Orcish Tribes).  There are many copies of the Book of Grudges
    distributed throughout the Dwarven colonies and these are constantly being updated with entries
    from far off book keepers to try and keep the books consolidated.
  </p>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Sodality of the Grey Monks</sectiontitle>
  <p>
  </p>
</section>


