
<section>
  <sectiontitle>Magic Items and Arcana</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    Herein lies the descriptions, such as they are, of the magical
    items that are widely known to any prepared to open a book and
    read.  Such creations are very rare and common folk may go their
    entire lives without ever seeing one.
  </p>  

  <!--
      http://hyboria.xoth.net/sorcery/sorcerous_societies.htm
      http://hyboria.xoth.net/sorcery/magical_items.htm
  -->

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Alkahest</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Even more rare and corrosive than the Bile of the White Wyrm, Alkahest
      is the universal solvent the result of the titrations and secret alchmical
      processes of master Alchemists.  Contained in small granite pots it can only
      be used for a few days after its creation as by that time it has eaten through
      its container.  Alkahest dissolves everything known to man.
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Amulet of the Martyr</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This amulet bears once belonged to a devotee of a god who was martyred
      for their cause.  Blood from the martyr has infused the symbol and allows
      the character to reroll lost magic dice after a spell is cast.  On a six
      the die is not lost.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ansible of the Gates/Ansible Portarum</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      An Ansible of the Gates is a small obsidian box, perhaps the size of a
      matchbox, inlaid with golden sigils such as a circle and pentagram.  The
      box feels hollow but there does not appear to be any means to open it.
    </p>

    <p>
      These boxes are used to entrap and contain demons.  If opened the demon
      within will escape and attack those around it.  If the box is put to the
      ear the demon will be able to whisper to the listener and may have
      conversations with them.  The demon will initially lie about the nature
      of the box and attempt to win them over.  Helping them in whatever way it
      can.  Its goal at this stage will be to attempt to get the listener to
      put the box somewhere where it will be badly damaged, releasing the demon.
      If found out the demon will attempt to intimidate the listener.  If that fails
      they will attempt to bargain with them, trading knowledge for their freedom.
      Finally, if all else fails the demon might resort to begging the listener for
      their freedom.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Apples of Derketa</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Fruit</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A deadly poisonous fruit found in the jungles to the south.
      The blackish juice causes death in seconds and the poison works
      by both contact and ingestion. The fruit was given this name by the Kushites.      
    </p>
  </subsection>

  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Athame of Tyaa</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Tags</term><description>magical, dagger, weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A fine black handled dagger.  The handle is inlaid with ivory.  The blade has
      an intricate golden filigree crow motiff.  Does damage +2 and counts as a magical blade,
      If the wielder is not a devotee of Tyaa then for every 1 rolled on a luck check, another die in
      the check with a face value greater than one, must be rerolled.  If there are no such dice then
      no reroll is required.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Hammer of the Dwarvish Lords</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>one dice</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This is a Dwarven Hammer, made by
      a master craftsman and ensorcelled with a rune of power.
      It does +1 damage, or +2 damage when wielded by a dwarf.
      The character can make a check and strike it upon the ground,
      if successful then all creatures within
      <measurement><metric>10m</metric><imperial>30'</imperial></measurement>, except the wielder,
      must check against agility or fall over, gaining the Prone condition.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Bag of Smoked Snigglets</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
    </descriptions>
    
    <p>
      A small bag containing 3d6 snigglets.  Salted garlic snigglets
      are, of course, a delicacy from far-off Arbonard.  Their
      moluscy, truffley flavour is overwhelming.  They are a famed
      aphrodisiac, and some say highly addictive treat.  Once tasted
      they can be used to provide +3 to a single negotiate test.
      Requires fresh swamp snigglets to make.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Bell of Bereavement</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This brass bell is about the size of a kettle and
      mounted upon an ebon handle.  The bell has
      many strange Enochian symbols carved upon it.
      When rung it will attract any undead in the area.
      Zombies and skeletons in particular will be unable
      to resist the call of the bell.      
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Bile of the White Wyrm</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>30gp</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      Kept in special silver vials with a screwable lid, the
      bial of the white wyrm is highly corrosive, disolving
      wood, stone, flesh, ferrous metals, leathers and materials.
      It comes from the stomachs of the great wyrms of the northern
      wastes.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Binding Stone</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A Binding Stone is a runic magic device designed to
      trap some magical being to the location by disrupting
      the flow of magical energies in the vicinity.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Black Candle</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>No</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>As per spell</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>50gp</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      A black candle has been specially crafted for use in necromantic and arcane spells.
      When used while casting a necromantic or arcana spell  the candle adds 1d6 to
      the magic pool prior to the check to cast the spell (use a different
      coloured die to represent the candle).
    </p>

    <p>
      Any number of candles may be used per casting but their combined
      contribution is the maximum result of the candles. For example suppose
      three candles are used in a necromantic spell, each candle rolls 1d6 towards
      the magic and
      gets the following results: 3, 6, and 1.  The combined contribution to
      the casting of all three candles is 6.  The candle that rolled the 1 is exhausted
      and cannot be used again.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Blood-Drinker</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Sword</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A blood drinker is a sword or dagger created by foul vampyres 
      in a ritual that baptizes the weapon in their blood infusing it
      with some of their dark powers. 
      Every time the sword hits a living creature it does
      1 damage to health.  If the sword strikes the killing
      blow for a human or elf that creature has a 33<percent/>
      chance of rising as a lesser vampyre upon the next
      full moon.
    </p>

    <p>
      While blood drinkers are often decorated with the
      heraldic emblems of their creators family: wolves,
      moons, bats, spirits, and the like.  Occasionally they
      are decorated with the symbols of light: the sun,
      eagles, lions, bears, roses and the like.  Scholars
      believe that vampyres make these swords as the 
      creation of tools for the perversion of good brings
      great amusement and pleasure to them.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Book of Leviathan</subsectiontitle>        
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>Casters Magic Pool</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>100</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>105</description>
    </descriptions>        
    <p>
      Written by the mad monk Thelonius Freidburg in his own blood, immediately
      before his suicide, the Book of Leviathan describes a way to open a gate of
      immense proportions, allowing the reader to summon forth one of the Gods beyond
      the veil, leading to the almost certain destruction of this world.  Many
      believe that the Book is a legend told to frighten overly inquisitive young
      practioners.  
    </p>

    <p>
      A number of attempts have been made to destroy the book but it is surprisingly
      resilient, being warded from physical damage.  It is theorized that the book
      is a fetish and forms a contagious connection with some god in another plane.
      Therefore the only way to destroy the book is to return it from whence it came
      and destoy it there.
    </p>	  
    
    <p>
      The Book is an immensely corrupting influence on those around it.  It is
      contained in a large box of meteoric iron, protected by dwarven runes and
      a small poisonous needle trap.  Once the box is opened the book is revealled.
      The book is well known, and any magic-user can make an Std Check vs 7
      to recognize it.
    </p>

    <p>
      Using True Sight on the book or touching it requires the character to make three
      consecutive Break Checks exhausting dice on a 3 or less.  If they fail they gain the
      <emph>Servant of Leviathan</emph> aspect.  They may have to flee raving like
      a lunatic as well.  The book seeks the end of the world and will attempt to get
      the characters to take it to someone capable and willing to do so.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Brazen Head</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Statue</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Small brass primitive statue that depicts a XXXX.
      The statue fits comfortably in the palm of your hand.
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Bright Blade</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions> 
    <p>
      FIXME Two handed flaming Sword.. very heavy
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Colloidal Silver</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Colloidal Silver is silver ground very finely and suspended in
      a liquid substrate, usually oil.  When poured upon a weapon
      it gives that weapon the <emph>Silvered</emph> tag for the duration
      of the next combat or the next day, whichever is shorter.
    </p>

    <p>
      Colloidal silver can be made using the Alchemy skill,
      some silver (<eg/> a silver coin) and some oil.  It takes about an
      hour to prepare.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Compendium Maleficarum</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item, Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>None</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>Once per day</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
      <term>Price</term><description>100gp</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      The Compendium Maleficarum is a witch-hunter's manual.
      If the reader chooses they may take the <emph>Thou shalt not suffer a witch to live</emph>
      Aspect.  If they do so then with daily perusal of the compendium they may reroll a mettle
      check once per day.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Compass of Seeking</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>Once per day</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>3000gp</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      The needle of this fine golden compass always points in
      the direction of the last object that has been
      imprinted upon it.  In order to imprint an object on the
      compass a spell caster needs to make a DDC:10 magic check.
      The compass may be confounded by travel over open water (and to a
      lesser extent open seas) or via magical means such as a
      Circle of Protection.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Conlon Stoutfoot's Runcible Spoon</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Not being of a particularly magical bent, the Halfling race has
      yet to produce a wielder of magic of almost any note.  The chief
      exception raised by Halflings in opposition to this point is that
      of Conlon Stoutfoot, perhaps best known amongst Halflings for his
      recipe for duck pie with chives.  However, he is only slightly less
      well known for his, somewhat mediocre, magical achievements.
    </p>

    <p>
      As a youth Conlon journeyed widely in an attempt to discover new
      meal times.  He gained some notoriety for his discovery of Tiffin
      but was thrown into scandal when he claimed to have discovered
      Brunch.  His critics claimed that Brunch was just another name
      for Tiffin and that he was merely a mendacious clock fiddler.
    </p>

    <p>
      Stung to the quick by these acusations, Conlon left his Halfling
      settlement for the last time.  It is said that he travelled widely.
      It is known that he dabbled in magical matters that are better
      left undabbled, and spent much time in the presence of people
      he should have known better than to have done so.  He disappeared
      some thirty years ago and it is presumed that he has died,
      a victim of his own folly.
    </p>

    <p>
      Interestingly, a gift arrived addressed to all of Conlon's
      heartiest detractors some ten years after Conlon's disappearance..
      a particularly fine runcible spoon of clear magical power.  Upon
      stirring a dish with the spoon, that dish becomes incredibly
      delicious.  The discovery of its power led to immediate and widespread
      chaos, and a number of physical altercations amongst the Halfling
      cognoscenti.  This fractiousness continued for a number of months
      until The Spoon mysteriously vanished.  Some say that it returned
      to the demon plane from whence it came,  while others claim that
      someone probably nicked it to make a few bob.  Whatever the truth is,
      it is lost in the mists of time.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Coronet of the Elf Kings</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Cultes des Goules</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Cultist's Candle</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>No</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>As per spell</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>50gp</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      This candle has been specially crafted for use in dark magics.
      When used in a conjuration or evocation spell the candle adds 1d6 to
      the magic pool prior to the check to cast the spell (use a different
      coloured die to represent the candle).
    </p>

    <p>
      Any number of candles may be used per casting but their combined
      contribution is the maximum result of the candles. For example suppose
      three candles are used in a evocation, each candle rolls 1d6 and gets the
      following results: 3, 2, and 5.  The contribution to the casting of all
      three candles is 5.  The candle that rolled 2 is exhausted and may not
      be used again.  The use of the candles must be declared before the
      spell is cast and takes a round to light each candle (assuming the
      caster already has a method to light the candles.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Dhol Chants</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Draught of Living Death</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Potion</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>1</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A potion that places the embiber in a state of sleep that makes them seem
      like they are dead for an hour.  It will be extremely difficult to
      tell through non-magical means that the embiber is not actually dead
      (they are just mostly dead and as we all know, there is a big difference
      between mostly dead and all dead).  One of the main ingredients of this
      potion is the venom of a serpent.
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Durandil</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions> 
    <p>
      FIXME Sword
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Dwarven Compass</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>d20</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Various Dwarven Rune Masters have created a number of magical compasses
      with two or more needles pointing to any combination of the following:
      <list>
        <li>Toward magnetic North</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest source of water</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest evil thing</li>
        <li>Aligned with the nearest ley line</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest iron deposit</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest copper deposit</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest gold deposit</li>
      </list>
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Doctrine of the Small Gods</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>
    
    <p>
      There are many minor and highly specialized deities that
      spy on this world from planes both near or deep.  Hungry for
      attention they listen for prayers.  This slight book is dedicated
      to the small gods and contains the scrawlings of a gibbering
      prophet.  Amongst the deranged rambling text are 1d4 + 1 prayers
      to various highly specialized, highly obscure, and very minor
      deities.  When read the character may ask for a small boon
      from the god.     Once all the spells have been cast the book
      collapses into a different dimension in order to spread the word.
    </p>

    <p>
      The default chance to succeed is Very Difficult using a std check.
      The difficulty level can be reduced by one step if the character
      provides suitable embellishment for his prayer (e.g. the name of
      the small god, their varied domains, and their achievements).
      The difficulty level can be reduced by a further step if the task
      is very specific and very minor or increased by a step if the task
      is demanding of the small god.      
    </p>      
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Enochian Keys</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      This set of steel keys is marked with runic passages that swim before the eye.
      Occult literature states that they can open the gates to hell, though it is
      vague is which hell they are referring to.
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Elixir contenant un tentacule squameux</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Potion, One-Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>3</description>
    </descriptions>        
    <p>
      A small vial containing an opaque green liquid, in which is suspended a,
      still twitching, sample of a squidlike tentacle.
      When ingested this potion heals 2d6 damage caused by burn type injuries
      including acid and electrical attacks.  These potions are created
      by the Frosch using some unknown dark magics.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Eyes of Azathoth</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Kept in little clay jars under a layer of oil, this onyx/silver dust when
      thrown in the air immediately ignites causing temporary blindness to those
      who fail a perception check against it DDC14, people who understand its use
      and who know it will be used gain a +5 to this save.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Foaming Plaster</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item, Trinket, One-Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>See Below</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>        
    <p>
      Foaming Plaster is a white pastey substance in a little
      terracotta clay pot (about the size of an apple) and sealed
      with red sealing wax. when the white paste touches the air
      it expands and hardens.  If left openeed the foaming plaster
      expands to about the size of a small keg of beer.  The pot can
      be resealed with fire.  Each pot contains four small applications
      or one large one.  The plaster takes about one round to set.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Gate of Tongues</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>2d6/month</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>8</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The Gate of Tongues is a book by the renowned author Comenius,
      that teaches the language of Aquillonian.  After two months
      of casual study, or one month of intense study, the reader
      can make a check to see if they have learned the language.
      If they succeed they gain Aquilonian III, if they fail they
      gain Aquilonian I.  If unsucessful, the reader can recheck every
      month.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Helm of the Minotaur</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Hand of Glory</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A Hand of Glory is the ensorcelled and embalmed severed hand
      of a murderer.   Each finger can be lit, like a candle, and
      each finger contributes 1d4 to a single spell cast while they are lit.
      The fingers burn rapidly and once lit they cannot be reused.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ignis Sacer</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item, Trinket</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A small pot of black powder.  When a pinch of the powder is
      consumed it induces hallucinations, nausea, vomiting, muscle
      pain and weakness, numbness, or itching rendering the consumer
      <emph>Poisoned</emph> for a period of 2d8 hours.  Requires
      rye bread and a few weeks of time to make.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Immovable Staff</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Medium Item</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d10</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>        
    <p>
      This staff is enscribed with two sets of Dwarvish runes.  When the user reads
      the first set of runes, which say ``Kegeth Ak'', the staff becomes fixed in space
      requiring a Strength check against a difficulty of 15 to move.  When the user
      speaks aloud the second set of runes, which say ``Elnär zór'', the staff becomes
      movable again.
    </p>

    <p>
      In addition the staff has a break save of 3.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Index Daemonorum</subsectiontitle>        
    <p>
      A leather bound tome of obvious, but ineffable age, the
      Index Daemonorum is clearly a vile artifact to any character
      with True Sight.  Its presence is disturbing to anyone
      receptive of magical energies.  
    </p>

    <p>
      The Index Daemonorum is a powerful artifact that incarcerates
      between the protective symbols of its enscribed bindings
      a greater demon, known by some as Inoch, or Metator, Adiryaon
      and to some as Mattatron.  The bound demon knows the deep secrets
      of many of those that move in the darkness.
    </p>

    <p>
      Magic users who touch the index gain the <emph>It Whispers</emph>
      aspect allowing the book to influence the careless through time and
      space.  It seeks the destruction of the book which will set it free,
      but the book is strongly warded.  It will try and gain information
      of how the wards may be lifted.  If it has no current paths of wnquiry,
      it will amuse itself with the destruction of people it believes
      have wronged it in the past, using its servants.
    </p>

    <p>
      Those who have touched the book may ask of it questions.  The book
      will write upon its pages the answers if it knows them, which it may well
      do. The reader should beware, however, as the book twists words just as it
      twists the souls of men.
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Iron Crown</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      FIXME? 
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Kismet Ring</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The wearer may make a check to reroll any Luck check.
      All dice must be rerolled.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Kotterszwerg's Arquebus</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      There were a limited number of these fine weapons made
      by Master Dwarven Gunsmith Augvst Kotterszwerg.
      A Kotterszwerg's Arquebus is a Masterwork quality arquebus
      which loses the inaccurate tag (so will hit on a successful
      to-hit Bane).  It is said that this accuracy derives
      from the spiral patterns engraved on the inner surface of the
      barrel.  Some say that the spiral pattern is some unknown
      form of Runic magic.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ley Stone</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Ley Stones are massive stone menhirs that were erected by the great
      druids before the first cities were built to mark the confluence of
      Ley Lines.  Spell casters with magickal skills may use ley lines 
      to gate to other ley nexuses.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Liber Ivonis</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A tome written by the dark wizard Eibon.
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Liber Juratus Honorii</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The Sworn Book of Honorious is a non-mgaical tome that
      covers witchcraft, the summoning of demons, the planes,
      devils and necromancy.  The reader may research within
      the tome for information pertaining to a subject once
      per day - reading takes time and it is not particularly
      well organized (in fact it's more a stream of consciousness
      Honorious was a mad leper imprisoned in a monastery).
      When doing so, the player makes a check DDC 13, Book Learning
      bonuses apply.  Depending on the question History or Theology
      may also be used (modifiers don't stack).  The more specific
      the question the harder the check (at the GMs discretion).
    </p>

    <p>
      On a success the GM should provide some vaguely related
      pieces of information related to the question asked that
      are probably useful and a little misinformation.
      On a successful boon the GM should provide an answer if
      that seems appropriate (it's a book, not a crystal ball).
      On a failure the GM should provide a lot of misinformation
      and some truth.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Limaceous Grease</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      Allows the player to squeeze into unnaturally small
      places when rubbed upon the skin.  Requires the ichor of a demon.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lotus Powder, Black</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Is made from the black lotus, whose blossoms wave in the
      lost jungles of Khitai, where only the yellow-skulled priests
      of Yun dwell. Those blossoms strike dead any who smell of them.
      When the Black Lotus powder is burned in an incense bowl, it
      produces a dark green smoke. Black Lotus is a lethal poison.
    </p>

    <p>
      FIXME

      In powder form, Black Lotus is treated as Dust of Sneezing and Choking.
      In liquid form it is treated as poison (contact DC 20, initial damage 3d6 Con, secondary damage 3d6 Con).
      When burned, inhaling the smoke of the black lotus has certain magic-restoring properties (see link above).
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lotus Powder, Purple</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The Purple Lotus Swamp lies in south-central Stygia and is the
      source of a plant whose juices produce temporary paralysis. The
      swamp is said to be haunted by ghosts.
    </p>

    <p>
      Under the effects of the purple lotus, the mind can sense everything
      but has no control at all over the body. Sorcerers use it in small
      doses to free their mind from the bonds of their bodies, but many
      unsavorily people use it for much darker purposes. The potion looks
      and smells like clear water and is undetectable.      
    </p>
  </subsection>
  


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lotus Powder, Yellow</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Yellow Lotus is a narcotic used for trances and visions.
      It blooms only in certain remote areas of Kush.
      The lotus itself is sometimes seen in these visions, and it could be
      that the flower itself exerts a malign influence through them.
      The inhabitants of Xuthal, an ancient city in the Southern Desert of Shem, were
      addicted to the yellow lotus and spent most of their lives in lotus-induced dreams.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lotus Powder, Grey</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Grey Lotus is a drug which in liquid form causes madness, found in
      the Grey Lotus Swamp east of Khitai. The madness causes the imbiber to
      become a raving berserk that attacks everything in sight with unnatural
      strength. The victim has no control of himself and will kill and destroy
      until the effect wears off in a few minutes.      
    </p>
  </subsection>
  


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lotus Powder, White</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This is a beneficial herb that heals wounds and cures disease. It is said to be cultivated in a
      secret place in Vendrhya.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lotus Powder, Golden</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      The juice of the golden lotus cures insanity and disease.
      It is even rumored that this potion can save a man poisoned
      by the black lotus.  It is not known where it blooms but
      it can be found from time to time for sale in the   
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Mirrors of the Prince of Shadows</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The Mirrors of the Prince of Shadows (Speculis Principes Umbras), are a
      set of silvered glass mirrors with brass frames carved with disturbing,
      other-worldly sigils.   They are transparent from one side and reflective
      from the other.   There purpose is to collimate ley line potential for the
      purpose of capturing ley energies.  When set up at the juncture of two or
      more Ley Lines they are able to concentrate Ley energy providing the caster
      with an extra +3 magic energy, only at that point and only for rituals.
    </p>

    <p>
      Anyone who gazes into the mirrors must check verses Mettle with difficulty
      12 or gain a temporary insanity condition.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Mourning Blade</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>


  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Necronomicon</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Orb of Elogh</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Cursed.. activates when touched.</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>3d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>Weekly</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>7</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      It is written that Aldinach, also known as The Hand in the Shadows,
      and The PuppetMaster, whispered temptations in the night to Elogh, Mage
      of the Second Circle instructing him to construct a wonderous work to
      his description.  Ambition overcoming caution, Elogh created the
      <emph>Orb of Elogh</emph>, a crystal orb containing vistas of swirling
      bilious green mists.  The Orb allows the weilder to raise and control the dead.
      Unfortunately for Elogh, canny Aldinach did not reveal that the number of dead
      controlled is signicantly smaller than the number raised.
    </p>

    <p>
      When touched the Orb raises an undead for each of the non-one dice in the pool.
      The character who touched the orb may control one undead for each of the dice
      with a result of four.  Uncontrolled undead will automatically attack the nearest
      non-undead opponent, preferring mammalian humanoids.  In the event that multiple
      targets are the same distance from the uncontrolled undead then the bearer of the
      orb can decide the target.  In the event that three 1s are rolled on the dice roll
      all undead in the region are raised -- Aldinach is a fickle god.
    </p>      

    <p>
      Aldinach watches the world through the orb and hungers.   If one raises the
      orb to ones ear Aldinach might speak to them, whispering sweet promisings.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Orcbane</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon.</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This is a Dwarven weapon, an Axe or a Hammer, made by
      a master craftsman and ensorcelled with a rune of power.
      It does +1 damage and does double damage against
      greenskins.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Pnakotic Manuscripts</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Pelagic Idol</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Idol</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Pompatus Chapeau</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A fine hat made by the great Elvish miliner Hylonus of Sylvannia
      that distracts all those who know anything about fashion.
      Civilized observers must make a difficult will power check
      or gain the Distracted condition the first time they see the hat
      in a non-combat situation.  Any character that wears
      this fine hat will be sure to be noticed.  Fey creatures are
      immune to its effects.
    </p>
  </subsection>  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Potion of Odic Visions</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      Lets the character see the auras of other beings for a short period
      of time.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Puzzlebox</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d6 to 10d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>1240gp</description>
      <term>Check</term><description>Dice Pool vs Opponents Endurance</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Pearl of Atlach-Nacha</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A glossy black sphere the size of a mans fist.  When the secret words 
      are spoken it hatches into an astral spider and attacks the being
      it is commanded to.  After some time the spider dies, unable to exist
      on this plane.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Poppet</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A small doll used in arcane rituals and curses.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Portal Chalk</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>d4 uses</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>            
    <p>
      This greenish looking stub of chalk is actually a powerful magical item that
      enables a magic user to draw a circle on a surface and create a magical
      portal that leads to a nearby location.  In order to make the chalk work the
      users must make a difficulty 5 check using their magic pool.  The portal created
      is a swirling translucent gate, but not transparent, vortex.  Furthermore the
      destination of the portal is chosen by magicks beyond the control of the user,
      though the destination is generally benign.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Potion of Entheogenesis</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This psychoactive potion can be used during theurgical rituals to gain a clearer
      channel to the casters patron.  If the check is sucessful then the
      caster gains +2 to their ritual check.
    </p>

    <p>
      The embiber must check verses Mettle with difficulty 7 or gain a temporary
      insanity condition.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Rabbits Foot</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Potion</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions> 
    <p>
      A specially ensorcelled rabbits foot created using
      secret rituals. After a check has been rerolled using
      the luck based Reroll ability, the rabbits foot allows
      a free second reroll of a check.    One use only.
      This item is the only way that a check may be rerolled
      twice.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ring of Gyges</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A ring of invisibility.. FIXME.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ring of the Serpent King</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Allows the wearer to mesmerize someone by looking into their eyes.
      They must make a Very Difficult Std Check added by their will power
      or gain a Hypnotized Aspect with a starting difficulty equal to 14
      minus their will power modifier or do as instructed.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ring of Luck</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A ring of luck appears to be a plain golden ring.
      On the inside of the ring is an enscription that says
      "Semper felix".  May be used to attempt to reroll dice.
      Once the dice pool is exhausted the ring must be passed
      on to a new recipient (and the dice pool is then
      refreshed).  This only works if the recipient has not used
      the ring before.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ring of the Rats</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The ring enables the wearer to check to transform into a rat
      for up to five minutes.  After the transformation the user
      gains the ``Craves Cheese'' aspect at difficulty 12 if they
      do not already have it.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ring of the Wraith</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Ring</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>3d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A ring embued with the will of a wraith.  It may reanimate 
      corpses as per the spell.  Will animate one human sized corpse
      for every point rolled over the difficulty.
    </p>

    <p>
      Part of the spirit of the wraith lies within the ring.  The
      spirit yearns for the death of innocents and will try to control
      the wearer.  The first time the ring is worn the wearer gains
      the "Under the Shadow of the Wraith" aspect at difficulty 10.
      When the opportunity arises to murder an innocent and get away
      with it the GM can attempt to compel the wearer.  If the compel
      succeeds the character murders the innocent but is unaware that
      they have done so (though maybe they are missing time or find
      blood on their shirt).  If the character attempts to get rid of
      the ring or tell others about it they must first roll to see if
      they are compelled by the ring (Compel Own PC).  If successful
      they may remove the ring or tell others about it, otherwise they
      may not.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Runehammer</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>4d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The Runehammers are ancient Dwarvish artifacts.  For game
      purposes they are high quality war hammers.  They have however
      been ensorcelled with magics that allow them to shatter
      magical protective barriers on a successful cast.  
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Scroll of Bubastis</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Scroll</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Written by the High Priest Luveh-Keraph of Bast.  This scroll describes
      the worship of the ghoul-goddess, and the Black Rites of Bast.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Seven League Boots</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Boots</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The Seven League Boots grant extra speed.  The owner can
      make a DC 4 check using the items magic pool.  If successful
      they can make two move actions in a turn.  The boots' magic pool
      refreshes after a long rest.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Soul Stealer</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions> 
    <p>
      FIXME Sword
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Snaga</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions> 
    <p>
      FIXME Northern Battle Axe
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Spirits of Quickening</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <!-- <term>Refresh</term><description>1d6</description> -->
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The drinker has three turns per round during combat, can move double
      their normal movement, and get +5 to their initiative roll.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Silver Shackles</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Silver shackles interfere with the casting of magic making
      overcasts far more likely.  A caster wearing silver shackles
      casts all spells with an overcast modified by -3.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Snare Scripture</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Snare scriptures are small books that appear similar to a Doctrine
      of the Small Gods.  This is not by unlikely coincidence.  As a spider,
      burning with hunger in the icy night of their existence, pale entities
      wait patiently for the unwary to read from their books which
      they carefully seed across the inner planes.
    </p>

    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Staff of Scorpion Wood</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The wood from a deeply poisonous tree, that hails from the 
      cold deserts of the west.  Staffs of this wood make a poison 
      attack whenever they hit.  The wielder should use gloves when
      fighting with this weapon.  If struck the defender gains
      the Poisoned condition.
    </p>
  </subsection>

 
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Staff of the Constrictor</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A staff that can choke an attacker after a successful strike.
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Steel Termites</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Small Item</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>9+1d4 dice</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A small brass box containing a 9+1d4 steel termites, each
      approximately <measurement><metric>2cm</metric><imperial>1"</imperial></measurement>
      in length.  When placed upon a wooden structure they
      will begin to rapidly chew through the wood.  Wooden doors and
      support posts can be chewed through in a time that depends on the number
      of steel termites used, approximately 6 hours divided by the number of termites
      used (so half an hour for 12 termites, forty five minutes for eight termites, one hour
      for six termites, nintey minutes for four, three hours for two and six hours for one).  
      At the end of the given time roll the dice pool (one for each termite).  If the
      check succeeds the item is rendered structurally useless (it will crumble in the hand,
      if it's a structural piece the thing being supported may well collapse).  Any 1's
      reduce the number of functional termites remaining (each termite contains a bound
      spirit of very low power, once the containing termite is sufficiently damaged the
      spirit is released and the termite ceases to function and longer).  When the brass
      box is placed upon the ground the remaining functional termites will return to it.
    </p>

    <p>
      This device may be used offensively against wood based opponents by throwing the box
      at the target.  It causes d4 damage per termite per round.  After each round the dice
      pool is rerolled to see how many termites have been lost.  This continues until the
      target is destroyed or the box is placed upon the ground.   The Fey hate this item
      and will confiscate it and have it destroyed if they are able.  Because the termites
      contain evil spirits they are effected as such (e.g. a Circle of Protection will work
      against them).
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Sunlance</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This weapon is a silver spear of high quality, saves at 3
      for breaking.  The user may attempt to use the spears power
      after they have struck an opponent.  If successful the attacks
      total damage is doubled and the spear emits a bright white light.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Sword of the Lady</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Weapon</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This is probably the most beautiful sword the characters
      have ever seen.  It has a gold hilt with a naked woman motif
      and a number of small embedded red rubies.  There is a       
      succubbus bound to the sword using runic magic.   The sword
      lusts for revenge against those who rejected her.  The
      sword will try and dominate the current owner and force
      them to kill its former owners who have abandoned it.   
    </p>
  </subsection>
   
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Sword of the Phoenix</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Book</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Grants the wielder Adversery [Demons] III.
    </p>
  </subsection>  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Tears of Lethe</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d6 to 10d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>140gp</description>
      <term>Check</term><description>Dice Pool vs Opponents Endurance</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      You apply Tears of Lethe to food or drink. A creature
      that consumes that food or drink is subject to
      a dice pool check versus their Endurance.  If they fail they
      are rendered unconcious for one hour for each drop of the
      Tears of Lethe used.  A vial will typically hold d6 + 4
      drops of the Tears.  Each drop is represented as a die
      in the items magic pool.  Tears of Lethe are made from Laudanum.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Tillinghast Resonator</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Device</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>Special</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>140gp</description>
      <term>Check</term><description>Dice Pool vs DC 7</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      An electro-psychic device that emits a resonance wave, which stimulates an affected person's pineal
      gland, thereby allowing them to perceive planes of existence outside the scope of accepted reality.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Tincture of Dhampyr Spleen</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Potion</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>3</description>
    </descriptions> 
    <p>
      Small vial of liqiod containing a sample of Dhampyr spleen.
      Heals 2d6 hit points when ingested.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Thurible of Righteousness</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Holy Symbol</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description></description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description></description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description></description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The Thurible of Sleep is a censer suspended on chains that acts as a holy symbol for
      a particular patron.  The thurible may be used by a character in combat as a morning
      star.  Thuribles are specific to a given patron.  A character does not gain the
      Holy Symbol boon when using a Thurible designed to exalt a patron the character does
      not follow.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Tongue of the Gatewalkers</subsectiontitle>        
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Charged</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>By sacrifice</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>5</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      A Tongue of the Gatewalkers is an ornately carved silver dagger.  The dagger
      has intricate depictions of tentacled creatures sacrificing people on altars.
      Its special ability is to open a localized gate (as per the greater gate spell)
      to some nearby location within the same plane by slicing through the fabric of
      space and time allowing people to step through the gate as one would step behind
      a curtain.
    </p>

    <p>
      Recharging the dagger is accomplished by killing creatures with it.  The dagger
      then drains the creature of its animus.  For each death make a Std 2d8 check
      against a difficulty of 9, if the check succeeds the the animus has been
      successfully drained and the death adds +1 to the daggers dice pool.  Note
      that the difficulty of this check is lower when slaying more virtuous victims,
      when killing children and the pure of heart the difficulty for the recharge check
      might drop as low as 5.  If a Bane occurs then the dagger realizes that
      it is no longer in the possession of its masters and implodes into a different
      dimension, from which it will eventually find its way home.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      On an overcharge the daggers extra energy attracts one of those who lurk beyond.
      A demon may climb through the portal, or one of the characters might gain an
      aspect <eg/> <emph>Touched by the Darkness</emph> rendering them an unwilling
      servant of some unspeakable horror god.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Vagúsh Kestez</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>one dice</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>3</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
    </descriptions>

    <p>
      A fine hand axe, clearly of Dwarvish construction,
      with ``Mir vagúsh kestez'' enscribed along it's edge.
      Has a bunch of Dwarven runes inlaid on the edge
      (which say "Made by Udolfus for King Bardii.  I kill Orcs" in Dwarvish).
      The axe has the following special powers:
    </p>

    <olist>
      <li>+1 to all axe ability checks,</li>
      <li>+3 to all axe ability checks when used against Greenskins,</li>
      <li>After striking, the wielder may attempt to Cleave with the axe
      by making a check using the axes magic pool.  If successful the axe
      does double damage or may instantly cut ropes, small chains and the
      like.
      </li>
    </olist>      
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>War-Fire</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      War Fire is an alchemical solution that burns when it contacts air
      (it is created in a bath of oil).  Usually it is stored in glass
      vials about the size of an apple.  The War Fire can be thrown
      and when the vial breaks the war fire ignites.  If a target is
      hit then that target gains the <emph>Aflame</emph> condition.
      Additionally the dice from the dice pool is rolled for damage
      each round until it is exhausted (a one is rolled).  If the target
      removes their clothes then the exhaustion number is increased by +1.
      Throwing water on the fire has no effect also increases the exhaustion
      number by +1.  Submersion in water will temporarily stops the fire.
      But the fire will reignite in the air again.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Warp Lightning Trident</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      This trident is powered by a shard of warp stone mounted into
      the tridents hilt.  This enables it to shoots warp lightning at a
      target checking to hit using the Gun-Shoot ability.  If the target 
      is hit the trident does 2d8 damage.
    </p>

    <p>
      The Warp Lightning Trident is a very unstable item.  In the event
      of a Bane, roll on the Bane table below.
    </p>

    <table>
	<tablecategory>Standard</tablecategory>
	<tablespec>
	  <fixed>0.1</fixed>
	  <fixed>0.74</fixed>
	</tablespec>
	<tabletitle>Warp Lightning Bane Table
	</tabletitle>
	<tablelabel>table:{{ doc_name }}-warp-lightning-bane</tablelabel>

	<tableheaderrow>
	  <td>Roll d88</td>
	  <td>Effect</td>
	</tableheaderrow>

	<tablerow>
	  <td>11-23</td>
	  <td>
	  The warp stone power surges.  The weapon does double damage.  The weapon is ok.</td>
	</tablerow>      
	<tablerow>
	  <td>24-36</td>
	  <td>
	    The warp stone short-circuits in a puff of smoke.  The trident will not fire again
	  unless the warp stone is replaced.  The trident is still usable as a trident.</td>
	</tablerow>
	<tablerow>
	  <td>37-52</td>
	  <td>
	    The warp stone explodes.  The wielder suffers 1d8 damage. The character is
	    transformed by the winds of magic.  Roll 1d8: 1-3 gain a bulls tail,
	    4-6 gain a rats tail, 7 gain a wolves tail, 8 the character gains a set of
	    small horns that sprout from their forehead. This will be seen
	  as a sign of malevolent sorcery by witch-hunters and peasants.</td>
	</tablerow>      
	<tablerow>
	  <td>53-58</td>
	  <td>
	    The warp stone explodes.  The wielder suffers 1d8 damage. One of the characters
	    hands is transformed by the winds of magic.	Roll 1d8: 1-2 into a bird-like claw,
	    3-4 a rat-like claw, 5 a crabs pincer, 6-8 a suckered tentacle.  This will be
	  seen as a sign of malevolent sorcery by witch-hunters and peasants.</td>
	</tablerow>      
	<tablerow>
	  <td>60-63</td>
	  <td>
	    The warp stone explodes.  The wielder suffers 1d8 damage. One of the characters
	    legs is transformed by the winds of magic.  Roll 1d8: 1 into a bird-like claw,
	    2 into a rats claw, 3-4 a goats leg, 5 a wolves leg, 6-8 a suckered tentacle.
	    This will be seen as a sign of malevolent sorcery by witch-hunters
	  and peasants.</td>
	</tablerow>
	<tablerow>
	  <td>64-68</td>
	  <td>
	    The warp stone explodes.  The person holding the trident receives 2d8 damage.
	  The trident is no longer usable.</td>
	</tablerow>
	<tablerow>
	  <td>69-79</td>
	  <td>
	    The warp stone explodes.  The person holding the trident receives 3d8 damage.
	    All characters in base contact with the character holding the trident suffer
	  1d8 damage.</td>
	</tablerow>
	<tablerow>
	  <td>80-88</td>
	  <td>
	  Something weird happens.  Roll on the overcharge effects table.</td>
	</tablerow>
    </table>    
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Voynich Palimpsest</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Zheimmer's Candle</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Candle</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1+1d2</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Zheimer's candle is a powerful artifact that can control
      time.  To use the candle's magical powers, first the candle
      is lit by a magic user in a ritual with a group of people, then
      after some time the candle is put out and the timeline returns to
      when the candle was lit.  The candle burns for eight hours per
      invocation.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Once returned to the original timeline all participants of the
      ritual remember the previous timeline and continue to suffer any
      mental effects that happened during that timeline but are otherwise
      unaffected. If an incation is made while putting the candle out then the
      timeline remains unchanged and the characters in the ritual do
      not return to the time when the candle was lit.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Zulfikar the Protector</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      This famous and powerful sword from Ophyr gives the wielder a free
      Parry action every round of combat.
    </p>
  </subsection>  
</section>

