<!--
    thurible of sleep.

-->


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Miscellaneous Magic Items</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    Herein lies the descriptions, such as they are, of the magical
    items that are widely known to any prepared to open a book and
    read.
  </p>

  <!--
      http://hyboria.xoth.net/sorcery/sorcerous_societies.htm
      http://hyboria.xoth.net/sorcery/magical_items.htm
  -->

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Alkahest</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Even more rare and corrosive than the Bile of the White Wyrm, Alkahest
      is the universal solvent the result of the titrations and secret alcehmical
      processes  of master Alchemists.  Contained in small granite pots it can only
      be used for a few days after its creation as by that time it has eaten through
      its container.  Alkahest dissolves everything known to man.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ansible of the Gates/ Ansible Portarum</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      An Ansible of the Gates is a small obsidian box, perhaps the size of a
      matchbox, inlaid with golden sigils such as a circle and pentagram.  The
      box feels hollow but there does not appear to be any means to open it.
    </p>

    <p>
      These boxes are used to entrap and contain demons.  If opened the demon
      within will escape and attack those around it.  If the box is put to the
      ear the demon will be able to whisper to the listener and may have
      conversations with them.  The demon will initially lie about the nature
      of the box and attempt to win them over.  Helping them in whatever way it
      can.  Its goal at this stage will be to attempt to get the listener to
      put the box somewhere where it will be badly damaged, realeasing the demon.
      If found out the demon will attempt to intimidate the listener.  If that fails
      they will attempt to bargain with them, trading knowledge for their freedom.
      Finally, if all else fails the demon might resort to begging the listener for
      their freedom.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Draught of Living Death.</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>1d4 uses</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A potion that places the taker in a state of sleep that makes them seem
      like they are dead for half an hour.  It will be extremely difficult to
      tell through non-magical means that the embiber is not actually dead
      (they are just mostly dead and as we all know, there is a big difference
      between mostly dead and all dead).
    </p>
  </subsection>


  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Dwarven Compass</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>d20</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      Various Dwarven Rune Masters have created a number of magical compasses
      with multiple needles pointing which point to any combination of the following:
      <list>
        <li>Toward magnetic North</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest source of water</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest evil thing</li>
        <li>Aligned with the nearest ley line</li>
        <li>Toward the nearest metal deposit</li>
      </list>
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Bile of the White Wyrm</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>30gp</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      Kept in special silver vials with a screwable lid, the
      bial of the white wyrm is highly corrosive disolving
      wood, stone, flesh, ferrous metals, leathers and materials.
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Tears of Lethe</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d6 to 10d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Price</term><description>140gp</description>
      <term>Check</term><description>Dice Pool vs Opponents Endurance</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      You apply Tears of Lethe to food or drink. A creature
      that consumes that food or drink is subject to
      a dice pool check versus their Endurance.  If they fail they
      are rendered unconcious for one hour for each drop of the
      Tears of Lethe used.  A vial will typically hold d6 + 4
      drops of the Tears.  Each drop is represented as a die
      in the items magic pool.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Limaceous Grease</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      Allows the player to squeeze into unnaturally small
      places when rubbed upon the skin.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Orb of Elogh</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Cursed.. activates when touched.</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      It is written that Aldinach, also known as The Hand in the Shadows,
      and The PuppetMaster, whispered temptations in the night to Elogh, Mage
      of the Second Circle.  Ambition overcoming caution, Elogh created
      the <emph>Orb of Elogh</emph>, a crystal orb containing vistas of swirling
      bial green mists.  The Orb allows the weilder to raise and control the dead.
      Unfortunately for Elogh, canny Aldinach did not reveal that the number of dead
      controlled is signicantly smaller than the number raised.
    </p>

    <p>
      Aldinach watches the world through the orb and hungers.   If one raises the
      orb to ones ear Aldinach might speak to them, whispering sweet promisings.	  
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Potion of Odic Visions</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      Lets the character see the auras of other beings for a short period
      of time.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Tongue of the Gatewalkers</subsectiontitle>        
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>Charged</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>5d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>By sacrifice</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>5</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>10</description>
    </descriptions>
    <p>
      A Tongue of the Gatewalkers is an ornately carved silver dagger.  The dagger
      has intricate depictions of tentacled creatures sacrificing people on altars.
      Its special ability is to open a localized gate to some nearby location
      within the same plane by slicing through the fabric of space and time allowing
      people to step through the gate as one would step behind a curtain.
    </p>

    <p>
      Recharging the dagger is accomplished by killing creatures with it.  The dagger
      then drains the creature of its animus.  For each death make a Std 2d8 check
      against a difficulty of 9, if the check succeeds the the animus has been
      successfully drained and the death adds +1<d4/> to the daggers dice pool.  Note
      that the difficulty of this check is lower when slaying more virtuous victims,
      when killing children and the pure of heart the difficulty for the recharge check
      might drop as low as 5.  If a consequence occurs then the dagger realizes that
      it is no longer in the possession of its masters and implodes into a different
      dimension, from which it will eventually find its way home.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      On an overcharge the daggers extra energy attracts one of those who lurk beyond.
      A demon may climb through the portal, or one of the characters might gain an
      aspect <eg/> <emph>Touched by the Darkness</emph> rendering them an unwilling
      servant of some unsepeakable horror god.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Book of Leviathan</subsectiontitle>        
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>Casters Magic Pool</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>100</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>105</description>
    </descriptions>        
    <p>
      Written by the mad monk Thelonius Freidburg in his own blood, immediately
      before his suicide, the Book of Leviathan describes a way to open a gate of
      immense proportions, allowing the reader to summon forth one of the Gods beyond
      the veil, leading to the almost certain destruction of this world.  Many
      believe that the Book is a legend told to frighten overly inquisitive young
      practioners.  
    </p>

    <p>
      A number of attempts have been made to destroy the book but it is surprisingly
      resilient, being warded from physical damage.  It is theorized that the book
      is a fetish and forms a contagious connection with some god in another plane.
      Therefore the only way to destroy the book is to return it from whence it came
      and destoy it there.
    </p>	  
    
    <p>
      The Book is an immensely corrupting influence on those around it.  It is
      contained in a large box of meteoric iron, protected by dwarven runes and
      a small poisonous needle trap.  Once the box is opened the book is revealled.
      The book is well known, and any magic-user can make an Std Check vs 7
      to recognize it.
    </p>

    <p>
      Using True Sight on the book or touching it requires the character to make three
      consecutive Break Checks exhausting dice on a 3 or less.  If they fail they gain the
      <emph>Servant of Leviathan</emph> aspect.  They may have to flee raving like
      a lunatic as well.  The book seeks the end of the world and will attempt to get
      the characters to take it to someone capable and willing to do so.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Enochian Keys</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Foaming Plaster</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>See Below</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>        
    <p>
      Foaming Plaster is a white pastey substance in a little
      terracotta clay pot (about the size of an apple) and sealed
      with red sealing wax. when the white paste touches the air
      it expands and hardens.  If left openeed the foaming plaster
      expands to about the size of a small keg of beer.  The pot can
      be resealed with fire.  Each pot contains four small applications
      or one large one.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Compass of Seeking</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The needle of this fine golden compass always points in
      the direction of the last object that has been
      imprinted upon it.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Pompatus Chapeau</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A fine hat made by the great Elvish miliner Hylonus of XXX
      that distracts all those who know anything about fashion.
      Civilized observers must make a difficult will power check
      or gain the Distracted condition.  Any character that wears
      this fine hat will be sure to be noticed.  Fey creatures are
      immune to its effects.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Runcible of XXXX</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Vagúsh Kestez</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>one dice</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>3</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
    </descriptions>

    <p>
      A fine hand axe, clearly of Dwarvish construction,
      with ``Mir vagúsh kestez'' enscribed along it's edge.
      Has a bunch of Dwarven runes inlaid on the edge
      (which say "Made by Udolfus for King Bardii.  I kill Orcs" in Dwarvish).
      The axe has the following special powers:
    </p>

    <olist>
      <li>+1 to all axe ability checks,</li>
      <li>+3 to all axe ability checks when used against Greenskins,</li>
      <li>After striking, the wielder may attempt to Cleave with the axe
      by making a check using the axes magic pool.  If successful the axe
      does double damage or may instantly cut ropes, small chains and the
      like.
      </li>
    </olist>      
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Bag of Smoked Snigglets</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
      <term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
    </descriptions>
    
    <p>
      A small bag containing 3d6 snigglets.  Salted garlic snigglets
      are, of course, a delicacy from far-off Arbonard.  Their
      moluscy, truffley flavour is overwhelming.  They are a famed
      aphrodisiac, and some say highly addictive treat.  Once tasted
      they can be used to provide +3 to a single negotiate test.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Doctrine of the Small Gods</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>
    
    <p>
      There are many minor and highly specialized deities that
      spy on this world from planes both near or deep.  Hungry for
      attention they listen for prayers.  This slight book is dedicated
      to the small gods and contains the scrawlings of a gibbering
      prophet.  Amongst the deranged rambling text are 1d4 + 1 prayers
      to various highly specialized, highly obscure, and very minor
      deities.  When read the character may ask for a small boon
      from the god.     Once all the spells have been cast the book
      collapses into a different dimension in order to spread the word.
    </p>

    <p>
      The default chance to succeed is Very Difficult using a std check.
      The difficulty level can be reduced by one step if the character
      provides suitable embellishment for his prayer (e.g. the name of
      the small god, their varied domains, and their achievements).
      The difficulty level can be reduced by a further step if the task
      is very specific and very minor or increased by a step if the task
      is demanding of the small god.      
    </p>      
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Snare Scripture</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Snare scriptures are small books that appear similar to a Doctrine
      of the Small Gods.  This is not by unlikely coincidence.  As a spider,
      burning with hunger in the icy night of their existence, pale entities
      wait patiently for the unwary to read from their books which
      they carefully seed across the inner planes.
    </p>

    <p>
      XXXX
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Steel Termites</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Mirrors of the Prince of Shadows</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The Mirrors of the Prince of Shadows (Speculis Principes Umbras), are a
      set of silvered glass mirrors with brass frames carved with disturbing,
      other-worldly sigils.   They are transparent from one side and reflective
      from the other.   There purpose is to collimate ley line potential for the
      purpose of capturing ley energies.  When set up at the juncture of two or
      more Ley Lines they are able to concentrate Ley energy providing the caster
      with an extra +6<d12/> magic energy, only at that point and only for rituals.
    </p>

    <p>
      Anyone who gazes into the mirrors must check verses Willpower with difficulty
      12 or gain a temporary insanity condition.  The character can attempt to save
      against the condition once per day until they do so.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Helm of the Minotaur</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Necronomicon</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Hand of Glory</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>


  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ignis Sacer</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>3-6 uses</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      A small pot of black powder.  When a pinch of the powder is
      consumed it induces hallucinations, nausea, vomiting, muscle
      pain and weakness, numbness, or itching rendering the consumer
      <emph>Poisoned</emph> for a period of 2d8 hours.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Index Daemonorum</subsectiontitle>        
    <p>
      A leather bound tome of obvious, but ineffable age, the
      Index Daemonorum is clearly a vile artifact to any character
      with True Sight.  Its presence is disturbing to anyone
      receptive of magical energies.  
    </p>

    <p>
      The Index Daemonorum is a powerful artifact that incarcerates
      between the protective symbols of its enscribed bindings
      a greater demon, known by some as Inoch, or Metator, Adiryaon
      and to some as Mattatron.  The bound demon knows the deep secrets
      of many of those that move in the darkness.
    </p>

    <p>
      Magic users who touch the index gain the <emph>It Whispers</emph>
      aspect allowing the book to influence the careless through time and
      space.  It seeks the destruction of the book which will set it free,
      but the book is strongly warded.  It will try and gain information
      of how the wards may be lifted.  If it has no current paths of wnquiry,
      it will amuse itself with the destruction of people it believes
      have wronged it in the past, using its servants.
    </p>

    <p>
      Those who have touched the book may ask of it questions.  The book
      will write upon its pages the answers if it knows them, which it may well
      do. The reader should beware, however, as the book twists words just as it
      twists the souls of men.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Eyes of Azathoth</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Kept in little clay jars under a layer of oil, this onyx/silver dust when
      thrown in the air immediately ignites causing blindness to those who fail
      against it, or who know of its use, for one turn.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Compendium Maleficarum</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Is a witch-hunter's manual.  Daily perusal provides the reader with
      +2 to will power rolls against other-worldly temptations.
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Immovable Staff</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d10</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>        
    <p>
      This staff is enscribed with two sets of Dwarvish runes.  When the user reads
      the first set of runes, which say ``Kegeth Ak'', the staff becomes fixed in space
      requiring a Strength check against a difficulty of 15 to move.  When the user
      speaks aloud the second set of runes, which say ``Elnär zór'', the staff becomes
      movable again.
    </p>

    <p>
      In addition the staff has a break save of 3.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Pearl of Atlach-Nacha</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A glossy black sphere the size of a mans fist.  When the secret words 
      are spoken it hatches into an astral spider and attacks the being
      it is commanded to.  After some time the spider d
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Portal Chalk</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>d4 uses</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
    </descriptions>            
    <p>
      This greenish looking stub of chalk is actually a powerful magical item that
      enables a magic user to draw a circle on a surface and create a magical
      portal that leads to a nearby location.  In order to make the chalk work the
      users must make a difficulty 5 check using their magic pool.  The portal created
      is a swirling translucent gate, but not transparent, vortex.  Furthermore the
      destination of the portal is chosen by magicks beyond the
      control of the user, though the destination is generally benign.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Staff of Scorpion Wood</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The wood from a deeply poisonous tree, that hails from the 
      cold deserts of the west.  Staffs of this wood make a poison 
      attack whenever they hit.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ring of the Serpent King</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Allows the wearer to mesmerize someone by looking into their eyes.
      They must make a Very Difficult Std Check added by their will power
      or gain a Hypnotized Aspect with a starting difficulty equal to 14
      minus their will power modifier or do as instructed.
    </p>
  </subsection>



  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Ring of the Rats</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The ring enables the wearer to check to transform into a rat
      for up to five minutes.  After the transformation the user
      gains the ``Craves Cheese'' aspect at difficulty 6 if they
      do not already have it.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Spirits of Quickening</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The drinker has three turns per round during combat, can move double
      their normal movement, and get +5 to their initiative roll.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Kismet Ring</subsectiontitle>
    <descriptions>
      <term>Type</term><description></description>
      <term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
      <term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
      <term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
    </descriptions>    
    <p>
      The wearer may make a check to reroll any Luck check.
      All dice must be rerolled.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
</section>
