
<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Planes</sectiontitle>
  
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Close Planes</sectiontitle>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Mortal Realms</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A fractured group of planes representing a range of different divergent futures
      and pasts.  Forming one of the largest sets of known planes, and the origin of
      mankind.  Hopefully, at least one of these planes is familar to the reader.  
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Anuwyn</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Anuywn, sometimes called Faeire, the Wylds or Nilfholme is the plane of
      the fey lords and their kith.  It is a vast, highly magick, wilderness.
      Anuwyn is highly congruent with the mortal realms. In a few places
      it is possible to cross from the mortal realms into Anuwyn and back again
      without magical assistance.  
    </p>

    <p>
      The fey lords are fickle, vituperative, highly magical, and very long lived.
      Their two great Queens are practically demigods.  The fey are divided into
      three factions: those that support the Summer Queen and her Seelie, or Summer,
      Court, those that support the Winter Queen and her Unseelie, or Winter, Court,
      and the neutral masses trying to avoid slaughter.  For the most part these
      courts coexist in a tense detente, but periodically pitched battles break out
      between the two sides.  The reason for this conflict has been lost in the
      mists of time.
    </p>

    <p>
      Goblins are one of the races of the lesser fey.  From them sprang the Orcs
      of the Mortal Realms a magically fused hybrid of goblin and man who exhibit the
      worst features of both races.  Similarly the Elves are the offspring of humans
      and the fey lords.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Shadow Realms</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The shadow realms are a mirror plane of the mortal realms.  In the shadow realms
      there is no warmth, there is no joy.  Light itself has been bastardized.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Demimonde</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The Demimonde is a demonic plane ruled by der Frosch.  It is a twisted
      pocket dimension where the Frosh Lords rule over 
      currate 
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The City of Brass</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A pocket dimension that forms a bridge between the Mortal Realms and
      The Maelstrom realms of Fire and Earth.  The City of Brass sits on
      an island in a sea of lava on a flat world in the Ether.  It is ruled
      by the Efreet and is populated by a range of races including the Djinn.
      It is a central hub of trade between planes with the main items of trade
      being precious metals, gems, metalwork, slaves and other delicacies. 
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Maelstrom</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The Maelstrom is a world of powerful elemental forces it is the source
      of elemental potential.  
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lost Carcosa</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Stygian Library</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A pocket plane of knowledge resembling a large, dark library.
      Entry to the plane is usually via a library or book.  Many delve here
      for answers there are here.  But most do not return.  See
      <emph>The Stygian Library</emph> by Emmy 'Cavegirl' Allen for more details.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Cist</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      A non-euclidean plane of death.  The inhabitants live in a kind of purgatory
      state.  Churned mud and swampland stretches out into the gloom. Thick fog
      hangs heavy in the air. Rolling barrows loom out of the murk. A strange
      root writhes underfoot. A thousand years after the defeat of Napoleon at
      the Battle of Austerlitz, the world has fallen into decay. Endless war has led
      to technology stagnating, and beautiful countrysides have been ground to a
      thick ruin under the boots of a million dead men.
    </p>

    <p>
      Now, nothing grows. A bizarre and horrible root covers the land; strangling
      the life from the trees, poisoning the water, and filling the sky with an
      acrid mist. Humanity barely endures by harvesting this disgusting tuber. It
      twists their bodies and minds. It infests their thoughts with divine visions
      of lost vegetables.
    </p>

    <p>
      Bizarre religious orders have formed. They stockpile abandoned weapons
      unearthed by the twisting roots.  Marching in column under fluttering
      banners, brandishing mud-clogged muskets and rusted bayonets, they
      are cruel parodies of long-forgotten armies on the march
    </p>

    <p>
      For more information see the works of Max FitzGerald and his Turnip28 wargame.
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Lost Carcossa</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME TBD .. see Robert W Chambers and The King in Yellow.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>The Far Planes</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    The Far Planes .. FIXME TBD 
  </p>  
</section>

