<section>
  <sectiontitle>Introduction</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    <indexentry>Magic</indexentry>
    Magic infuses this and all worlds.  It links and binds all things, tying entities 
    together and creating invisible bonds between the planes.  The utilization of magic
    is concerned with controlling the flow of thaumaturgical energies along these paths.
    Magic appears to be goverened by well known principles and is as much a science 
    as Physicks, Mathematics, Theosophy, Astrology, Phrenology or even Biology.  However,
    due to the chaotic nature of thaumic energies the application of these laws
    is unreliable, and frequently dangerous.  
  </p>

  <p>
    The basic principles of magic are as follows:    
  </p>
  <descriptions>
    <term>Law of Potentials</term>
    <description>
      In order for magic to occur there must be a difference in thaumaturgical 
      potentials, a high potential and a low potential.
    </description>

    <term>Law of Flux</term>
    <description>
      Magic occurs when thaumaturgical energies flow from a high potential to a 
      low potential along a line of flux.
    </description>

    <term>Law of Conductivity</term>
    <description>
      Lines of magical flux may be created, broken or enhanced using a variety of techniques.
      Different materials conduct magical energies better than others.
    </description>

    <term>Law of Contagion</term>
    <description>
      As magic shapes all things it follows logically that similar things are linked by the
      lines of flux that created them.  The relationship between things can be used to gain
      more control over magic.
    </description>

    <term>Law of Knowledge</term>
    <description>
      The more you know about a subject the greater your knowledge about the 
      lines of flux that bind them, and the more power you have over them.  This can be
      considered to be a corollary of the Law of Contagion.
    </description>
  </descriptions>
  
  <p>
    Later in this chapter we explore in more depth how the fundamental laws of magic effect casting.
  </p>

  <figure position="!b">
    <img id="rackham_frogs" scale="0.38"/>
  </figure>
  
</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>Casting Spells</sectiontitle>
  
  <p>
    <label>sec:magic-dice</label>
    Mechanically, magical spells are abilities.  Casting magic uses a pool of magic dice, and
    magic checks are dice pool checks.  Characters that do not cast spells also have a magic pool 
    that represents their life-energy, their animus.  Non-casting characters will have no
    magic abilities that use their magic pool.  However their magic pools can be used as a 
    a defence against certain magical effects.  Specialized magic casting characters will have
    larger magic dice pools, greater energy, and a variety of skills that allow them to use that pool.
  </p>

  <p>
    Follow these steps to cast a spell:
  </p>
  <descriptions>
    <term>Roll Magic Check</term>
    <description>The player chooses any number of dice from their pool
    and rolls them and sums the face values of the dice to get a result.</description>
    <term>Check Success</term>
    <description>If the sum of the magic dice is less than the difficulty then the spell is 
    under-powered, sputters out and fails without further effect.   If the result is greater or equal to 
    the difficulty the spell check succeeds and the spell is cast.  The spells effects apply now.
    <equation>
      <line>Difficulty <leqqsymbol/> Result + Ability Rank</line>
    </equation>    
    </description>    
    <term>Check Overcharge</term>
    <description>
      Thematically an overcharge occurs when the caster
      embues a spell with too much power and the extra theurgical energies become too great for the caster
      to handle, the caster loses control over the casting and the extra energies must be disipated somehow.
      Mechanically, an overcharge occurs if the number of sixes rolled in the check exceeds the spells
      overcharge value.  Armour can effect spell overcharge, see the table of Magic Modifiers,
      Table<ref>figure:{{ doc_name }}-magic-modifiers</ref>,  for details.
      At that point a range of strange and usually bad things can happen.  The GM
      determines an overcharge effect based on the spells overcharge information and possibly referring to
      Table<ref>figure:{{ doc_name }}-overcharge-effects</ref> for some suggested overcharge effects to
      inspire the GM.
    </description>
    <term>Remove Dice</term>
    <description>
      Finally any remaining Exhausted dice are removed from the casters magic dice pool.
    </description>
  </descriptions>

  {% include "docs/tables/magic_modifiers.xml" %}
  {% include "docs/tables/overcharge_effects.xml" %}
  {% include "docs/tables/overcharge_effects_pt2.xml" %}

</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Principles of Magic (Optional)</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    Magical checks are affected by the complex, chaotic nature of thaumaturgic
    energies.  We now explain the laws of magic, which describe how magic is effected by
    context and circumstance.  But the reader should beware; magic is a dark art; those
    who play with the devil's toys will be brought by degrees to wield his sword.
  </p>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Law of Potentials</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      The first law of magic is that <indexentry>Rules of Magic<subentry>First</subentry></indexentry>
      <emph>magic requires a potential difference in energy levels as a prerequisite</emph>.
      Furthermore, <indexentry>Rules of Magic<subentry>Second</subentry></indexentry>
      <emph>the productive use of magic requires the construction of a thaumaturgical 
      conduit between potentialities</emph> through which magical energies can flow. 
    </p>

    <p>
      There are many different sources of thaumaturgical potentialities, such as the 
      potential difference between planes of existance, energy from stored thaumaturgical
      sources, the animus (a person or animals spark of life) and so on.  We examine the most
      important, and the most widely used, of these potentialities here.
    </p>

    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Raw/Planar Magical Sources</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Planar Magicks are those that use the raw potential differences between two
	planes directly, these so-called Protinus magics, are the most powerful, the
	most volatile, and most dangerous of the magical sources to use.  Casters
	attempt to harness the flow from planes of higher energy to planes of
	lower energy.  There are two main dangers to using this form of thatumaturgical
	energy.  The first is its volatility. Casters using this energy source are more
	likely to overcharge their spells.  The second danger are the lurkers in the dark.
	There are a myriad of creatures lurking in the frigid abyssal planes who hunger
	eternally to escape to higher planes and feed indiscriminately.  They wait for the
	opportunity a miscast might provide.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	<defn>Elemental Magic</defn> is a subset of planar magic that uses the potential
	between a particular set of well-known planes of existance, the so-called
	elementatal planes.  The advantage of this energy source is that these planes are
	comparatively stable and their behaviour is fairly well-understood.  Unfortunately,
	elemental magic is less	versatile than, the more general, planar magic.
      </p>

      <p>
	If a magical act uses extra-planar differentials, and the flow of energies
	is from this plane to some other lower 
	potential plane then energies are expended from this plane, the temperature  
	drops, lights dim and ice may form.  We call such an action an endothaumic 
	reaction.  In contradistinction, if energy flows to this plane from some higher 
	plane then the magic is of a type named exothaumic and the tell-tale side effects 
	of such practice are bright lights, heat are sometimes smoke of a sulfurous nature.
	No other magic sources have such side-effects.
      </p>      
    </subsubsection>

    <figure position="!" fullwidth="true">
      <img id="skull" scale="0.34"/>
    </figure>
    
    
    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Magic Items and their Power Sources</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Magical items typically use thaumaturgical energies stored within the device itself.
	Magic by its very nature is evanescent - it has a tendency to dissipate after
	a period of time.  Magical items, therefore, tend to be made of thaumic insulating
	materials in order to minimize the rate at which magic is dissipated.
      </p>

      <p>
	In game, this stored magical potential is representated by some magical devices
	having their own magic pool and refresh rates.  The item used to store magical energies
	may be one use, rechargeable or self recharging.  One use magic items will have no
	refresh rate.  When a one-use items dice pool is depleted the device is spent.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
	<term>Runic Magic</term>
	<description>
	  <p>
            are essentially spells that automatically cast 
	    themselves when a certain triggering event occurs, <ie/> the runes are read or
	    touched.  The effects of runic magic are typically limited to the vicinity of the
	    runes.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    The small amount of magic required to cast the runespell is stored in the runes 
	    themselves when they are created.  Overtime this magic will leach from the rune
	    and it will no longer be viable, but may still be replenished by a skilled
	    Runemaster.  Depleted runic magic will have limited or even no effect.
	    For this reason runes are typically carved into materials which are
	    highly thaumaturgically non-conductive such as ferrous metals or rock.  Once the
	    runespell is cast it behaves as any other spell, drawing the energy for the spell
	    itself from some second source.  For runes carved in stone, glass and steel this
	    is almost always from the elemental planes of earth as the spells powers are
	    enhanced by the contagious nature of the substrate.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    Magical swords, armour, rings and the like are typically runic in nature.
	    See Section<ref>sec:attunement</ref> on page<pageref>sec:attunement</pageref>
	    for information on using magic items and attunement.
	  </p>
	</description>	
	
	<term>Scrolls</term>
	<description>
	  <p>	     
	    contain the written incantations that must be entoned to cast a spell <label>sec:scrolls</label>.
	    They often also contain background thaumic theory, notes on the casters experiences with casting
	    the spell, other bits of information relevant to the spell, and sometimes bits of information
	    completely irrelevant to the spell.  Unlike runes they do not contain any magical energies with
	    which to automatically trigger or power the spell instead drawing their energy from
	    the readers magic pool.  Most scrolls are written in Inochian, though some
	    are written in languages like Aquillonian, Lagashi, and Fey, and the caster must be able to read
	    from the scroll to cast it.  These requirements make scrolls difficult for non-casters to use.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    Scrolls may be used in the following ways: a caster may cast a spell from a scroll, or
	    they may learn that spell from that scroll, or both.
	  </p>
    
	  <p>
	    <emph>When casting a spell from a scroll the caster must first make a successful language
	    check in the language that the scroll is written in to read the scroll</emph>.  If they
	    fail then the spell is not cast and no magic energy is
	    expended.  If they fail with a boon they receive +3 to the next attempt.  If they
	    fail with a bane they must expend an extra magic die after the spell is cast.  If they
	    succeed with a boon they may add or subtract 3 to their roll or return a magic die exhausted
	    in the casting to their magic pool.  <emph>After reading the scroll
	    the spell is cast normally using the casters own magic pool as a a rank 0 ability</emph>.
	    Casting spells at 0 rank overrides the spells normal rank so if a spell has a
	    minimum rank of 1 then it can still be cast at 0 rank from a scroll.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    A caster may learn a spell from a scroll given time to study it, and with the use of an 
	    ability promotion of the appropriate rank.    
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    Scrolls may be reused unless they become damaged, or the creator has written some
	    limiting clause into the scroll.  This may be done in order to reduce the danger
	    of misuse or limit competition with the creator.  A common example of scroll
	    limitation is to include a glyph of destruction in the scroll so that it may not
	    be used more than once and cannot be learned.  Another example, are cursed scrolls
	    designed as a trap to protect the author's trade secrets from others.  Note that the
	    proliferation of magic is seen as a dangerous thing.  Their unfettered use is frowned
	    upon and policed by both the College of Mages and the Witchhunters.
	  </p>
	</description>

	<term>Potions</term>
	<description>
	  store thaumic energy in liquid form.  The magic is enfused in a liquid
	  solvent, and contained within a glass flask with binding magical inscriptions.
	  At the best of times potions have a limited shelf-life.  However, the energy stored
	  in a potion begins to escape rapidly as soon as the flask is opened.  Potions
	  are generally created by magic users for the use of non magic users as potions
	  are easy to use and moderately easy to create.  
	</description>
	
	<term>Wands</term>
	<description>
	  are slight batons made from thaumic conducting materials that are used to
	  better focus and control raw thaumic energy. Wands are not intrinsically magical
	  but are instead tools to better focus and control magic.
	  See Section<ref>sec:wands</ref> on page<pageref>sec:wands</pageref>.
	</description>

	<term>Rods</term>
	<description>
	  A rod is a short, <measurement><metric>60cm</metric><imperial>2'</imperial></measurement>,
	  heavy baton that is used to store and direct the flow of thaumic energy.  Casters who
	  use rods recharge the energy stored within them on a regular basis.
	  See Section<ref>sec:rods</ref> on page<pageref>sec:rods</pageref>.
	</description>

	<term>Staffs and Spears</term>
	<description>
	  Staffs and spears may be used to ground out magic.   Like wands, staffs do not need
	  to be intrinsically magical to be used in this manner.  
	  See Section<ref>sec:staves</ref> on page<pageref>sec:staves</pageref>.
	</description>

	<term>Holy Symbol</term>
	<description>
	  Holy symbols use contagion to increase the strength of the conduit between a
	  theurgical caster and their sponsor.  They need not be inherantly magical.
	</description>      
      </descriptions>
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>The Animus</subsubsectiontitle>
      
      <p>
	<indexentry>animus</indexentry>
	Every living creature is imbued with a store of thaumic energy within and of
	themselves, their <emph>Animus</emph>.  This is why even non-magical archetypes
	have a magic pool.   This energy is used by a number of 
	forms of magic, the most widely know examples are: necromantic draining, blood 
	magic, death curses, and human sacrifices.
      </p>

      <p>
	It has been postulated that the phenomenon of life is the flow of magical power 
	from some higher plane through to some lower plane.  In such a model the body is
	the conduit through which magical energies flow.  An alternate
	model holds that living creatures are wellsprings of magical energies, <ie/> that
	they are the sources of magical energies themselves.  A third model holds that both
	of the first two models hold true.  Which of these models, if any, are correct
	remains an extremely contentious area of debate amongst scholars of the dark arts.
	In any case, it is widely believed that their exists an animatic flow that is
	replenishes the animus from some source.
      </p>

      <p>
	The rate of the animatic flow is proportional to the strength of emotions that 
	the living creature is feeling.  For this reason many thaumatergical predators 
	will enhance these emotions while feeding.
      </p>

      <p>
	Further, it has been hypothesized that apparations, ghosts, banshees and other
	spiritual manifestions are the remnants of powerful residual animatic flow.  They
	are the eddies in the animatic flow, left by the passing of highly magical or highly
	emotive creatures.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>

    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>The Biome</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Rather than draw magical power from a particular animus, some animistic casters,
	such as	Druids, are able to draw very small amounts of magic from all surrounding
	living creatures.  While very powerful these magics can be difficult to use if the
	biome is not in balance. 
      </p>

      <p>
	Wild magic is effected by the environment in which it is cast.  In biomes with a
	great deal of balanced animistic energy, forests, swamps etc, Wild Magic spells
	receive a +1 DC modifier.  In cities and deserts wild magic suffers a -1 DC
	modifier.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Channelled Magic</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Theurgic, Channelled, or Sponsored Magic is magic whose power has been channelled 
	from a third party one of the so-called ``gods'', demons or celestial agents.  It is 
	assumed that the caster of channeled magic is using a shared ``holy'' symbol to
	establish or strengthen the conduit between a caster and the third-party source.  In
	this type of magic the caster typically acts as	an agent for the third-party, allowing
	the third-party to project their power and their influence.  See
	Section<ref>sec:holy-symbol</ref> on page<pageref>sec:holy-symbol</pageref>
      </p>

      <p>
	Those with an enquiring mind may be wondering where the third-party gets their
	energy from.  It seems clear that many gain their power from planar magics.
	For these 'gods' it has been surmised that the act of prayer forms a 
	conduit with the god through which some small part of the devotees animus travels.
	Thus people pray to a god,  the god gains animus,  the god grants power to clerics
	to project the gods interest, the clerics use this power to protect those of their
	faith and convert new devotees, .. and so on.  Though, this is just a theory and
	such musings are clearly not meant for mere mortals such as ourselves.  Many
	religions have also practiced sacrifice as a faster and simpler way of providing
	animatic energies to their deity.
      </p>

    </subsubsection>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Law of Flux</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      In order for magic to happen thaumic energies must flow, as water must flow for
      a water mill to grind flour.  
    </p>

    <p>
      Stopping the flow stops the magic.  Hindering the flow hinders the magic.
      <bold>To use magic there must be a potential difference and a flow.</bold>  Certain
      magical symbols, chiefly the pentagram and the circle, when carved, drawn or laid out
      upon the ground in salt will stop the flow of magic (salt is used because it is
      non-conductive, granular, common, cheap, and white.. which makes it easier to see
      any discontinuities in the symbols).
    </p>

    <p>
      An alternate problem happens when there is too much conductivity.  In practice
      this happens most often when there is too much water around, e.g. when it rains, or
      when the caster is standing in water.  Here the caster is likely to dissipate more
      energy than they otherwise would.  In practice this means that dice are exhausted
      on rolls higher than the usual value.  In rain the exhaust value increases by one,
      if you are standing in water (above your ankles) the exhaust value increases by two,
      if you are swimming the exhaust value increases by three.  For example, typically,
      magic dice are exhausted on a roll of 1 or 2.  If the character is standing knee-deep
      in "water" in a sewer they exhaust dice on a roll of 4 or less.  If they cast a four
      dice spell and rolled 1, 3, 4, 6 they would exhaust three dice.
    </p>  
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Law of Conductivity</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Magic shapes and binds all things.  Objects that share similarities are linked by 
      magical ties.  These ties can be used to strengthen magical spells.  For example, having 
      the blood or hair of a person can be used to strengthen certain spells when used upon
      that subject.
    </p>

    <wrapimg position="r" id="demon" scale="0.14"/>
    
    <p>
      Different materials affect the flow of magic differently.  Natural and biological 
      materials such as flesh, wood, and water conduct magic very well.   Ferrous metals 
      glass, and rock do not conduct magic well and can interfere with its casting in
      unpredictable ways.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Iron interferes with the flow of magic.  Magical creatures,
      particularly the Fey, do not like it.  In contrast non-ferrous metals.. Platinum,
      Gold, Silver, Copper, conduct magic, though scholars are in disagreement as to why
      these do so, given iron does not.  Silver, is a particularly excellent conductor and
      so adversely affects those possessed by extra planar entities such as the undead and
      lycanthropes.
    </p>

    <p>
      Magical circles break conductivity (and therefore also break contagion).
      What the circle is made of generally doesn't matter.  Though there are specialized 
      protective circles for the protection of particular beings that while more 
      powerful require special ingredients, (e.g. salt for vampires).
    </p>

    <p>
      Ferrous armour disrupts the flow of magical energies and adversly affects 
      grounding.  It is impossible to ground-out magic when wearing armour.
      Similarly, if using a wooden shafted spear with a ferrous head then only the 
      lowest die may be removed as the metal head interferes with the thaumaturgical 
      conductivity of the shaft.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      Water, and particularly running water, is an excellent magical channel.
      Characters casting magic in standing water or casting in the rain exhaust dice
      from their result on a roll of a 1 or 2.  In running water they exhaust dice on a
      result of 1-3.  In addition, running water breaks contagion.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Law of Contagion</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Magical contagion refers to the conduits that exist between similar things.
      All things are bound by magic, and magic binds all things.  But some things
      are much more closely bound than others.  These sympathetic ties effect the
      casting of spells for good or ill.
    </p>

    
    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Blood Magic</subsubsectiontitle>  
      <p>
	The power of <defn>Blood Magic</defn> is derived from thaumaturgical contagion between
	the blood and the animus of the subject.  Blood magic drains the animus from the subject.
	This allows necromancers and the like to use someone elses magic pool in spells
	without	their consent (see the rules for shared magic pools).  Blood for this purpose has to be
	fresh - remember magic is evanescent.  Casting blood magic without a specially prepared
	sacrificial dagger, an athamé, is done with a -2 DC Modifier.  You do not have to be a
	caster to cast blood magic.  Some shamen use their own blood as a potential pool of energy.
      </p>

      <figure position="h">
	<img id="jordan_cultist" scale="0.18"/>
      </figure>      
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Symbolic Contagion</subsubsectiontitle>  
      <p>
	Similar symbols form flux lines connected by contagion.  Ritual use of special
	patterns can form an association to other locations and other realms.  Holy symbols
	form conduits between theurgic source, a deity or demon, and the caster.  Shared
	symbols carved into portals tie one portal end point to another.  Contagion is
	the motivation for the use of all symbology in magic. .
      </p>
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Magical Ingredients</subsubsectiontitle>  
      <p>
	Magical ingredients are used to bind a spell to its target or purpose
	or bind a spell to previous castings of that spell.  Theurgical magic users
	rarely need or use magical ingredients.	Non-theurgical magic
	casters are assumed to have a small cache of reasonably general purpose
	spell casting ingredients about their person at most times (mistletoe,
	salt, spiders web, mandragora, iron powder, coffin nails, adders tongue
	and the like).  There are enough suitable substitutes for most ingredients
	that we can assume that the caster is reasonably well stocked with something
	that will do at any time.  If however the magic caster has had his stock
	of ingredients removed then his spells will be cast with a -1 DC Modifier.
	If the ingredients exhibit strong and unusual contagion with the spell in
	question the GM might grant a +1 DC Modifier to the check.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>
    

    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Somatic Hand Gestures</subsubsectiontitle>  
      <p>
	Spells are usually cast using somatic hand gestures.  These gestures tie
	the spell to other castings of the same spell in the past and in the future,
	increasing their power.  Magic Checks are performed with a -3 DC Modifier if
	the caster does not use somatic hand gestures when casting.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>


    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Words of Power</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
	<indexentry>Words of Power</indexentry>	
	Words are the key to magic.  When the first great spell casters,
	monumentally powerful inter-planar beings, cast their spells they
	did so while intoning in Innochian, the language of magic.  Intoning
	the same words forms a contagious link with the original castings
	and other castings of this spell through time. Magic words may also
	be used to train the invokers thoughts and to gain the attention of
	other worldly beings, like ringing a bell in the dark.  Casting a
	spell without verbally intoning the correct words of power
	is done so at a -1 DC Modifier.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	Truely powerful creatures are very strongly bound to their true
	names.  Knowing the true name of a being is a powerful connection
	when it comes to casting spells that target that indivdual.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>

    
    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Temporal Contagion</subsubsectiontitle>  
      <p>
	Events that occur at the same time are connected by contagion.  This allows
	casters to draw on the power of great celestial and planar events, <eg/>
	eclipses, syzygy, and aniversaries are all potent times due temporal contagion,
	in order to increase the power of specific spells.
	Similarly, various times of the year are more auspicious for the casting
	certain rituals because of the contagion with the castings of the
	spell at the same time of in prior years, <eg/> the solstices.  The GM
	should feel free to apply modifiers to casting as they see fit at such times.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>

      
    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Proximal Contagion</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
      	Things that are close to one another are linked by proximal contagion.
      	This is why many spells have a range.  Beyond that range it becomes
      	difficult to form a decent conduit.  Magic at great distance is very difficult.
	If something has been close to the subject of a spell for a long time then
	that item might make a good spell component.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>

    <subsubsection>
      <subsubsectiontitle>Portals</subsubsectiontitle>
      <p>
      	Portals are ethereal pathways between or within planes that allow travel
      	or projection through those portals.   A portal, once established, allows the caster
      	to overcome many of the barriers of proximal contagion.  Portals are geographically
	distributed points bound by powerful contagious energies.  
      	There are two types of porta, those that are known as Greater Portals, True Portals or
      	simply just Portals, through which corporeal travel is possible, and Lesser Portals,
      	sometimes called conduits, which are purely magical conduits through which spells may
	be cast. Opening a portal of any size is such a difficult and dangerous practice that
	it usually requires assistance at the destination.
      </p>

      <p>
      	Greater portals require huge amounts of thaumaturgical energy to create and to keep
      	open.  Once open they allow beings to physically pass from one plane to another.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	Lesser portals are used for communication.  Devils and demons may create a simulacrum
	of themselves through a lesser portal.
      	Their facsimile is created by congealling ectoplasm from the environment.
      	When the lesser portal is shut this breaks any link through the portal.  However,
      	the simulacrum remains linked with their parent by contagion for some time afterwards.
      	Possession is also made possible by lesser portals.
      </p>
      
      <p>
      	Opening portals is extremely dangerous as their are countless beings lying
      	in wait, in a manner not to disimilar to the way the monstrous glowing demon fish
	hungrily await their hapless prey in the cold and the dark of the deep oceans.
      </p>
    </subsubsection>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>The Law of Knowledge</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Thaumaturgical fluxes bind all things.  The better a caster understands a subject,
      the better he understands the contagious influences that effect that subject, and
      the easier it is for the magic user to cast spells that effect the subject.
      The greater the knowledge the magical practitioner has about his subject the more
      power they have over that subject <indexentry>Rules of Magic<subentry>Third</subentry>
      </indexentry>, knowledge is power.
    </p>

    <p>
      The GM, at their discretion, should apply modifiers to the DC if the caster can
      demonstrate deep or special knowledge about the subject.  Similarly, having an accurate
      physical or mental model or representation of the target of a spell may grant an
      additional modifier.
    </p>

    <p>
      <indexentry>True Name</indexentry>
      Over time and with repetition the name of a being forms a contagious conduit with the
      being.  The names of truely ancient or powerful beings are spoken many many times and
      their name comes to hold significant power over them.  Knowing the True Name of a magical
      being grants an additional modifiers to the spell, at the GMs discretion and proportional
      to the beings age and power.  It is for this reason that many of these beings shroud
      themselves in the shadows of anonymity, and why many great casters seek solitude.  This
      is why it pleases the creatures of the night to be known by many names.  It is also why
      clerics invoke the names of their deities when casting.  The True Name of a creature is
      a Word of Power bound to that creature.
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Other Rules</sectiontitle>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Assisting a Cast</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      It is possible to cast spells cooperatively.  In order to do so the caster and one or
      more assistants simultaneously perform a Shared Dice Pool Check.  The result is the sum
      of all the dice rolled.  In order to assist a conduit must exist between any assistants and
      the caster, for example via physical contact, or some other magically conductive path (e.g.
      a staff).  Only the caster may ground out any magic.  Any assistants exhaust
      dice on a 3 or less, by default, as the conduit from assistant to caster is leaky.  In the
      event of an overcharge, any assisting casters will also be effected by the overcharge
      unless they make a Speed DC 14 Check to break the conduit with the caster.
    </p>    
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Rituals</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Rituals are spells cast cooperatively over a long period of time.  A ritual is cast by
      one or more participants over a period of hours.  There is always one leader of the spell
      who controls the magic.  The participants in a ritual must be casters or blood magic
      practioners.  Every hour the participants contribute one dice towards a shared pool, one
      die per hour.  For every hour after the first the participants must
      make a Willpower DC 9 check.  If they fail they lose concentration and the ritual fizzles.
    </p>

    <p>
      Ritual spells receive a +1 DC Modifier for each hour spent casting.  Only the ritual
      leader may exhaust dice or use items during a spell.  Ritual magic may also gain a +1 DC
      Modifier from the use of effigies, prepared casting circle, etc.
    </p>
  </subsection> 

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Influence, Possession and Domination</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Magic items embued with essence of other beings may come to exert pressure on
      the bearer of the item.  There are three levels of control a magic item may have
      over a PC: influence, possession, and domination.  Influence are purely story
      based effects.  The character has dreams or nightmares and feels the urge to do certain
      things or is drawn to certain people or locations.   Possession is represented
      in game by the character gaining a new Aspect to reflect the control of the item
      over the character.  If the character is dominated then the GM takes the characters
      sheet and runs the character, usually for a short period of time. The character may
      or may not be allowed a will-power save against these effects, depending on the item.
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Interaction of Magical Items</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Controlling magic during the casting of spells is a difficult process
      at the best of times.  Doing so with multiple casting aids is nearly impossible.
      For example, a caster should not use a wand and a rod in the same casting, or
      a wand and a staff.  The caster may carry and even hold multiple
      items but using more than one at a time is very difficult.  Woe betide the fool
      who attempts to make play things of such dark and potent energies.  
    </p>
  </subsection>


  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Holy Symbols <indexentry>Holy Symbols</indexentry></subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      <label>sec:holy-symbol</label>
      Holy symbols use contagion to increase the strength of the conduit between a
      theurgical caster and their sponsor.  It is assumed that theurgical casters have a
      magical symbol.  If a theurgical caster is not using a holy symbol they suffer a
      -2 DC Modifier.  This is reduced to a -1 DC Modifier if the caster has time to
      improvise a holy symbol.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Staves, Spears and Groundig<indexentry>Grounding - Staffs/Spears</indexentry></subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Staffs are long sticks, <measurement><metric>150-180cm</metric>
      <imperial>5'-6'</imperial></measurement>, that can be used in combat.  In addition
      because they are constructed from a conductive material, typically wood, they can be
      used to ground out spells, to mitigate the effects of overcharging spells.
      When using a staff to ground out dice you may remove any die from the roll.  A spear may
      also be used for this purpose but its metal tip effects the flow and so when grounding with
      a spear dice which rolled a six cannot be grounded out.  
    </p>


    <p>
      By using a conductive tool, typically a wooden staff, carved 
      appropriately, a character can ground-out a spell by holding it and planting 
      the end on the earth.  This removes either the highest or lowest die from the 
      result, at the characters discretion, and places it back in the characters pool.
    </p>

   
    <p>
      After the dice have been rolled the result may be greater than the overcharge value for the spell.
      When this occurs the caster may be able to <emph>ground</emph> out extra
      overcharge energy.  This involves disipating some of the magical energy by creating a conduit for
      magic to flow into the earth.  This is typically done using a wooden staff or spear.  Grounding
      allows the caster to exhaust any single die from the check before the results of the check are
      finalized. <indexentry>Grounding</indexentry> 
      <indexentry>Spell Casting<subentry>Grounding</subentry></indexentry>    
    </p>

    <p>
      The process of grounding requires a well controlled magical flux.  This flux is highly sensitive
      to metal.  Metal adversely effects the flow of magic and casters wearing armour cannot ground out
      spells.  Casters wearing light armours are mildly effected due to buckles, studs etc and suffer a
      -1 DC Modifier.  Spears with their metal tips are not as good at grounding as staves and suffer a
      -1 DC Modifier.  
    </p>
  </subsection> 

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Wands</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Using a wand allows the caster to reroll one of their spell dice.
    </p>
  </subsection> 

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Rods</subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Rods are
	  constructed from a thaumically conductive core encircled in an outer thaumic
	  insulating shell.  Typically, rods can store an extra die worth of thaumic
	  energy.  Magical rods can be used in combat and are equivalent to a club.  Once used
	  the caster needs to recharge the rod which they may do when they rest as if it were
	  their own pool.  The die used for the rod in a spell check should be rolled separetly
	  from the casters pool (the dice in these pools exhaust independently).
    </p>
  </subsection> 

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Attunement</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Powerful magical devices may be embued with the residual animus of their
      creators, or tainted by the nature of their magical source.  In either case,
      this is represented in game by the item having one or more aspects that are applied
      to characters when they attune with the item.  The nature of the interaction
      required to transfer the items aspects to the character depends on the item,
      <eg/> the aspects might be applied when they touch the item, or when they have used
      the item a number of times, <etc/>.
    </p>
  </subsection> 




</section>

