
<section>
  <sectiontitle>Character Creation</sectiontitle>


  <!--
      <figure position="tb">
      <img src="./resources/dragon.png" scale="0.4"></img>
      </figure>
  -->
  
  <p>
    Follow these steps to create a character
    <label>sec:character_creation</label>
  </p>


  <olist>
    <li>
      <p>
        Choose an archetype.
      </p>            
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
        Print out a character sheet for your archetype.  This will save you a lot
	of work during the game and is highly recommended.
      </p>            
    </li>
    
    <li>
      <p>
        Choose a name for the character.
      </p>            
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
        Write your name in the players name area on the character sheet.
      </p>            
    </li>

    <li>
      Fill in your height, weight, and age as specified by the archetype.  Choose
      whatever gender you like.  
    </li>
    
    <li>
      <p>
        Determine your Primary Attributes using one of the following two methods:
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        <term>Random</term> 
        <description>For each attribute, roll 2d4 + 4, and assign the sum of the dice
        to the attribute.  After all attributes have been assigned, optionally swap one
        or two pairs of	attribute values.
        </description>  
        
        <term>Fixed</term> 
        <description>Choose one of the following sets of numbers and assign them to 
	      the primary attributes of your choice:
	      <list> 
	        <li>12, 11, 10, 9, 8, 7, 6 or</li>
	        <li>12, 11, 9, 9, 9, 7, 6</li>
	      </list>
        </description>
      </descriptions>
    </li>

    <li>
      Fill in your opposed check modifiers.  The opposed check modifier for an attribute
      is the value of the attribute minus nine, <eg/> Dourli has a Strength of 12 and an
      Agility of 7.  His opposed strength check modifier is +3 and his opposed agility
      check modifier is -2.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Initiative Score and Modifier:
      <equation>
	<line>Initiative Score =</line>
	<line>Archetype Initiative +</line>
	<line>Speed Attribute Initiative Bonus</line>
      </equation>

      <p>
	<bold>N.B.</bold> Here the archetype initiative comes from the archetype document.
	It is different for each archetype.  The attribute bonus comes from the Attribute
	Bonus Table, on page <pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</pageref>.  The same basic approach is used when calculating the rest of the character statistics that follow; add a value from the archetype document to a bonus from the attribute bonus table.
      </p>
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Movement.
      <label>sec:character_movement</label>
      <equation>
	<line>Moves =</line>
	<line>Archetype Movement +</line>
	<line>Speed Attribute Move Bonus</line>
      </equation>
    </li>
        
    
    <li>
      Determine your Stamina.
      <equation>
	<line>Stamina =</line>
	<line>Archetype Stamina +</line>
	<line>Endurance Attribute Bonus for Stamina</line>
      </equation>
    </li>
    <li>
      Determine your characters Health.
      <equation>
	<line>Health =</line>
	<line>Archetype Health +</line>
	<line>Strength Attribute Bonus for Health</line>
      </equation>
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Resolve Dice Pool, Refresh Rate and Current Pool: 
      <equation>
	<line>Resolve =</line>
	<line>Archetype Resolve Dice +</line>
	<line>Willpower Attribute Bonus Dice for Resolve</line>
      </equation>
    </li>

    <li>
      Fill in your Magic Pool and Magic Refresh Rate as described by your archetypes
      level progression table.
      <equation>
	<line>Magic =</line>
	<line>Archetype Magic Dice +</line>
	<line>Willpower Attribute Bonus Dice for Magic</line>
      </equation>
      The current pool starts equal to your Magic Pool.
      Not all characters are able to cast spells, but all characters have a magic pool.
      This pool represents their animus, their spark of life, and can be use to resist
      spells.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Fate Refresh Rate and Max Fate Pool from your archetype
      with bonuses for Luck from the Attibute Bonus Table, see Table
      <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</ref> on page
      <pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</pageref>.  Set your Fate Pool
      to your Max Fate Pool value.
    </li>
    
    <li>
      The rate of character progression is determined by Experience Points (XP).
      Starting XP is zero unless the GM states otherwise.  The XP required to reach
      the next level is recorded in the archetype description document.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine the Skill Points you have available from your archetype level progression 
      table and record them on your character sheet.
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
        Players should choose a few initial aspects for their character.   Newly acquired 
	aspects have a difficulty of d4 + 4 unless the archetype description or the GM
	says otherwise.  It is best to do this in a group with the other players and
	the GM.  Better still let the other players choose an aspect for you.
      </p>
      <p>
	During the course of the game new aspects can be added and old aspects removed, so 
	the initial choice is not overly important.  We suggest you choose one aspect that 
	describe your characters politics, motivations or troubles and another one that 
	describes your characters relationship with some other member in the party.
      </p>
      <p>
	To provide inspiration, each archetype has some suggested aspects listed in their
	archetype document. There is also a table of random aspects in Section
	<ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_random_aspects</ref> on page
	<pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_random_aspects</pageref>.  You do not have to
	choose aspects from these lists.  You are more than welcome to create your own.  In
	fact it is preferable.  Just make sure to run your aspects past your GM before
	committing them to paper, as GMs and players may need to collaborate to ensure that
	their character's aspects and the world, interact in interesting ways and are cogent.  
      </p>
    </li>

    <li>
      Optionally sketch out a couple of lines of back story with your fellow players and 
      GM with a few points about the characters history.  For example, Dourli might come from 
      the Iron Mountains and be searching for his long lost cousin Grimli.
    </li>

    <li>
      Buy your starting skills using the skill point price list for your archetype.  The
      price of each skill may vary from one archetype to the next.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your starting money as described by your archetype.
    </li>

    <li>
      Buy equipment.  Note that each archetype also has a list of default starting equipment
      that you get for free at the start of the game.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Armour Class:
      <equation>
	<line>Armour Class =</line>
	<line>Archetype Armour Class +</line>
	<line>Shield Armour Class Bonus +</line>
	<line>Speed Armour Class Bonus</line>
      </equation>
      The shield bonus is available when equipping shields and a few other 
      weapons that can be used defensively.
    </li>
    
  </olist>


  {% include "tables/attribute_bonuses.xml" %}
</section>
