
<section>
  <sectiontitle>Character Creation</sectiontitle>


  <!--
      <figure position="tb">
      <img src="./resources/dragon.png" scale="0.4"></img>
      </figure>
  -->
  
  <p>
    Follow these steps to create a character
    <label>sec:character_creation</label>
  </p>

  <!--
      {% include "tables/hit_point_bonuses.xml" %}
  -->



  <olist>
    <li>
      <p>
        Choose an archetype.
      </p>            
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
        Choose a name for the character.
      </p>            
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
        Write your name in the players name area on the character sheet.
      </p>            
    </li>

    <li>
      Fill in your height, weight, and age as specified by the archetype.  Choose
      whatever gender you like.  
    </li>
    
    <li>
      <p>
        Determine your Primary Attributes using one of the following two methods:
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        <term>Random</term> 
        <description>For each attribute, roll 5d4, remove a single die with the lowest
	value, and assign the sum of the remaing dice values to the attribute.  After 
	all attributes have been assigned, optionally swap one or two pairs of
	attribute values.
        </description>  
        
        <term>Fixed</term> 
        <description>Choose one of the following sets of numbers and assign them to 
	the primary attributes of your choice:
	<list>
	  <li>15, 14, 12, 11, 10, 9, 7 or</li>
	  <li>14, 14, 13, 11, 10, 9, 7</li>
	</list>
        </description>
      </descriptions>
    </li>

    <li>
      Fill in your opposed check modifiers.  The opposed check modifier for an attribute
      is the value of the attribute minus nine, e.g. Dourli has a Strength of 14 and an
      Agility of 7.  His opposed strength check modifier is +5 and his opposed agility
      check modifier is -2.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Initiative Score and Modifier:
      <equation>
	<line>Initiative Score =</line>
	<line>Archetype Initiative +</line>
	<line>Speed Attribute Initiative Bonus</line>
      </equation>
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Movement and Movement Modifier.
      <label>sec:character_movement</label>
      <equation>
	<line>Moves =</line>
	<line>Archetype Movement +</line>
	<line>Speed Attribute Move Bonus</line>
      </equation>
      Your movement modifier is the same as your movement.
    </li>
        
    
    <li>
      Determine your Stamina.
      <equation>
	<line>Stamina =</line>
	<line>Archetype Stamina +</line>
	<line>Endurance Attribute Bonus for Stamina</line>
      </equation>
      The Archetype stamina is listed in the archetype description and the Attribute Bonus 
      Table, see Table <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</ref> on page <pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</pageref>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Determine your characters Health.
      <equation>
	<line>Health =</line>
	<line>Archetype Health +</line>
	<line>Strength Attribute Bonus for Health</line>
      </equation>

      The Archetype Health is listed in the archetype Level Progression Table and the
      Strength Bonus is in the Attribute Bonus Table <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</ref> on page <pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</pageref>.      
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Resolve Dice Pool, Refresh Rate and Current Pool: 
      <equation>
	<line>Resolve =</line>
	<line>Archetype Resolve Dice +</line>
	<line>Willpower Attribute Bonus Dice for Resolve</line>
      </equation>
      The Archetype Resolve is listed in the archetype Level Progression Table and the
      Attribute Bonus Table <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</ref> on page
      <pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses</pageref>.
    </li>

    <li>
      Fill in your Magic Pool and Magic Refresh Rate as described by your archetypes
      level progression table.  The current pool starts equal to your Magic Pool.
      Some archetypes have no magic pool and you can ignore this step for those
      archetypes.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Fate Refresh Rate and Max Fate Pool from your archetype
      with bonuses for Luck from the Attibute Bonus Table 2, see Table
      <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses2</ref> on page
      <pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_attribute_bonuses2</pageref>.  Set your Fate Pool
      to your Max Fate Pool value.
    </li>
    
    <li>
      The rate of character progression is determined by Story Progression Points.
      Starting SPP is zero unless the GM states otherwise.  The SPP required to reach
      the next level is recorded in the archetype description document.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine the Skill Points you have available from your archetype level progression 
      table and record them on your character sheet.
    </li>

    <li>
      <p>
        Players should choose a few initial aspects for their character.   Newly acquired 
	aspects have a difficulty of $4 + d4$ unless the archetype description or the GM
	says otherwise.
      </p>
      <p>
	During the course of the game new aspects can be added and old aspects removed so 
	the initial choice is not overly important.  We suggest you choose one aspect that 
	describe your characters politics, motivations or troubles and another one that 
	describes your characters relationship with some other member in the party.
      </p>
      <p>
	To provide inspiration, each archetype has some suggested aspects. There is also 
	a table of random aspects in Section <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}_random_aspects</ref>
	on page <pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}_random_aspects</pageref>.  You do not have to
	choose aspects from these lists.  You are more than welcome to create your own.  In
	fact it is preferable.  Just make sure to run your aspects past your GM before
	committing them to paper, as GMs and players may need to collaborate to ensure that
	their character's aspects and the world, interact in interesting ways and are cogent.  
      </p>
    </li>

    <li>
      Optionally sketch out a couple of lines of back story with your fellow players and 
      GM with a few points about the characters history.  For example, Dourli might come from 
      the Iron Mountains and be searching for his long lost cousin Grimli.
    </li>

    <li>
      Buy your starting skills using the skill point price list for your archetype.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine the starting money as described by your archetype.
    </li>

    <li>
      Buy equipment.
    </li>

    <li>
      Determine your Armour Class:
      <equation>
	<line>Armour Class =</line>
	<line>Archetype Armour Class +</line>
	<line>Shield Armour Class Bonus +</line>
	<line>Speed Armour Class Bonus</line>
      </equation>
      The shield bonus is available when equipping shields and a few other 
      weapons that can be used defensively.
    </li>
    
  </olist>


  {% include "tables/attribute_bonuses.xml" %}

  <!--
  { % include "tables/attribute_bonuses2.xml" % }
      
  <figure position="tb">
    <img src="./resources/dragon_head.png" scale="0.15"/>
  </figure>
  -->
</section>
