
<section>
  <sectiontitle>Pursuit</sectiontitle>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Stages of a Pursuit</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      At some point the characters are going to want to flee from an opponent or to
      chase a fleeing opponent.  This section descibes rules for fleeing and pursuit.
    </p>


    <p>
      There are four stages of pursuit:
    </p>

    <descriptions>
      
      <term>Disengaging</term>
      <description>
	If a group is trying to flee from combat they must first disengage.
	When playing on a grid this means they must make it to the edge of
	the grid and leave the map.  If playing using TOTM the group disengages
	when all members run from the combat.  At this point they are distant 
	enough from the battle that they are considered to be out of combat.
	In order for their attackers to start combat with them again they must
	be successfully pursued.
      </description>

      <term>Decide to Pursue</term>
      <description>
	Pursuit is optional.  Actors with the checked condition cannot pursue.
      </description>

      <term>Chasing</term>
      <description>
	Chasing is the most complicated of these steps and we cover it in more detail
	in the next section.
      </description>

      <term>Tracking</term>
      <description>
	Occurs when the pursuer can no longer see the quarry.  In the wilderness
	they have to use the Tracking skill vs their opponents Evasion.  In cities
	they might have to question people, possibly using diplomacy, intimidation,
	or bribery.
      </description>
      
    </descriptions>
    
    <p>
      Of these four steps, Chasing is the only one that is not covered elsewhere so
      we will cover that here.
    </p>
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Chasing</subsectiontitle>
    
    <p>
      Chasing occurs when one group is pursuing another and the pursued group is
      intermittently visible, or there is broken ground to stop the pursuers, or
      the quarry is running to some safe location.  The pursuers just need to close
      the distance between them and their quarry.   The quarry just need to get far
      enough ahead that they can slip away or reach safety.
    </p>

    <p>
      Pursuit works as follows.  Assign every member of the pursuit an initial chase
      rank that represents their position in the chase.  Give the lead pursuer a rank
      of 5 and other pursuers lower ranks. Now assign higher ranks to those being pursued
      relative to the lead pursuer.  For example the members of the quarry closest to the
      lead pursuer might get an initial rank of 6 or 7.  If there are members of the
      quarry who started running earlier then they might get an initial rank of 8, or 9.
    </p>

    <p>
      Every turn of the chase each member of the chase takes an action, see below
      for a list of example actions.  Most of these actions will effect their chase
      rank or the rank of other members of the chase.
    </p>

    <descriptions>
      <term>Move</term>
      <description>
	Increase rank by 2.
      </description>

      <term>Sprint</term>
      <description>
	Test versus movement.  If successful increase rank by 3, otherwise increase
	rank by 2 and gain the Tired condition.  If the character has the tired
	condition then they gain the Exhausted condition.  FIXME: MAKE THIS AN ABILITY.
      </description>
      
      <term>Flee</term>
      <description>
	FIXME: XXXX
      </description>

      <term>Ranged Attack</term>
      <description>
	Make a missile attack.  If the weapon is tagged Fast then the character
	can also increase their chase rank by one.  Benefits might slow a pursuer down
	as they take cover.
      </description>

      <term>Reload Slow Weapons</term>
      <description>
	Reload slow missile weapons.  The character takes the whole round to reload their
	weapon.
      </description>
      
      <term>Create Obstacle</term>
      <description>
	The character does something that will slow their pursuers.  Characters can only
	perform this action if they can describe a feasible way to slow their pursuers.
	For example they might tip over a cart in a town.  However on a plain there
	might be no way to create an obstacle.
      </description>
      
      <term>Melee Attacks</term>
      <description>
	When the lead pursuers rank is the same as that of the trailing quarry,
	the pursuer and the quarry may make melee attacks against one another.
	If they do so they increase their chase rank only one.
      </description>

      <term></term>
      <description>
      </description>
      
    </descriptions>
  </subsection>

  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>When does a Chase End?</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Chases end when some predetermined condition is reached.  The three most
      common conditions are: <defn>When the Pursuit is Lost</defn>, 
      <defn>Upon Arrival at a Destination</defn>, and <defn>When the Quarry is Run
      Down</defn>.
    </p>

    <p>
      Pursuit is lost when the lowest ranking quarrys rank is greater than the
      highest pursuers rank plus five at the end of the round.  In this case the
      quarry has evaded their pursuers.

      <equation>
	<line>Pursuit is Lost:</line>
	<line>Lowest Quarry Rank <geqqsymbol/> Highest Pursuer Rank + 5</line>
      </equation>      
    </p>

    
    <p>
      In certain scenarios there is some safe place to which the quarry is fleeing,
      for example, imagine a group of Halflings fleeing towards a river ferry while
      pursued by dark horsemen.  In these situations the ferry is represented by its 
      own chase rank.  Any of the quarry that reach the specified rank have arrived
      at their destination.
    </p>

    <p>
      When a pursuers chase rank <emph>exceeds</emph> the rank of the trailing quarry
      that quarry is said to be Run Down.  At this point the quarry can no longer flee
      and is back in combat.
    </p>    
  </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>Random Encounters while Chasing</subsectiontitle>

    <p>
      Random encounters may occur during a chase.  The chase might run into
      a midnight procession of the worshippers of the gods of bachanalia,
      maybe there is a cart blocking the path, or they run into the night watch.	
      Refer to chase events table for random events (FIXME: TO BE DONE LATER).
    </p>	        
  </subsection>
  
</section>
