<section>
  <sectiontitle>Death and Damage<label>sec:death</label></sectiontitle>

  <p>
    The GM is the final arbiter of who lives and dies in the game.  However
    these decisions are not made in a vacuum.  The GM should understand the
    expectations of the players about the lethality of the campaign.  It is
    perhaps best if the GM discusses campaign lethality with the players
    before the campaign starts.  Whatever lethality is acceptable it behooves
    the GM to exagerate the lethality of the game to the players while playing
    in order to maximise suspense. Any decisions about character death should
    be made with careful consideration and never made arbitrarily or maliciously.
    If possible delay the outcome to the next session to give you time to think of
    an alternative result.
  </p>

  <p>
    There are six game mechanisms by which we handle character death, injury
    and insanity.  They are Hit Points, Fractional Damage, Near Death, Instant Death,
    Aspects (for phobias, insanity, disease, chronic illnesses and disabilities) and
    Divine Intervention.
  </p>

  <descriptions>
    <term>Hit Points</term>
    <description>
      <p>
       Hit points, that is Stamina and Health, are used to determine the players
       well-being, mainly during combat and combat-like scenarios.  These are scenarios
       where the player's skill and experience would be pertinent to avoiding injury.
       Combat is one example of this.  Another example might be avoiding
       poison darts from a trap.
      </p>
    </description>

    <term>Fractional Damage</term>
    <description>
      <p>
       Fractional damage occurs to a character when the character suffers damage outside
       of combat.  For example a character that falls off a roof may take two thirds
       of their total full hit points damage.  When calculating fractional damage
       round down any remainder so that damage is minimized.
      </p>
    </description>

    <term>Near Death</term>
    <description>
      Once the characters hit points reach zero they gain the Near-Death condition and
      probably the Down and Prone conditions as well.  Each round
      they roll on the Near Death Table until their situation is resolved; see
      Table<ref>table:gmg-near-death-table</ref> on page
      <pageref>table:gmg-near-death-table</pageref>.  If an effect reduces a character
      to Near Death then all their hit points are reduced to zero.
    </description>

    <term>Instant Death</term>
    <description>
      There are some situations where the character cannot possibly survive, <eg/>
      falling from a great height into a sea of lava.  In this case the GM can
      rule that the character has died instantly.   The GM should remember that
      the characters are supposed to be epic heroes and give them every chance
      of saving themselves before having them die like this.
      <p>
	Before killing a character outright the GM may consider the following:
	<olist>
	  <li>Declare an alternate outcome of some sort, or</li>
	  <li>Negotiating an outcome with the player and the party, or</li>
	  <li>Ending the session to gain time to ponder the best response at length.</li>
	</olist>
      </p>
    </description>
    
    <term>Aspects</term>
    <description>
      One use of aspects is to encode ongoing effects to a character.  A character
      who nearly drowns might gain a hydrophobia aspect.  A charcter who falls
      off a building might gain a crippled aspect.  A character with a disease might
      gain a Coughs aspect.  Because these aspects have an ongoing effect on a character
      the GM should assign them sparingly to characters.
      We suggest only doing so in the case of banes rolled while saving.
    </description>

    <term>Divine Intervention<daggersymbol/></term>
    <description>
      Divine intervention is a special rule where the characters last act is to plead
      for intervention from a God or patron before they die.  They make a Std Check with
      a difficulty of 24, if successful the God intervenes, usually indirectly, on the
      characters behalf somehow.  Particularly religious characters gain a +1
      on this roll.    If the character has donated to the gods church recently they gain
      an additional +1.  Such intervention, when it happens, is never free of obligation
      and the god will surely require something in return.
    </description>
  </descriptions>


  <p>
    FIXME: 
    Outside of combat
    
    HP only in combat?
    - hit points are the enemy of narrative.
    - plot armour.
    - sword to the throat.
    - outs!!!

    The GM should choose the option that is most reasonable and narratively satisfying.
    If a character falls into a pool of lava they are dead.  If they have been knocked
    down by Orcs then roll on the Near Death Table.  

    How should we handle falling, drowning damage etc.   In short the
    answer is don't.  Whenever there's a chance of failure in potentially
    fatal checks like this you're doing it wrong.  Establish the potential
    consequences ahead of time and possible outs.  If they fail then their
    party members might have a chance to save them?  Possibly failure just
    means they can't perform the action (e.g. climb the cliff).
  </p>
  
  
  {% include "docs/tables/near_death_table.xml" %}
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Combat Damage
    <indexentry>Death <subentry>see Zero Health</subentry></indexentry>
    <indexentry>Zero Hit Points</indexentry>
    <indexentry>Banes</indexentry>
  </sectiontitle>

  <p>
    We make a distinction between damage dealt to characters within combat, and
    damage dealt to characters outside of combat.  The GM should handle damage dealt within
    combat using Hit Points and Near Death Rolls.  That is, when a character is hit
    they take the damage from the weapon and they subtract that damage from the characters
    hit points. A characters Health has a minimum value of zero.  When the characters
    Health is reduced to zero they are <defn>Down</defn>, and enter a
    <emph>Near Death</emph> state.  
  </p>
  
  <p>           
    This does <emph>not</emph> apply to damage dealt outside of combat, including danger
    to the character due to things like drowning, falling, fire, poison, assasination,
    coup de grâce etc.  In these situations, hit points are the enemy of the narrative,
    they kill suspense, and they should not be used.  Besides, it makes no sense that a
    10th level fighter character should be more resistant to drowning than a 1st level
    fighter.
  </p>    
  
  {% include "docs/tables/near_death_table.xml" %}
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Falling Damage</sectiontitle>

  <p>
    When a character falls the type of damage they receive depends on how
    far they fall, see Table <ref>table:falling</ref> on page
    <pageref>table:falling-table</pageref>.  The GM should feel free to
    make allowances for the character slowing their fall, or the surface that
    the character is landing on as they see fit.  For example the characters
    should be allowed to make a Luck check to see if they fall on something
    soft or at least not to damaging or perhaps hitting an awning half way down.
    The characters could make an agility check to see if they are able to grab
    something to reduce the speed of their fall.  Each such success should reduce
    the fall damage by one tier in the Falling Damage table.
  </p>

  <p>
    For example, a character falls off the top of a five story building. They make
    an agility check and hit an awning on the way down.  They make a further Luck
    check and land in a stack of hay.
  </p>

  {% include "docs/tables/falling_damage.xml" %}    
</section> 


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Suffication and Drowning</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    Most people can hold their breath for 2 minutes, 12 combat rounds.
    Beyond that they must start to roll on the Near Death table.  Once
    they can breathe again then they are restored completely.  No hit points
    are lost.  If they rolled a bane on any of their death rolls
    the GM might consider giving them an aspect or a temporary condition.
  </p>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Fire Damage</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    XXXX FIXME
  </p>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Coup de Grâce and Assassination</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    Narrative imperative...
  </p>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Poison</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    XXXX
  </p>
</section>




<section>
  <sectiontitle>Diseases<label>sec:diseases</label></sectiontitle>

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      The Red Death
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Wasting Murrain
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
      From zombies?
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      The Wasting Sickness
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Leprosy
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Confutatis Maledictis
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Sweating Sickness
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Bad Humours
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Hemophilia
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Hysterical Blindness
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Rabies
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  
  
  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      Spotted Fever
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
  

  <subsection>
    <subsectiontitle>
      The Ague
    </subsectiontitle>
    <p>
      FIXME: TO DO
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>


<section>
  <sectiontitle>Insanity<label>sec:insanity</label></sectiontitle>
  <p>
    When under stress or in the face of great danger a character might
    succumb to insanity.  See the section on Insanities below.
    Insanity might at the GMs discretion lead to sudden insights or
    vice versa.
  </p>
  

  {% include "docs/tables/insanities.xml" %}  
</section>
