<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  <titlepage>
    <vspace>2</vspace>
    <title>Malleus Deum</title>  
    <vspace>6</vspace>
    <img src="resources/dragon_title/dragon.jpg" scale="0.6"/>
    <vspace>6</vspace>
    <subtitle>Igitur qui desiderat pacem, praeparet bellum.</subtitle>
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <author>Blaize A. Rhodes</author>
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <author>William F. Rhodes</author>    
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <version>{{ db.version }}</version>
  </titlepage>


  <tableofcontents/>  

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Introduction</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Design Philosophy</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	Malleus Deum 
	favours a combat as war versus a combat as sport philosophy.  That is if the 
        players can avoid a fight or enter a fight with advantages due to planning then that 
        is a good thing.  Players should be attempting to tilt the balance of combat in their 
        favour.  The combat as sport approach has each fight an independent thing and it 
        should be "fair" to both sides.        
      </p>

      <p>
        Magic items are rare.  If everyone has a dozen magic items then they lose their 
        specialness.

	FIXME.. what the hell is this all about?
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>



  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Designing Campaigns, Adventures and Encounters</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Story-Telling</sectiontitle>       
      
      <p>
	If playing a tabletop RPG is collaboratively story-telling then what does
	the GM need to know to make for a good story?  At its simplest good stories
	are about conflict resolution.  There is some central problem that provides the
	Central Tension	to the story, which may, or may not, get resolved during
	the campaign.  As you play, other sub-problems or completely unrelated problems
	arise; see Matt Colville on Youtube, or various articles on the Three Act Structure
	or Harmon's story structure online for more information.  Progress in the game
	is about the progress of the solution of these problems so it behooves the GM to
	have a well defined idea about the problems in their campaign.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	In contrast, it is also important that the GM not enforce too much structure on the
	players.  So be open to adopting problems that the players generate and keep the
	possible solutions to those problems vague in your head. This stops you from
	railroading the players into following your path and also drastically reduces the
	amount of work you need to do in preparation.
      </p>

      <p>
	The game is played as a set of, loosely defined, encounters.  Encounters allow players
	to move the story forward by making progress towards solving the problems in the story,
	and develop their characters personalities.  An Encounter might be a fight, a
	diplomatic discussion, a trap, the site of a mystery, etc.  Malleus Deum has been
	designed to provide support for a wide variety of encounter types and their resolutions.
	We now briefly discuss planning various types of encounters while highlighting
	the rule mechanisms in Malleus Deum designed to make those encounters interesting.
      </p>

    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Combat Encounter Design</sectiontitle>
      <p>
	Combat encounters should be easy to design in Malleus Deum.  We aim to have
	a game where the GM can throw together an encounter during the game without
	too much effort.  This allows the GM to react to players actions, hopefully
	giving the world an open sand-box feeling.
      </p>


      <p>
	Our goal in this section is to determine the minimum amount of work to completely
	cover eventualities in a combat encounter so that you are not completely taken
	by surprise when something unusual happens.  
      </p>

      <p>
	Firstly, combat encounters need foes and a location.  Choose these at
	your discretion.
      </p>

      <p>
	The rest of the encounter design involves addressing each of the
	following points and write down a half dozen words or so for each one
	as an aid to memory, if applicable to that encounter.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        
        <term>Location:</term>
        <description>
        </description>

        <term>Foes:</term>      
        <description>
        </description>
      
        <term>Outs:</term>
        <description>
        </description>
      
        <term>Purpose:</term>      
        <description>
        </description>
      
        <term>Tension:</term>      
        <description>
        </description>
      </descriptions>

<!--
      <subsubsection>
	<subsubsectiontitle>Modifying the Difficulty on the Fly</subsubsectiontitle>
    <p>
      Toughening the encounter up on the fly...
      Add minions, a special ability, events etc .. should things get too easy.
    </p>
	
      </subsubsection>	

  
    <p>
      moral imperative/threat
      progression ... how does this move the story forward?
      tension/timer/what's at stake?
      treat
      out
      encounter nerfs and buffs

    </p>


    <p>
      Random encounters
      Random encounter rules?  .. provides tension.. forces the players not to camp.
    </p>
    


    
-->      
      

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Special Rules in Malleus Deum</subsectiontitle>	

	<p>
	  Malleus Deum has a few rules mechanisms designed to make combat a little more
	  multi-dimensional than most other systems.  Firstly, there is a cost to making
	  Magic and Morale checks.  This brings an element of resource management to combat
	  and imposes a cost on fighting.  The intention is to provide positive feedback
	  to avoiding combat or to ambushing the opponent.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Another difference between Malleus Deum and many other RPGs is that the characters
	  make Morale checks and may be forced to flee.  In other RPGs combat is often
	  a binary affair, the characters prevail or are all killed.  In Malleus Deum
	  the characters may be driven off.  This means that when designing an encounter
	  the result of the combat need not be in the players favour.  That uncertainty
	  leads to more tension during encounters.
	</p>

	<p>
	  To inject a little flavour and context into combat Std Checks have benefits and
	  consequences.  These provide hooks that allow the GM to reward characters by
	  describing their extraordinary success or failure, for example they might be
	  able to instantly kill a minor opponent, or their sword might break.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  Finally the initiative system is designed to provide a large advantage
	  for ambushers and encourages the diplomatic resolution of combat encounters.
	</p>
      </subsection>



      

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Combat Lethality and Outs</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          Balance is a difficult thing to maintain in role-playing games.  There are a 
          number of alternative ways to achieve balance.  Many games rely on the GM to achieve 
          balance and he spends his time buffing the monsters or nerfing them to make 
          encounters challenging.  Combat can be fast and lethal though and all of a sudden 
          the party might be in serious trouble purely due to unfortunate dice rolling.
        </p>

	<p>
	  The GM can create encounters that they know will be underpowered and will not
	  overly challenge the party.  This is a perfectly reasonable thing to do and
	  we encourage you, as a GM, to do this.
	</p>	  
	
        <p>
          Another approach is to have theoretical models of the players and the monsters 
          powers. In this way you constrain the effects of combat to within well understood 
          limits, reducing the lethality of combat.  The problem with this  type of combat 
          is it typically results in slow slog-fests and favours having all encounters of 
          equal difficulty which is rather dull. 
        </p>

        <p>
	  A third approach is to throw challenging combat encounters at the players and
	  provide them with <defn>Outs</defn>.  An out is a way for the party to get out
	  of their predicament.  Outs should be designed a priori.   When the encounter is
	  being constructed the GM should spend some time thinking of a few different outs
	  if they can.  Outs are not needed for non-lethal encounters.  Outs include
	  fleeing, or being saved by the cavalry, being captured and any other kind of
	  Deus Ex Machina effects that save the party at the last minute.
        </p>

        <p>
          As a GM, use your judgment designing outs.  Try to think of a way out that is 
          contextual,  that makes sense.  The most important thing to make an Out seem
	  reasonable and uncontrived is to foreshadow the out.  The most important thing
	  to know about foreshadowing the out is to know what the out is.
        </p>

        <p>
          Force the players to run away if they won't.  Force a party morale test - hopefully 
          they'll fail and run away of their own accord.   Compel characters with cowardly 
          aspects to run.
        </p>

        <p>
          Use a <emph>Luck</emph> roll or an <emph>Intelligence</emph> roll to provide the 
          players with some advantage before you use an out.   They might, luckily, see a key 
          hanging on the wall or they might realize that this would be the room where a key 
          might be stored.  It's better if the players abilities save them rather than a deus 
          ex machina.
        </p>

        <p>
          Use Luck Checks to get the party out of danger or to keep the story moving forward.
          Only one player should be allowed to make a Luck Check in a particular circumstance
          -- if everyone is allowed to make a Luck Check then it will very likely succeed and 
          the check will become meaningless.
        </p>


        <p>
          Finally, if you can think of nothing better use one of the <defn>outs</defn>
          defined for the encounter.  An out is a way to get the party out of immediate danger 
          or to avoid a TPK in the event of a loss.  For example:
        </p>

        <list>
          <li>In a town the town guards might turn up to help at a crucial moment.</li>
          <li>If the party is fighting the town guards themselves then have the guards run away
          or throw the players in gaol.</li>
          <li>If the players are fighting against slavers and they lose then they may wake up 
          in the hold of a slave ship.</li>
          <li>When fighting with Orcs they might be captured for sacrifice to one of their gods
          and or for eating at a later date.</li>
          <li>When fighting a bear get the player with woodland law to roll and then explain 
          that the bear is old, then have the bear die on the next hit.</li>
        </list>

        <p>
          If it becomes obvious to players that you are using outs then their actions become 
          meaningless and they may lose interest.   The advantage of outs is that because you 
          know what your outs will be you can use foreshadowing to make saving the characters 
          less heavy handed.  For example, say the players will be fighting cultists, mention 
          that ceremonially mutilated bodies are being found following a full moon, when the 
          players are wandering the streets mention how dark it is and that they will be 
          unlikely to catch anyone in flagrante delicto as it is not even a full moon.  Then 
          if they are captured they will be imprisoned until the next full moon.  
          Also have them meet the towns guard.  The towns guard will be very curious about what
          they are doing in the streets.  Later if the party is about to be overwhelmed by 
          cultists the towns guard can show up without it feeling like the GMs just saved them.
        </p>



	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Foreshadowing</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
            For combat to be interesting strategically it is important that there
            be a chance of failure.  However, as combat is highly lethal it may
            result in a total party kill, which is a generally undesirable outcome.
	  </p>
	  
	  <p>
            There are two approaches to solving this problem.  The first is to make
            sure that the characters are able to win the combat by providing deliberately
            easy foes.  While this works, if overused it leads to a dull combat experience.
	  </p>               

	  <p>
            The second approach to solving this problem is to provide an <defn>Out</defn>
            for the party should things go wrong. For example if the characters are fighting
            slavers and they lose then they can be enslaved and the game continues.  If
            they are fighting Orcs they may be kept for food later.  The city guards might
            throw them in the dungeon if they prevail against the party.
	  </p>


	  <p>
            A sub-type of the Out is the Deus Ex Machina.  In this case the party is
            saved right at the last minute by some third-party.  This is generally undesirable
            from a narrative perspective as it leads the players to believe that whatever
            they do some third-party will save them at the last minute, thus reducing tension.
	  </p>

	  <p>
            The trick to making Outs feel less contrived is <defn>Foreshadowing</defn>.
            As a GM, you should provide information to the characters about the Out so that
            if and when you have to use it the development in the narrative is less jarring.
            For example, if characters are trying to contact the elvish border guards in the
            Grey Forest and you, as the GM, know they are just about to run into giant spiders
            have the characters hear the guards trumpets in the distance.  If the players
            are fighting slavers, let them know that there have been slaver raids taking place.
            Also it is a good idea to plant these foreshadowing seeds earlier rather than later.
	  </p>

	  <p>
            In summary, to avoid combat annihilation try to have an Out for the characters
            before the combat.  Use foreshadowing in order to make the out seem less contrived.
	  </p>          
	</subsubsection>

	
	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Fleeing</subsubsectiontitle>

	  <p>
	    One good Out is to have fleeing be an option for the party.
	    When designing the encounter consider what will happen if the characters
	    have to flee.  If the characters flee, will they have a chance to escape,
	    consider characters on foot on the plains being pursued by horsemen, will
	    they be caught automatically.  If they are caught you need to have a reason
	    for the character not to be summarily killed, and most importantly
	    you need to have foreshadowed that reason in your narrative to the
	    players otherwise it will seem contrived, a deus ex machina.
	    If the players have an escape route mention that in the description
	    of the location.  Do not tell them ``This is the escape route''.
	    Let them work it out in the event they need to flee.  If the escape
	    is going to be a series of checks then have some idea what those might
	    be before hand.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>
	
	
	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Diplomacy</subsubsectiontitle>

	  <p>
	    Consider how the characters opponents might react to diplomacy.
	    If the foes are unlikly to normally be disposed
	    towards diplomacy, <eg/> an orc horde, then it is wise to foreshadow
	    that so that when they do start negotiating it does not seem
	    unusual, <eg/> there have been tales of orcs asking of the great
	    sword of M'lok and promising rewards for information leading to
	    its recovery.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Reveals, Goals and Story Progression</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Consider what the point of the encounter is.  How does it contribute
	  to the progression of the story.  What information might the characters
	  gain from the encounter.
	</p>

	<p>
	  If the characters have been had a series of
	  non-combat encounters then <emph>a change of pace</emph> is a reasonable
	  motivation for an encounter.
	</p>
	<p>
	  Is there any information that the characters should have and would have
	  before going into the combat?  If there is information that they might
	  have make them check for it.  Is there any information that the characters
	  should gain from the encounter?  Make sure that you remember to convey that
	  to them.
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Character Development</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Character Progression</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  The goals of a game shape the gaming experience.  It is one of the stated goals 
	  of Malleus Deum to deemphasize the role of combat in the game (compared with, say,
	  DnD). For this reason we do not award experience for combat as some other games do.
	  In fact, Malleus Deum does not use experience points at all.  Instead at certain
	  points in the game the GM just states <emph>you go up a level</emph>.  The GM should
	  choose these points when story arcs have been successfully resolved and the
	  characters are facing some down time.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Aspect Lifetime</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>





  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Special Cases</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Sudden Death</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	XXXX handle sudden death stuff (falling, drowning, poison etc)
      </p>
    </section>
    
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Damage</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Falling Damage</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  There are two types of falling damage.  Falls where
	  the character will be hurt and falls where the character
	  will die instantly.  It is important for the GM to remember
	  that this game is about heros.  So every opportunity to
	  avoid falling to the characters death should be given.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  When falling the character suffers d8 per <measurement><metric>5m</metric>
	  <imperial>10'</imperial></measurement> fallen.  
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  When characters are in danger of falling to their death
	  remember that this is not the story of

	  leaves on a bus.
	</p>

	<p>
	  XXXX  reroll, save to catch something, save to hit something on the way down, save for divine intervention.
	</p>
      </subsection> 

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Suffication and Drowning</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  XXXX
	</p>
      </subsection>
      

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Fire Damage</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  XXXX
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Divine Intervention</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  XXXX
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
    </section>    
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Monsters</chaptertitle>
    {% include "docs/fragment_monsters.xml" %}
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Magic Items</chaptertitle>
    {% include "docs/fragment_magic_items.xml" %}
  </chapter>



  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Customization</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Modular Design</sectiontitle>      
      <p>
	Adding abilities.  Adding Archetypes.	
      </p>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Dice Probabilities</sectiontitle>       
      
      <p>
	
	
      </p>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Game Balance, The Maths</sectiontitle>       
      
      <p>
	Balance is important in role-playing games.  Not everything has to be balanced but 
	it is important to know and make a conscious decision to make something imbalanced.
	Note that the effect of doing this can be far-reaching.  Imbalance is also important
	if the players chance of success always remains the same they have no motivation to 
	think outside the box in order to gain an advantage.
      </p>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Ability Point Costs</subsectiontitle>       
	<p>
	  Default point cost should be around 5 per ability, most abilities total point cost
	  should be in the range 3-7.  Abilities should only cost one type of point, <ie/>
	  one of Martial, Lore, General or Magical.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  Each level the character should get about 35 points.

	  Remember to take into account that lore and general points are usually less
	  useful during combat and so are less desirable than martial and magical points.

	  SPECIAL LEVELS NAME!!
	</p>
	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Monster Hit Points and Balancing Combat</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
          In order to balance play we have the following set of rules of thumb to 
          allow us to maintain game balance.  
	</p>

	<p>
          High damage dealing characters should be able to kill a ``standard'' monster
	  of their level with two average hits.  Non-combat specialist characters should 
          be able to kill a monster in two or three average hits.  By standard we mean
	  a typical monster for that level, <eg/> goblins for level 1.
	</p>      
	
	<p>
          Combat classes should hit on average two in three times.  Non combatants should hit 
          ever second attack.
	</p>

	<p>
          We will choose 
          
          Combat centric characters deal: 
          5 hit points + 2*level when they hit.
          
          Non combat characters deal:
          3 hit points + 2*level           
	</p>
	
	<p>
          Monster armour class flows from those two
	</p>

      </subsection>
      
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Creating New Skill Trees</sectiontitle>       
      <p>
	An average level skill should cost 5 skill points.
      </p>

      <p>
	If skills require successes/attempts then they must have a Check defined.
	The check should include a DDC.  If the check uses a dice pool the ability
	should also have an overcharge value.  The overcharge should be a value
	relative to the DC used .. e.g. DC + 5.
      </p>
      
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Creating New Roles</sectiontitle>        
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Temporary Insanity</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	Insanity might at the GMs discretion lead to sudden insights or vice versa.
      </p>
      
      {% include "docs/tables/insanities.xml" %}
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Monster and NPC Abilities</sectiontitle>

      {% from "docs/macro_ability.xml" import build_ability with context %}
      
      {% for ability in ability_groups.get_abilities() if ability.is_gmg_ability() %}
      {{ build_ability(ability) }}    
      {% endfor %}      
      
    </section>
    
  </chapter>  
</book>

