<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  <titlepage>
    <vspace>2</vspace>
    <title>Malleus Deum</title>  
    <vspace>7</vspace>
    <img src="resources/dragon_title/dragon_title.png" scale="0.3"/>
    <vspace>23</vspace>
    <subtitle>Igitur qui desiderat pacem, praeparet bellum.</subtitle>
    <vspace>2</vspace>
    <author>Blaize A. Rhodes</author>
  </titlepage>


  <tableofcontents/>  

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Introduction</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle></sectiontitle>       
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Philosophy</sectiontitle>       

      <p>
	Malleus Deum 
	 favours a combat as war versus a combat as sport philosophy.  That is if the 
        players can avoid a fight or enter a fight with advantages due to planning then that 
        is a good thing.  Players should be attempting to tilt the balance of combat in their 
        favour.  The combat as sport approach has each fight an independent thing and it 
        should be "fair" to both sides.        
      </p>

      <p>
        Magic items are rare.  If everyone has a dozen magic items then they lose their 
        specialness.
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>



  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Designing Adventures and Encounters</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Character Progression</sectiontitle>       
      
      <p>
	The goals of a game shape the gaming experience.  It is one of the stated goals 
	of Malleus Deum to deemphasize the role of combat in the game (compared with DnD).
	For this reason we do not award experience for like other games.  In fact, Malleus
	Deum does not use experience points at all.  Instead at certain points in the game
	the GM just states <emph>you go up a level</emph>.  The GM should choose these
	points when story arcs have been resolved and the characters are facing some down
	time.
      </p>


    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Story Arcs</sectiontitle>       

      <p>
        A <defn>Story Arc</defn> is a set of encounters that allow players to move their 
        story forward.  Encounters might be fights with the players nemeses or meetings 
        that divulge key facts that the players need to solve a mystery.
      </p>


      <p>
        The DM should use <defn>Foreshadowing</defn> to lead players into encounters.
      </p>

      <p>
        Goals associated with the story
      </p>

      <p>
        Lead ins

        what bits of information (foreshadowing) should the players have before getting here
        a list.
      </p>

      <p>
        Lead outs

        what bits of information should the players have when they leave.. or what bits might they pick up before they leave?
      </p>

      <p>
        Toughening the encounter up on the fly...
        Add minions, a special ability, events etc .. should things get too easy.
      </p>


      <p>
        Outs .. getting the players out of danger before they cark it.        
      </p>

      
    </section>

<!--
The GM doesn't have to spend a lot of time preparing - he or she just sketches Stakes and Consequences, some NPC names, and maybe a quick map of the local area. In Trollbabe, the author uses "Stakes" to mean an overall conflict in which the NPCs are engaged. Consequence is what's in jeopardy - a person's life, the existence of a village, the king's throne, etc. Stakes and Consequences are based on the Scale of the adventure - another cool concept that I will leave for the reader to discover should they decide to read the game text. The GM will usually need one situation for each Trollbabe.

-->



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Encounters</sectiontitle>       

      <p>
moral imperative
timer 
treat
threat
out
encounter nerfs and buffs
progression ... how does this move the story forward?

Personality. That is the key, the drum, the fife. Forget the plot."
—Chuck Jones 

The classical unities, Aristotelian unities, or three unities are rules for drama derived from a passage in Aristotle's Poetics. In their neoclassical form they are as follows:

    unity of action: a play should have one action that it follows, with minimal subplots.
    unity of time: the action in a play should occur over a period of no more than 24 hours.
    unity of place: a play should exist in a single physical space and should not attempt to compress geography, nor should the stage represent more than one place.



      </p>


      <p>
	Random encounters

Random encounter rules?  .. provides tension.. forces the players not to camp.
      </p>
        


      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Outs</subsectiontitle>       
        
        <p>
          Balance is a difficult thing to maintain in role-playing games.  There are a 
          number of alternative ways to achieve balance.  Many games rely on the DM to achieve 
          balance and he spends his time buffing the monsters or nerfing them to make 
          encounters challenging.  Combat can be fast and lethal though and all of a sudden 
          the party might be in serious trouble purely due to unfortunate dice rolling.
        </p>

        <p>
          Another approach is to have theoretical models of the players and the monsters 
          powers. In this way you constrain the effects of combat to within well understood 
          limits, reducing the lethality of combat.  The problem with this  type of combat 
          is it typically results in slow slog-fests and favours having all encounters of 
          equal difficulty which is rather dull. 
        </p>

        <p>
          Instead of balancing encounters our approach to this problem is to maintain the 
          potential lethality of combat but to provide a series of <defn>Outs</defn>.  An 
          out is a way for the party to get out of their predicament.  Outs are designed a 
          priori.   When the encounter is being constructed the DM should spend some time 
          thinking of a few different outs if they can.  Outs are not needed for non-lethal 
          encounters.
        </p>

        <p>
          As a DM, use your judgement designing outs.  Try to think of a way out that is 
          contextual,  that makes sense.  Tell the characters what is happening and allow 
          them to get away somehow.
        </p>

        <p>
          Force the players to run away if they won't.  Force a party morale test - hopefully 
          they'll fail and run away of their own accord.   Compel characters with cowardly 
          aspects to run.
        </p>

        <p>
          Use a <emph>Luck</emph> roll or an <emph>Intelligence</emph> roll to provide the 
          players with some advantage before you use an out.   They might, luckily, see a key 
          hanging on the wall or they might realize that this would be the room where a key 
          might be stored.  It's better if the players abilities save them rather than a deus 
          ex machina.
        </p>

        <p>
          Use Luck Checks to get the party out of danger or to keep the story moving forward.
          Only one player should be allowed to make a Luck Check in a particular circumstance
          -- if everyone is allowed to make a Luck Check then it will very likely succeed and 
          the check will become meaningless.
        </p>


        <p>
          Finally, if you can think of nothing better use one of the <defn>outs</defn>
          defined for the encounter.  An out is a way to get the party out of immediate danger 
          or to avoid a TPK in the event of a loss.  For example:
        </p>

        <list>
          <li>In a town the town guards might turn up to help at a crucial moment.</li>
          <li>If the party is fighting the town guards themselves then have the guards run away
          or throw the players in gaol.</li>
          <li>If the players are fighting against slavers and they lose then they may wake up 
          in the hold of a slave ship.</li>
          <li>When fighting with Orcs they might be captured for sacrifice to one of their gods
          and or for eating at a later date.</li>
          <li>When fighting a bear get the player with woodland law to roll and then explain 
          that the bear is old, then have the bear die on the next hit.</li>
        </list>

        <p>
          If it becomes obvious to players that you are using outs then their actions become 
          meaningless and they may lose interest.   The advantage of outs is that because you 
          know what your outs will be you can use foreshadowing to make saving the characters 
          less heavy handed.  For example, say the players will be fighting cultists, mention 
          that ceremonially multilated bodies are being found following a full moon, when the 
          players are wandering the streets mention how dark it is and that they will be 
          unlikely to catch anyone in flagrante delicto as it is not even a full moon.  Then 
          if they are captured they will be imprisoned until the next full moon.  
          Also have them meet the towns guard.  The towns guard will be very curious about what
          they are doing in the streets.  Later if the party is about to be overwhelmed by 
          cultists the towns guard can show up without it feeling like the DMs just saved them.
        </p>
        
      </subsection>
      
    </section>




    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Foreshadowing and Outs</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        For combat to be interesting strategically it is important that there
        be a chance of failure.  However, as combat is highly lethal it may
        result in a total party kill, which is a generally undesirable outcome.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        There are two approaches to solving this problem.  The first is to make
        sure that the characters are able to win the combat by providing deliberately
        easy foes.  While this works, if overused it leads to a dull combat experience.
      </p>               

      <p>
        The second approach to solving this problem is to provide an <defn>Out</defn>
        for the party should things go wrong. For example if the characters are fighting
        slavers and they lose then they can be enslaved and the game continues.  If
        they are fighting Orcs they may be kept for food later.  The city guards might
        throw them in the dungeon if they prevail against the party.
      </p>


      <p>
        A sub-type of the Out is the Deus Ex Machina.  In this case the party is
        saved right at the last minute by some third-party.  This is generally undesirable
        from a narrative perspective as it leads the players to believe that whatever
        they do some third-party will save them at the last minute, thus reducing tension.
      </p>

      <p>
        The trick to making Outs feel less contrived is <defn>Foreshadowing</defn>.
        As a GM, you should provide information to the characters about the Out so that
        if and when you have to use it the development in the narrative is less jarring.
        For example, if characters are trying to contact the elvish border guards in the
        Grey Forest and you, as the GM, know they are just about to run into giant spiders
        have the characters hear the guards trumpets in the distance.  If the players
        are fighting slavers, let them know that there have been slaver raids taking place.
        Also it is a good idea to plant these foreshadowing seeds earlier rather than later.
      </p>

      <p>
        In summary, to avoid combat annihilation try to have an Out for the characters
        before the combat.  Use foreshadowing in order to make the out seem less contrived.
      </p>          
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Sudden Death</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        XXXX handle sudden death stuff (falling, drowning, poison etc)
      </p>
    </section>

  </chapter>



  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Monsters</chaptertitle>
    {% include "docs/fragment_monsters.xml" %}
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Magic Items</chaptertitle>
    {% include "docs/fragment_magic_items.xml" %}
  </chapter>
  


  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Customization</chaptertitle>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Modular Design</sectiontitle>      
      <p>
	Adding abilities.  Adding Archetypes.	
      </p>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Dice Probabilities</sectiontitle>       
      
      <p>
	
	
      </p>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Game Balance, The Maths</sectiontitle>       
      
      <p>
        Balance is important in role-playing games.  Not everything has to be balanced but 
        it is important to know and make a conscious decision to make something imbalanced.
        Note that the effect of doing this can be far-reaching.  Imbalance is also important
        if the players chance of success always remains the same they have no motivation to 
        think outside the box in order to gain an advantage.
      </p>

      <p>
	Default point cost should be around 5 per ability, most abilities total point cost
	should be in the range 3-7.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        In order to balance play we have the following set of rules of thumb to 
        allow us to maintain game balance.  
      </p>

      <p>
        High damage dealing characters should be able to kill a monster of their 
        level in two turns on average.  Non-combat specialist characters should 
        be able to kill a monster in three turns on average.
      </p>      
      
      <p>
        Combat classes should hit on average two in three times.  Non combatants should hit 
        ever second attack.
      </p>

      <p>
        We will choose 
        
        Combat centric characters deal: 
           5 hit points + 2*level when they hit.
           
        Non combat characters deal:
           3 hit points + 2*level           
      </p>
          
      <p>
        Monster armour class flows from those two
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Creating New Skill Trees</sectiontitle>       
      <p>
        An average level skill should cost 5 skill points.
      </p>

      <p>
        If skills require successes/attempts then they must have a Check defined.
	The check should include a DDC.  If the check uses a dice pool the ability
	should also have an overcharge value.  The overcharge should be a value
	relative to the DC used .. e.g. DC + 5.
      </p>
      
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Creating New Roles</sectiontitle>        
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Temporary Insanity</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	Insanity might at the GMs discretion lead to sudden insights or vice versa.
      </p>
      
      {% include "docs/tables/insanities.xml" %}
    </section>    
  </chapter>  
</book>
