<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Magic Items</chaptertitle>    
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Miscellaneous Magic Items</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	Herein lies the descriptions, such as they are, of the magical
	items that are widely known to any prepared to open a book and
	read.
      </p>

      <!--
	http://hyboria.xoth.net/sorcery/sorcerous_societies.htm
	http://hyboria.xoth.net/sorcery/magical_items.htm
      -->

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Limaceous Grease</subsectiontitle>
	<descriptions>
	<term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
	<term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
	<term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
	<term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
	</descriptions>
	
        <p>
          Allows the player to squeeze into small places when rubbed upon the skin.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Potion of Odic Visions</subsubsectiontitle>
	<descriptions>
	<term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
	<term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
	<term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
	<term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
	<term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
	</descriptions>
        <p>
          Lets the player see the auras of other beings for a short period of time.
        </p>
      </subsubsection>


      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Book of Leviathan</subsubsectiontitle>
	  
        <p>
        </p>
      </subsubsection>


      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Enochian Keys</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
        </p>
      </subsubsection>

      
      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Compass of Seeking</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  The needle of this fine golden compass always points in
	  the direction of the last object that has been
	  imprinted upon it.
        </p>
      </subsubsection>


      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Pompatus Chapeau</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  A fine hat made by XXX of YYY that distracts all those who
	  know anything about fashion.	  Civilized observers must
	  make a difficult will power check or gain the Distracted
	  condition.
        </p>
      </subsubsection>


      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Runcible of XXXX</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
        </p>
      </subsubsection>
      

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Bag of Snigglets</subsubsectiontitle>
	<descriptions>
	<term>Type</term><description>One Use</description>
	<term>Dice Pool</term><description>2d6</description>
	<term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
	<term>Difficulty</term><description>4</description>
	<term>Overcharge</term><description>12</description>
	</descriptions>
	
        <p>
	  A small bag containing 3d6 snigglets.  Salted garlic snigglets
	  are, of course, a delicacy from far-off XXXX.  Their
	  moluscy, truffley flavour is overwhelming.  XXXX	  
        </p>
      </subsubsection>
      

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Doctrine of the Small Gods</subsubsectiontitle>
	<descriptions>
	<term>Dice Pool</term><description>1d4</description>
	<term>Refresh</term><description>N/A</description>
	<term>Difficulty</term><description>2</description>
	</descriptions>
	
        <p>
	  There are many minor and highly specialized deities that
	  spy on this world from planes both near or deep.  Hungry for
	  attention they listen for prayers.  This slight book is dedicated
	  to the small gods and contains the scrawlings of a gibbering
	  prophet.  Amongst the deranged rambling text are 1d4 + 1 prayers
	  to various highly specialized, highly obscure, and very minor
	  deities.  When read the character may ask for a small boon
	  from the god.	 Once all the spells have been cast the book
	  collapses into a different dimension in order to spread the word.
        </p>

	<p>
	  The default chance to succeed is Very Difficult using a std check.
	  The difficulty level can be reduced by one step if the character
	  provides suitable embellishment for his prayer (e.g. the name of
	  the small god, their varied domains, and their achievements).
	  The difficulty level can be reduced by a further step if the task
	  is very specific and very minor or increased by a step if the task
	  is demanding of the small god.	  
        </p>	  
      </subsubsection>

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Snare Scripture</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  Snare scriptures are small books that appear similar to a Doctrine
	  of the Small Gods.  This is not by unlikely coincidence.  As a spider,
	  burning with hunger in the icy night of their existence, pale entities
	  wait patiently for the unwary to read from their books which
	  they carefully seed across the inner planes.
        </p>

	<p>
	  XXXX
	</p>
      </subsubsection>

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Steel Termites</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
        </p>
      </subsubsection>


      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Necronomicon</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
        </p>
      </subsubsection>

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Hand of Glory</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
        </p>
      </subsubsection>

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Helm of the Minotaur <fightsymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
          The Helm of the Minotaur is a horned greater helm that allows the
          wearer to make a head butt attack once per battle at Std2d8 + 4 which does
          2d10 damage.  It is created by sacrificing a minotaur and trapping its animus
          in the helm using special entrapment runes.
        </p>

        <p>
          In addition the Helm may be used to bellow once per day.  Bellowing forces
          a morale check for the wearers opponents.
        </p>
      </subsubsection>

      

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Eyes of Azathoth</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  Kept in little clay jars with a layer of oil, this dust when thrown 
	  in the air immediately ignites causing blindness to those who fail against 
	  it for one turn.
        </p>
      </subsubsection>

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Compendium Maleficarum</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  Is a witch-hunter's manual
        </p>
      </subsubsection>

      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Pearl of Atlach-Nacha</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  A glossy black sphere the size of a mans fist.  When the secret words 
	  are spoken it hatches into an astral spider and attacks the being
	  it is commanded to.  After some time the spider d
        </p>
      </subsubsection>


      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Staff of Scorpion Wood</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  The wood from a deeply poisonous tree, that hails from the 
	  cold deserts of the west.  Staffs of this wood make a poison 
	  attack whenever they hit.
        </p>
      </subsubsection>


      <subsubsection>
        <subsubsectiontitle>Ring of the Serpent King</subsubsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  Allows the wearer to mesmerize someone by looking into their eyes.
	  They must make a Very Difficult Std Check added by their will power
	  or gain a Hypnotized Aspect with a starting difficulty equal to 14
	  minus their will power modifier or do as instructed.
        </p>
      </subsubsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
