<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<book>
  <titlepage>
    <vspace>2</vspace>
    <title>Malleus Deum</title>
    <vspace>6</vspace>
    <img id="dragon_title" scale="0.6"/>
    <vspace>6</vspace>
    <author>Blaize A. Rhodes</author>
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <version>{{ db.version }}</version>
  </titlepage>
  
  <tableofcontents/>
  <listoffigures/>
  <listofart/>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Introduction</chaptertitle>
    <section>    
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	<emph>
	The enemies are at the gates brothers!  Mankind is assailed on all sides.
	Go, tell them that they shall have no satisfaction while we still stand.  Those
	that seek to destroy us, both from without and from within, shall rue the day
	that they first sought our downfall, those that have sought to sow the
	wind, shall now reap the whirlwind. 
	</emph>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <indexentry>GM</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>NPC</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Player Character</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Non-Player Character</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Character</indexentry>
        Malleus~Deum is a fantasy pen and paper, tabletop, role-playing game (TTRPG).
        In Malleus Deum one player assumes the role of Game Master or <defn>GM</defn>
        and plays the part of a narrator in a collaborative story.  Other 
        players adopt the role of individual people within the story, called
        Player Characters.  All the other characters, and any monsters within the story
        are controlled by the GM and are referred to as Non-Player Characters or 
        <defn>NPCs</defn>.  We  use the term  
        <defn>Character</defn> to denote both player characters and non-player
        characters.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Difficulty</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>DC</subentry></indexentry>
        Each player character is described by a Character Sheet. Any narrative decisions 
        of moment within the game are made by <emph>Making Checks</emph> which involves 
        rolling dice.  The details of how this all fits together, how to create a
	character, how to make checks, and more is covered in the next few chapters.
      </p>

      <figure position="!b">
        <img id="durer_nativity" scale="0.4"/>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Character Creation</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:character-creation</label>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Character Overview</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Character</indexentry>
        Player Characters are described by:
        <list>
          <li>An Archetype and a Level.  The Archetype describes the characters race
          and their profession.  The Level describes how advanced, how powerful,
          the character is.</li>
          <li>
            <indexentry>Primary Abilities</indexentry>
            A set of five Primary Abilities: Strength, Endurance, Agility, Speed,
            and Perception.
          </li>
          <li>Four or more Defensive Abilities: Armour, Dodge, Block and Parry.</li>
          <li>Two Hit Point stats: Stamina and Health.</li>
          <li>Three Dice Pool stats: Mettle, Magic, and Luck.</li>
          <li>A set of Aspects. Aspects are statements that describe some facet of the
  	  characters personality, relationships, or philosophy e.g:
  	  Silent Outcast, Naive Appeaser, Dipsomaniac, Declared vengeance
  	  against Elogh King of the Goblins.  Aspects are tied to game mechanics and have
	  real consequences in the game, </li>
          <li>A range of other Abilities, drawn from four groups General, Lore, Martial and Magic,
	  <eg/> Sword Strike, Arcane Lore, Pick Locks, 
          and <ellipsis/></li>
          <li>Optionally, a description of the character, a back-story for the character,
          and any tertiary statistics the player might want to include:
          Height, Weight, Age, Hair Colour and so on.</li>
        </list>
        The characters abilities and aspects allow players to make checks to see whether their
        characters can successfully perform certain actions within the game.  Checks are
  	described further in Section<ref>sec:checks</ref> on page<pageref>sec:checks</pageref>.
        Steps to create a character can be found in the archetype document for the archetype
  	you wish to play.
      </p>

      <playexample>
        <img id="dwarf" scale="0.3">
          Young Dourli, Dwarven Shield Guard
        </img>

  	<p>
  	  For examples sake, in this book, we shall illustrate game mechanics using
  	  three PCs Dourli, intrepid dwarven warrior; Rozlyn, shadowy cutpurse; and
  	  Mophissius, sometime dabbler in the dark arts.
  	</p>
      </playexample>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Archetypes</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Archetype</indexentry>
        Each character has an archetype.  An <defn>Archetype</defn> is a combination of a
        race and a class, for example a character might choose to be a Dwarven Shield
        Warrior or a Halfling Rover.  Archetypes define which abilities a character may have
  	or learn and how hard it is for them to acquire that ability.
      </p>
      
      <design>
        Archetypes are indivisible because it makes them more modular and allows us to balance
        one archetype without effecting existing archetypes.
      </design>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Level</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Level</indexentry>
        Each character has a level which represents how much experience the characters has.
        The character's level usually starts at one and increases when the GM decides that
  	it is appropriate.  There are no experience points in this game. As a rule of thumb
	characters should gain levels at the end of a story arc or when the players have
	accomplished something noteworthy in the game.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Primary Abilities</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        All characters share a set of <defn>Primary Abilities</defn> that describe the characters
  	physical capabilities.  These provide a bonus to certain checks and may be
  	prerequisites for other abilities.   In Malleus Deum primary attributes are treated like all
	other abilities, see
	Section<ref>sec:primary_abilities</ref> on page<pageref>sec:primary_abilities</pageref>.	
      </p>

        <descriptions>
          <term>Strength</term><description>physical power</description>
          <term>Endurance</term><description>toughness, fitness and physical robustness</description>
          <term>Agility</term><description>nimbleness and fine motor control</description>
          <term>Speed</term><description>swiftness and fleetness of movement</description> 
          <term>Perception</term><description>insight and ability to notice things</description>
        </descriptions>

      <figure position="b">
        <img id="footer" scale="0.45"/>
      </figure>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Defensive Abilities</sectiontitle>
      <indexentry>Defence Check</indexentry>
      <p>
        Defensive abilities represent how difficult a character is to hit.  When an NPC tries to
  	hit a PC in combat the player makes a defensive ability check against the difficulty
  	of the attack.  The four most common defensive abilities that are available to
  	all characters are Armour, Dodge, Parry and Block, though there are others.
	We use the term <defn>Defence Check</defn> <indexentry>Defensive Checks</indexentry>
        to refer to these ability checks irrespective of what underlying defensive ability the
	player choose to make the check.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
	<term>Armour</term>
	<description>
          <indexentry>Defensive<subentry>see Armour</subentry></indexentry>
          <p>
  	    The character takes the brunt of the attack on their armour, hoping that it
  	    will protect them.  The bonus for this check is determined by the armour the
  	    character is wearing. A character may be harder to hit because they are wearing
  	    armour or carrying a shield.
          </p>
	</description>

	<term>Dodge</term>
	<description>
	  <indexentry>Defensive<subentry>see Dodge</subentry></indexentry>
	  <p>
  	    The character uses the dodge ability to attempt to leap out of the way of the
  	    attack, see page<pageref>ability:dodge</pageref>.
	  </p>
	</description>
	
	<term>Block</term>
	<description>
	  <indexentry>Defensive<subentry>see Block</subentry></indexentry>
	  <p>
	    The character blocks the attack using a shield or buckler using the
	    Shield Block skill, see page<pageref>ability:block</pageref>.
	  </p>
	</description>

	<term>Parry</term>
	<description>
	  <indexentry>Defensive<subentry>see Parry</subentry></indexentry>
	  <p>
	    The character attempts to stop the attack by parrying with their
	    weapon using the Parry skill (if the weapon can be used to parry).
	    Different weapon classes have their own parry abilities, see
	    Staff Parry on page<pageref>ability:staff.parry</pageref>. and
	    Sword Parry on page<pageref>ability:sword.parry</pageref>.
	  </p>
	</description>
      </descriptions>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Dice Pool Statistics</sectiontitle>
      <p>
  	Characters have three dice pool statistics: Mettle, Magic and Luck.
	Dice pools consist of a number of six sided dice.  Players start the game with
  	full dice pools. During the game they may lose dice from those pools by making dice pool
  	checks,	and they may return dice to their pools using various means including by resting.
	We describe how to use dice pools to make checks in Section<ref>sec:dice-pool</ref> on
        page<pageref>sec:dice-pool</pageref>.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        <term>Mettle</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Pools<subentry>see Mettle</subentry></indexentry>
          This dice pool measures the characters strength of character,
  	  their spirits and will-power, their mental well-being, morale, fear, shock,
  	  sanity and determination.
        </description>


        <term>Magic</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Pools<subentry>see Magic</subentry></indexentry>
          <p>
            Casting magic uses a dice pool and many special rules described in
            Section<ref>ch:magic</ref> on page<pageref>ch:magic</pageref>.
          </p>

  	  <p>
  	    Not all characters are able to cast spells, but all characters have a magic pool.
  	    This pool represents their animus, their spark of life, and can be use to resist
  	    spells.
  	  </p>
        </description>
	
        <term>Luck</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Pools<subentry>see Luck</subentry></indexentry>
          <p>
            <indexentry>Luck Pool</indexentry>
            Characters have a Luck Pool that represents the players
  	    manifest destiny, their luck.
          </p>
        </description>
      </descriptions>

      <figure position="!b">
        <img id="rackham_slum" scale="0.35"/>
      </figure>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Hit Points</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        A characters physical well-being is represented by two sets of
        statistics: Stamina and Health, collectively called their <defn>Hit Points</defn>.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        <term>Stamina</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Stamina<subentry>see Hit Points</subentry></indexentry>
          <p>
            <indexentry>Stamina</indexentry>
            is the characters freshness, their energy, their vigour, and their ability to
	    shrug off minor wounds, bruising, scratches, glancing blows,
	    near misses and the like.  Damage to stamina leaves the character breathless,
	    a little stunned, bruised and battered but not physically too badly hurt.
	    As the character's Stamina decreases their ability to fend off serious damage
	    from attackers decreases and the danger of getting really physically hurt
	    increases.  Stamina heals quickly.
          </p>
        </description>

        <term>Health</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Healing<subentry>Health</subentry></indexentry>
          <p>
            represents the characters brawn, their physical capacity to take damage.
	    Damage to health reprensts open lacerations, deep bruising, sprained joints.
	    Wounds that take time to heal, so it takes time to restore health. The character
	    gains Health back slowly, at their Rest Rate when they Sleep.
          </p>
        </description>
      </descriptions>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Health</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Zero Health</indexentry>
        Characters can take damage to either of these stats as the result of an in-game event.
	For example, when a character takes damage during combat they will usually take it from
	their Stamina first and	then their Health. Other damage, such as falling damage, applies
	directly to Health irrespective of the current Stamina.
      </p>

      <playexample>
        <p>
          Dourli, our amiable dwarven friend has somehow managed to find himself
          in a brawl with some of the towns thugs.  He stabs one of the thugs 
          for 4 damage.  The thug has only 3 Stamina remaining so his Stamina
          is reduced to 0, his Health is reduced by 1. The thug is bloodied and has to make
  	  a morale check. He rolls poorly and flees the fight.
        </p>
      </playexample>
      
      <p>
	Both of Stamina and Health have a minimum value of zero, they cannot be
	negative numbers.  A character with zero Stamina gains the <defn>Bloodied</defn> condition.
	A character with zero Health is <defn>Down</defn>, see page<pageref>sec:conditions</pageref>
	for more information on conditions.  Characters who are down are effectively
  	too hurt and too weak to defend themselves or do too much and are in danger of dying,
  	see Section<ref>sec:death</ref> on page<pageref>sec:death</pageref> of the GMG.	See
  	Section<ref>sec:healing</ref> on page<pageref>sec:healing</pageref> for information
  	on Healing.
      </p>      
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Other Abilities</sectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Abilities</indexentry>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Abilities</indexentry>
        In addition to primary and defensive abilities, each character has a range of other
	<defn>Abilities</defn> represent learned skills which allow them to perform actions within
	the game.
      </p>

      <p>
        A character's initial abilities are determined by their archetype.  The characters
  	archetype assigns a number of abilities for the player to choose from.  Abilities are
  	discussed further in Chapter<ref>ch:abilities</ref> on page<pageref>ch:abilities</pageref>.
  	Characters gain abilities when they gain levels.	
      </p>

      <p>
	Abilities are divided using tags into a number of categorizes. For example, the Axe Strike
	ability	is tagged Weapon, Heavy, Martial, Axe.  This means that if the character gains a
	martial ability	when they go up a level they may take the Axe Strike ability or any of the
  	other martial abilities of the given rank.  If the character gains an axe ability
  	they may only choose from the abilities tagged with <emph>axe</emph>.  In order to take
	an ability the abilities prerequisites must be met.
      </p>

      <p>
	<indexentry>Ability Rank</indexentry>
	<indexentry>Rank - Ability</indexentry>
	Abilities have ranks and the higher the ability rank the easier it is for the character
	to succeed at those ability checks.  Ability ranks are written after
	the ability.  So, for example, we might say that Dourli has Axe Cleave 3, which means
	that he has Axe Cleave at rank 3.  
      </p>

      <p>
	<indexentry>Ability[Templates]</indexentry>
	<indexentry>Template - Ability</indexentry>
	Some abilities may be templated.  In this case the template will follow the ability name
	and be written in square brackets, <eg/> History[Westreich] 2.  The template indicates that
	the knowledge is narrower than the ability name alone suggests.  The GM can choose whatever
	template values they like for templated abilities.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Aspects</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        Aspects are descriptions about a characters personality, their philosophy or
	their relationships.  Aspects tie those descriptions to game mechanics and allow checks
        to be made against them.  Aspects are defined in detail in chapter
        Chapter<ref>ch:aspects</ref> on page<pageref>ch:aspects</pageref>.  We describe the
        process by which aspects are assigned to new characters in
        Section<ref>ch:character-creation</ref> on character creation.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Background</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        Players may create a background or back-story for their character.  At least
        some of the players background should be fleshed out at character creation time.  The
        background helps to tie characters to one another and to give them a purpose and a
        feeling for how they fit in the world.  This is best done collaboratively with the
	GM and possibly	with the other players as well.
      </p>

      <figure position="h">
  	<img id="rackham_wolves" scale="0.24"/>
      </figure>

      <figure fullwidth="true" position="!">
  	<img id="sintel_ishtar" scale="1.6"/>
      </figure>
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Leveling Up<label>sec:leveling_up</label></sectiontitle>
      <p>
	At some point in the game the GM will notify the characters that they have leveled up.
	The archetype document has a table at the back of the changes availble to the character
	for their new level.
      </p>

      <p>
	Changes are of the following types.
        <descriptions>
          <term>New Level</term><description>The player should modify the level for their character on the character sheet.</description>
          <term>Increased Stamina or Health</term><description>The player increases the amount of the relevant hit points on their character sheet.</description>
          <term>Gain Ability</term><description><indexentry>Ability<subentry>Gaining</subentry></indexentry><indexentry>Gaining an Ability</indexentry>
	  The character may gain a completely new ability.  The character must be able to learn the ability, and the character must have mastered any prerequisites.</description>
          <term>Ability Promotion</term><description><indexentry>Ability<subentry>Promotions</subentry></indexentry><indexentry>Promoting an Ability</indexentry>An ability promotion allows the character to increase the rank of an already mastered ability by one.</description>
        </descriptions>	
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>
    
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Checks</chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Making Checks <label>sec:checks</label></sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Check</indexentry>
        In this chapter we describe <emph>Checks</emph>, the core mechanic
  	of the game.  Checks are used to determine whether a character can do things, like
  	climbing a wall, closing a protective circle, blocking an attack against them, casting
	a spell, or jumping a horse over a fence.  In order for a players character to perform
	a challenging action they must make a <defn>Check</defn> which involves rolling some
	dice, possibly adding a modifier and determining whether the total of the roll and
	modifier is greater than or equal to some difficulty, if so the check succeeds,
	otherwise it fails.
      </p>
      
      <p>
        There are two main varieties of check: <emph>Standard 2d12 Checks</emph>, and
  	<emph>d6 Dice Pool Checks</emph>.  These two checks use a different set of dice
	and have different rules.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Standard Checks</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Standard Check</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Standard</subentry></indexentry>
        Standard Checks are the simplest and most common check.
        In order to make a <defn>Standard Check (Std Check)</defn> the player
        rolls 2d12, adds any relevant bonus for proficiency in the skill being used to the
  	result.  The check succeeds if the total dice result rolled is greater than or equal
  	to the task's difficulty.  The GM determines the <defn>Difficulty (DC)</defn> and any
	modifiers.  The modifiers may be different for different characters.	
        <equation>
          <line>Std Check:</line>
          <line>2d12 + Bonus <geqqsymbol/> DC - Modifiers</line>
          <line>... the Bonus is usually the Ability Rank</line>
        </equation>	
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Modifier</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Bonus</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Modifiers</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Bonus</subentry></indexentry>
	The value on the left in the equation above is calculated by the player making the check,
	the value on the right is calculated by the GM.  Note that <emph>the modifier is subtracted from
	the DC</emph>. That means that modifiers for the players that are good are always positive, modifiers
	that are bad for the players are negative.  This distinction becomes important for dice pool checks
	which have an overcharge value.
      </p>

      <p>	
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>DDC</subentry></indexentry>
	The DC for the check is determined by GM fiat based on their interpretation of the difficulty
	of the task, the current environment and any other factors that might apply.  Some abilities
	have a <defn>Default Difficulty</defn>, or <defn>DDC</defn> this number represents a
	<emph>non-binding suggestion to the GM</emph> for a DC for a <emph>typical</emph> check for
	this ability.
      </p>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Doubles Are Special</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Boon</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Bane</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Standard Check<subentry>Boon</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Standard Check<subentry>Bane</subentry></indexentry>
	  When rolling Std Checks there are a few special results.
          Doubles rolled on Std Checks trigger unusual effects.
  	  Double odds are bad and trigger a <defn>Bane</defn>, double evens are
  	  good, granting a <defn>Boon</defn> to the character.
        </p>

  	<descriptions>
          <term>Double 1s</term>
          <description>
            <p>
              Is a <defn>Critical Failure</defn><indexentry>Critical Failure</indexentry>.
	      It always automatically fails.  In addition the character receives a
	      significant bane.
            </p>
          </description>
	  
          <term>Other Double Odds</term>
          <description>
            <p>
              If the player rolls any other odd double result then their character
              receives a bane.
            </p>
          </description>
	  
          <term>Double 12s</term>
          <description>
            <p>
              Is a <defn>Critical Success</defn><indexentry>Critical Success</indexentry>
              which is always an automatic success.  In addition the character
              receives a significant boon.
            </p>
          </description>
	  
          <term>Other Double Evens</term>
          <description>
            <p>
              If the player rolls any other even double result then their
              character receives a boon.
            </p>
          </description>
  	</descriptions>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Boons and Banes</subsectiontitle>
	
        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Boons</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
	    <indexentry>Boon</indexentry>
            Whether the check succeeds or not, through skill or luck, the character
            has gained some advantage.  When the character gains a boon
            the GM may describe the boon or may allow the player to call the result,
            describing the result of the check to the rest of the table.  The player is
            allowed to add some minor advantageous secondary effect to the result.  For
            example, the opponent could be pushed back, drop the scroll they are carrying, or
            be forced to make a morale check.  As always the GM is the final arbiter of
            whether a players call is reasonable and he may temper the results of the
  	    success, as he chooses.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Banes</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
	    <indexentry>Bane</indexentry>
            Something has gone wrong.  The GM should describe some additional bad
            outcome for the check, or roll on one of the failure tables for inspiration.
            For example, the character may have struck with the flat of the blade
            (requiring the weapon to make a save), they may have lost their footing,
            left themselves open to attack or dropped some item they were carrying.
            In other words, some adverse affect applies.  The GM should decide
            on an appropriate bane for the character, or roll on
            one of the blunder tables for inspiration.
          </p>

          <playexample>
            <p>
  	      Dourli has to make a quick getaway from a burning stable surrounded by
  	      a crossbow wielding gang.  The one horse inside the stable is panicking
  	      because of the fire.
            </p>
	    
            <p>
  	      Dourli attempts to mount the horse and ride to freedom.  Dourli doesn't
  	      have Horsemanship or Animal Husbandry but he does have a fairly good 
  	      Strength.  So Dourli attempts to control the horse using a Strength Ability
  	      Check.  The GM decides that the task has a difficulty of 14, so Dourli must
  	      roll a 14 or more in order to get the horse under control.  Dourli has a
  	      Strength 2, <ie/>he has the Strength ability at rank 2, and so he gets a
	      bonus to his role of +2.  Dourli rolls a pair of
  	      fives on his 2d12, for a total of 10 and adds his Strength Rank of 2 to get 12
	      which isn't enough to make the 14 required to control the horse.   In addition,
	      because he rolled double odds he suffers a bane.  The GM declares that the
	      horse bolts, smashing through the burning stable doors and running into the night.
            </p>
          </playexample>
  	</subsubsection>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <sectiontitle>Advanage and Disadvantage</sectiontitle>
  	<p>
	  <indexentry>Advantage</indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Disadvantage</indexentry>
	  <emph>When making a standard check with advantage the player rolls three d12s and chooses
	  the highet two results.  When making a standard check with disadvantage the player
	  rolls three dice and chooses the lowest two.</emph>
  	</p>
      </subsection>
      

      <subsection>
        <sectiontitle>Dichotomy of Std Checks, Difficulty vs Bonuses</sectiontitle>
  	<p>
  	  We can easily convert back and forth between a Std Check DC and a Std Check Bonus.
  	  The average value of 2d12 is 13.  To convert from a DC to a Std Check Bonus we
  	  subtract the DC from 13.  To convert back from a Std Check Bonus to a DC just add 13.
  	  Alternatively, use the
  	  Table<ref>table:phb-std-check-dc-to-bonus</ref> on
  	  page<pageref>table:phb-std-check-dc-to-bonus</pageref>.	  In this way the GM can quickly
	  change who rolls the die for a check.  This may be handy when characters are performing
	  opposed rolls against other player characters.  Or if the GM wants to roll against a 
	  characters ability as a DC instead of having the character roll aginst the DC they provide.
	  It is the GM's prerogative who rolls for a check.
  	</p>

        {% include "docs/tables/std_check_dc_to_bonus.xml" %}
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <sectiontitle>Some Exceptions</sectiontitle>
  	<p>
	  Abilities tagged <defn>Untrained</defn> or <defn>Primary</defn> can be used without training.
	  In these cases the lowest ability rank is used.  Abilities tagged <defn>Inaccurate</defn>
	  do not add their rank to their checks.
  	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Dice Pool Check<label>sec:dice-pool</label></sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Dice Pool Check</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Dice Pool</subentry></indexentry>
        Dice pools represent some finite resource that will run out if overused,
        <eg/> for player characters these are Magic, Mettle and Luck, but monsters, magic items,
	and other things can have dice pools as well.  When the player has to make a dice pool check
        they <emph>choose one or more d6s</emph> from their dice pool and
        roll them to try and get a result greater than or equal to a given difficulty or DC.
  	Some dice pool checks will also have an overcharge value (usually relative to the DC,
  	<eg/> DC+6).  If the result is greater than or equal to the over charge then the check succeeds
	however a bane occurs.
        <equation>
          <line>Dice Pool Check:</line>
          <line>DC - Modifiers <leqqsymbol/> Dice Result <ltsymbol/> Over-Charge</line>
        </equation>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        <indexentry>Dice Pool Check<subentry>Exhaustion</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Dice Pool Exhaustion</subentry></indexentry>
        Doubles have no special effect in Dice Pool Checks.  However, when a dice rolls low,
  	that dice is said to be <defn>Exhausted</defn>.  For most dice pool checks, and unless
	otherwise stated, dice in a dice pool are exhausted when they roll a two or less.
	Though exhaustion for magic dice pools is more complicated, and magic dice may be
	exhausted at even higher values depending on the context of the casting, see the
	rules of magic for more information.
      </p>
      
      <p>
  	The PC dice pools: <emph>Magic, Mettle and Luck dice are restored to the pool by resting</emph>
	or through the use of special abilities.  For other dice pools, <eg/> some magic item
	magic pools, exhausted dice can never be replaced, others dice pools will have their own
	replacement schedule. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
	The number of dice in a characters dice pools are defined by their archetype, level
	and abilities. 	For character dice pools like Luck, Magic and Mettle the dice pools
	will have a rest rate which allows the player to return dice to his dice pool over time or
  	when certain events occur.  For magical items and other dice pool checks the loss
  	might be permanent.  Exhaustion only applies to Dice Pool Checks, not Std Checks.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Dice Pool Check<subentry>Shared Dice Pools</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Shared Dice Pool</indexentry>
  	Some checks will allow the use of a <emph>Shared Pool of Dice</emph>.  In this case the dice to be
  	used are selected from all the pools before the check.  Then all the selected dice are
  	rolled simultaneously but are kept separate.   The check succeeds or fails based on
  	the sum of all the dice rolled. Dice are exhausted from the pool from whence the die came.
  	Characters do not decide which pools to exhaust dice from.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Dice Pool Check<subentry>Empty</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Empty Dice Pool</indexentry>
  	When a dice pool is empty, <ie/> it has had all its dice exhausted, any further
  	checks made against that pool automatically fail.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Dice Pool Check<subentry>Modifiers</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Modifier to a Dice Pool Check</indexentry>
  	Like a Std Check, a Dice Pool Check can have modifiers.  These modifiers effect the DC for
  	the check and are suggestions for the GM.  For example a +1 DC modifier <emph>reduces</emph> a
  	dice pools checks difficulty by one, making the check easier, but does not effect the
  	checks overcharge.  A -1 DC modifier makes the check harder and does not effect the checks
  	overcharge.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Types of Check</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        There are many different types of Check.  When choosing which one to use
        the rule of thumb is <emph>use the check most specific ability to the task at hand.
	The less relevant an ability is to a task the harder the DC should be to perform
	that task</emph>.
      </p>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Ability Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  Ability Checks are any checks against an ability.  For example attack rolls are a
	  type of ability check using an appropriate weapon abiliy, as are spell casting checks
	  using the appropriate magic ability.  For these checks the dice used, the modifier
	  and a suggested default difficulty are provided in the ability description.  
          <indexentry>To Hit Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>To Hit</subentry></indexentry>
        </p>

        {% include "docs/tables/std_check_difficulties.xml" %}	

        <playexample>
          <p>
  	    Dourli attempts to strike a thug with his axe using the Axe Strike ability
  	    which he has at Rank 1.  He rolls 2d12+1 and the difficulty is the thugs
  	    defence DC.  The +1 bonus is provided by his rank with the Axe Strike ability.
          </p>
        </playexample>
      </subsection>


      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Primary Ability Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Ability</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Ability Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Primary Ability Check</indexentry>
          Primary Ability Checks are a special type of ability check, that are  made using one of
	  the characters primary abilities, when no more specific check applies, <eg/> a character
	  might check their agility when trying to catch a falling object as there is no catch ability.
	  To check whether a character can  make it to shore from a sinking ship should be made using
	  the swim ability and not the endurance primary ability.
        </p>

        <p>
	  These checks work the same as other ability checks, the character rolls a Std Check
  	  which is modified by the characters Primary Ability Rank and the result is compared
	  against a DC  chosen by the GM as they see fit.  For inspiration
  	  see Table<ref>table:std-check-difficulties</ref> on
          page<pageref>table:std-check-difficulties</pageref> for a list of
          suggested difficulties.
        </p>
	

        <playexample>
          <p>
  	    Dourli tries to shift a large wine barrel that is sitting on a trap door
  	    in a cellar.  The GM declares that in order to do so Dourli must make a Strength
  	    Check with a difficulty of 12.  The player rolls a 4 and a 5 on their 2d12.
  	    Dourli has Strength 2, and so gets a bonus of +2 for a total of 11.  Dourli
  	    fails to move the wine barrel.  If he had a Strength 3 he would have succeeded.
          </p>
        </playexample>

        {% include "docs/tables/ability_modifiers.xml" %}

  	<figure position="!b">
          <img id="rackham_giant_frogs" scale="0.38"/>
  	</figure>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Aspect Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Aspect checks are standard checks against an aspects difficulty.
          They are discussed further in Chapter<ref>ch:aspects</ref> on
          page<pageref>ch:aspects</pageref>.
        </p>
      </subsection>



      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Hidden or Passive Ability Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Passive</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Hidden</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Passive Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Hidden Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Passive Perception Check</indexentry>
  	  When players should not know that a check is being made the GM can
  	  secretly make those checks for them, and the player is a passive participant.
	  We call this a passive check.  A good example of this is a passive perception
	  check.  In order to make a passive perception check, the GM rolls a Std Check
	  and adds the characters perception rank for the character and compares it with
	  the nominated DC.
        </p>
      </subsection>



      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Opposed Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Check<subentry>Opposed</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Opposed Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Ties<subentry>Opposed Check</subentry></indexentry>
          In an <defn>Opposed Check</defn> instead of checking against a DC the player
	  character checks against their opponents check result for the same ability.
	  In the case of ties between players the result is a success with a bane.  
          <equation>
  	    <line>Opposed Ability Check</line>
  	    <line>
  	      Std2d12 + Mod. &gt; Std2d12 + Opponents Mod.
  	    </line>
          </equation>
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
  	    Dourli wants to convince the Mage Guilds Presidium that Mophissius's
  	    Maester has been involved in nefarious dealings.  Mophissius's wants to
  	    stop him.  Dourli tries to negotiate with the Presidium to convince them.
  	    In this context Negotiate is an Opposed Ability Check.  The players role-play
  	    the presentation of their characters arguments and evidence and the GM then,
  	    optionally, awards bonuses to the check based on the characters role-playing.
  	    Finally, both Dourli and Mophissius roll and add their negotiate bonus and
  	    any additional contextual bonus the GM awarded.  Whoevers modified roll is
  	    higher wins.  Ties draw.
          </p>
        </playexample>

        <p>
          When making an opposed ability check against an NPC the GM can state
          a difficulty for the player to beat, converting the opposed ability check
          into a normal ability check.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Hidden Opposed Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <indexentry>Check<subentry>Opposed, Hidden</subentry></indexentry>
        <indexentry>Hidden Opposed Check</indexentry>
	
        <p>
  	  A Hidden Opposed Check is an Opposed Ability Check where the
  	  GM makes the opposing check in secret.   This means that the players can
  	  have some idea about how likely they are to have succeeded after the check
  	  but will not be certain of their success or failure.
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
  	    Consider the intrepid Dourli playing cards in an ale house.  He is trying to
	    spread a rumour that an opposing gang of thieves is responsible for his latest
	    heist.  The GM could choose to play this as a hidden opposed Deceive check or
	    just a straight check against a stated DC.  The former means that Dourli cannot
	    be sure of his result, unless he rolls a critical, while the latter is a little
	    simpler and faster.
          </p>
        </playexample>	
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Morale Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Morale Check</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Break Check<subentry>Morale Check</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Morale</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Break see Morale Check</subentry></indexentry>
          Morale Checks occur when characters have to face their fears.  This
  	  process is described further in Section<ref>sec:mettle-checks</ref> on
  	  page<pageref>sec:mettle-checks</pageref>.
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Encumbrance Checks (Optional)</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Encumbrance</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Encumbrance Check</indexentry>
          Encumbrance is an optional rule.  When the characters are doing something
          where the weight of their pack could be problematic then the GM can make the
          player roll against encumbrance.  This check is discussed further in
          Section<ref>sec:encumbrance</ref> on page<pageref>sec:encumbrance</pageref>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Generic Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Generic checks are a catch-all check for when nothing else applies.  The player
          rolls a Std Check against a difficulty chosen by the GM.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Other Check Details</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Rounding</subsectiontitle>
  	<p>
          <indexentry>Rounding</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Check<subentry>Rounding</subentry></indexentry>
  	  Some rules require numeric values to be halved, quartered and so on. For example
  	  a bane on a combat roll halves the damage done, and falling damage can do a
  	  quarter of your hit points damage.  What do we do decide what half of an
  	  odd number is?  The rule is: Always round down.  So half of 7 is 3, and a quarter
  	  of 7 is 1.
  	</p>
      </subsection>

      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Rerolls</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Rerolls</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Rerolls</indexentry>
  	  The most important rule for rerolls is that no check can be rerolled more than
  	  once for any reason.  Secondly, a reroll is just that.  The Character cannot choose
  	  to perform a different action, they are already committed to performing the original
  	  action, they are just able to reroll the check.  If the player rerolls the check they
  	  must take the result from the second roll. When making a reroll the player must reroll
  	  the same number of dice they used in the original check - they cannot choose to add or
  	  remove dice from the check.  All checks may be rerolled unless the ability states
  	  otherwise. When a dice pool check is rerolled, exhausted dice are lost from the reroll
  	  but not from the original roll.
        </p>	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>How often can you Check?</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Check Once</subentry></indexentry>
          In the usual course of play each character can perform a check once - twice if a
  	  reroll is used.  For example,  Dourli might try opening a box quickly by picking
  	  locks.  If Dourli fails he might check to open the box with his axe but he can't
  	  try picking the lock again.  The GM may consider that Dourli has used all the time
  	  available in his attempt to pick the lock and so no other characters may attempt
  	  to do so, or that there is further time available and someone else can try and
  	  pick the lock.
        </p>

  	<p>
  	  The GM should use their commonsense to determine what constitutes a new check,
  	  an attempt to quickly open a lock is one check.  However Dourli may be able to
  	  make multiple checks to see if he can shoot a lever on the other side of a room
  	  as each shot is it's own new and unique check.
  	</p>
	
        <p>
          <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Taking Time</subentry></indexentry>
          <indexentry>Taking Time</indexentry>
  	  Many tasks can be automatically completed given enough time.  For example,
  	  for a mundane lock the GM might rule that Dourli automatically unlocks the box
  	  if he spends a few hours tinkering with it.  This process is called
  	  <defn>Taking Time</defn>.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>When to Check?</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          As a GM when should you require that your players make a check?  Make sure that
          you only require players to check when: <emph>the outcome is uncertain and failure
          makes the game more interesting</emph>.  Many tasks are easy enough that they
  	  can be completed automatically.  In this case no check is required to perform the
  	  action. Harder variants of the task might require a check though.  For example,
  	  opening a door might be considered an easy task that automatically succeeds,
  	  while opening a door quietly might require a check.  Similarly breaking down a
  	  door might require a check to perform quickly but can be done automatically given
  	  enough time and given that one of the characters has an axe.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Party/Group Checks</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
  	  <indexentry>Group Checks</indexentry>
  	  <indexentry>Party Checks</indexentry>
  	  <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Group</subentry></indexentry>
  	  <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Party</subentry></indexentry>
          Sometimes checks have to be made by the party.  In this section we discuss the
  	  different party checks.
        </p>
        
        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Everyone Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
  	    <indexentry>Everyone Checks</indexentry>
  	    <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Everyone</subentry></indexentry>
  	    Sometimes everyone in a group has to make a check.  For example, if the party is
  	    attacked using poisonous gas everyone in the party has to save.  When
  	    <defn>Everyone Checks</defn>, each group member makes a separate check
  	    independent of the rest of the group and each individual suffers any
  	    repercussions separately if they fail.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>

        <subsubsection>
          <subsubsectiontitle>Delegate Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
          <p>
  	    <indexentry>Delegate Checks</indexentry>
  	    <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Delegate</subentry></indexentry>
  	    In a delegate check a player character is <emph>delegated</emph> by the GM
  	    to make a check on behalf of the whole group.  If that check fails the party
  	    fails the check. The GM may choose the delegate at random or at their own
  	    discretion. Some examples of Delegate Checks are Initiative, Stealth,
  	    Perception, Ambush and Surprise rolls.  But more on these later.
          </p>
        </subsubsection>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  


  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Tags, Conditions, and Aspects</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:aspects</label>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Tags</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Tag</indexentry> 
        A <emph>Tag</emph> is a label or signifier attached to something  in the world.
	A cellar might be <emph>dark</emph> and <emph>musty</emph>, or a monsters attack
	might be <emph>necrotic</emph> <indexentry>Damage Type</indexentry>.
        If the GM describes a cellar as being dark then we say it is tagged dark, a dwarven 
        character is tagged dwarf.  Tags form a bridge between the narrative game and the
	game rules.
      </p>

      <p>
	Various rules apply only when certain tags are in play.  Other events apply new tags
	to characters, objects and scenarios in the game.
        Characters may use tags to gain an advantage in a check.  Tags may also be prerequisites
        for using abilities, describe weapon damage types, properties that effect magic use,
        monster classes <etc/>
      </p>

      <playexample>
        <p>
          Dourli hides from a local gang of thugs in a cellar.  The GM describes the 
          cellar as dark and dank and storing old barrels.  The thugs enter the cellar 
          and look around.   Dourli invokes the dark tag of the cellar saying ``They'll 
          have trouble seeing me in the dark''.  The GM agrees and reduces the difficulty
	  of Dourli's Sneak check.
        </p>
      </playexample>
    </section>    



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Conditions <label>sec:conditions</label></sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Condition</indexentry> 
        A <defn>Condition</defn> is a tag with explicit in-game rules attached to it.
        All conditions are tags, but not all tags are conditions. What follows is a
	list of some common conditions.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
        <term>Aflame</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Aflame Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Aflame</subentry></indexentry>
	  The character is on fire.  They must attempt to put out the fire or make
	  a Morale Check each round to resist doing so.
        </description>

        <term>Alert</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Alert Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Alert</subentry></indexentry>
	  <label>condition:alert</label>
	  The character is alert for danger.  They are less likely to be surprised.
	  They gain +3 to Awareness checks.  It is difficult to stay alert for long periods
	  of time. PCs cannot claim to be alert for hours on end.  Something has to happen to
	  alert them.  For example, guards are typically not alert, infiltrators typically are alert.
	  If a group is makes a lot of noise, <eg/> due to combat, then other groups
	  nearby will become alert.
        </description>

        <term>Aware</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Aware Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Aware</subentry></indexentry>
	  See the description of Aware in the Surprise section on page<pageref>sec:aware</pageref>.
	  If a character is not Aware they are Unaware.
        </description>        
	
        <term>Blind</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Blind Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Blind</subentry></indexentry>
          The character cannot see.  Ambush, Surprise, Initiative, Attack Roles,
	  Dodge, Parry and Block receive a -6 modifier against all opponents.
        </description>

        <term>Bloodied</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Bloodied Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Bloodied</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has suffered damage to their Health.  When a character first
	  suffers health damage in a fight they must make a morale check.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Broken</term>
        <description>
          <label>condition:broken</label>
          <indexentry>Broken Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Broken</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has lost the will to fight and must withdraw from battle.
          On their turn they may attack but must move away from the enemy if they
          can.  This condition occurs after a character has failed two morale checks
          in combat.
        </description>
        
        <term>Checked</term>
        <description>
          <label>condition:checked</label>
          <indexentry>Checked Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Checked</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has lost momentum in a fight. The character must make an 
	  additional Morale Check to charge or pursue.  This condition occurs after the
	  character has failed a single morale check in combat.
        </description>
        
        <term>Dazed</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Dazed Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Dazed</subentry></indexentry>	  
	  The character receives a -3 modifer to all Checks.
	  This often occurs when the character has suffered a nasty injury and are suffering a great deal of pain
	  Endurance check DDC 12 ends the condition.
        </description>

        <term>Drunk</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Drunk Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Drunk</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has had too much alcohol to drink.  They make Agility and Perception
          checks at -3 and they make Luck checks at +3.
        </description>

        <term>Distracted</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Distracted Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Distracted</subentry></indexentry>       
          Something has caught the characters attention and they are not paying
          attention to their surrounds.  They make Ambush, Surprise,
          Perception Checks at -3.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Deaf</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Deaf Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Deaf</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character cannot hear.  They make checks Ambush, Surprise,
          Perception Checks at -3 and have some trouble communicating with others,
	  use Language saves to determine success.	  
        </description>
        
        <term>Down</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Down Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Down</subentry></indexentry>
	  The character is very badly hurt, semi-conscious and is only capable of
	  making a single minor action in their turn.  Characters who are Down
	  also have the Near-Death condition and usually have the Prone condition
	  as well.
        </description>

        <term>Enraged</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Enraged Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Enraged</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is wild with rage.  They can't flee or retreat.
	  Mettle check DDC 3 to save.
        </description>

        <term>Exhausted</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Exhausted Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Exhausted</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is very tired.  Make Strength, Endurance, Speed and Movement
          checks at -4.
        </description>

        <term>Fast</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Fast Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Fast</subentry></indexentry>       
          The NPC forces an Initiative Check when first attacked.
        </description>    
                
        <term>Fearless</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Fearless Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Fearless</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has no fear and automatically succeeds any morale checks.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Fey Resilience</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Fey Resilience Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Fey-Resilience</subentry></indexentry>       
	  The fey are resistant to damage from non-magically conductive sources.
	  Reduce physical damage from non-iron weapons by two.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Flanked</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Flanked Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Flanked</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is being attacked from multiple sides simultaneously.
	  This drastically reduces their ability to defend themselves and they
	  suffer -3 to their Armour Checks while flanked.  See 
	  Section<ref>sec:flanking</ref> on page<pageref>sec:flanking</pageref>
        </description>

        <term>Immune[]</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Immune[] Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Immune[]</subentry></indexentry>
	  The character takes no damage if they are immune to that type of damage.
	  For example, if a character is Immune[Fire] and they take 6 points of
	  damage tagged with Fire then they take no damage.
        </description>

        <term>Inaccurate</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Inaccurate Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Inaccurate</subentry></indexentry>
	  Inaccurate weapons get -3 to hit.  Very Inaccurate weapons get -6 to hit.
	  Abilities tagged <defn>Inaccurate</defn> do not add the weapons rank to their
	  check.
        </description>
	
        <term>Invisible</term>    
        <description>
          <indexentry>Invisible Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Invisible</subentry></indexentry>       
          same as if others were blinded in actions that include the character.
	  Ambush, Surprise, Initiative, Attack Roles, Dodge, Parry and Block against this
	  character all receive a -6 modifier.
        </description>

        <term>Ungainly</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Ungainly Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Ungainly</subentry></indexentry>       
          creature that has trouble turning and changing direction.
          must make a move turn in the same direction as the charge straight
	  after making the charge.      
        </description>
        
        <term>Natural Sprinters</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Natural-Sprinter Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Natural-Sprinters</subentry></indexentry>
	    While slow to get moving, the character can build up a fair
	    amount of speed in a straight line over time.   The character gains
	    +1 move <emph>distance</emph> while running.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Near-Death</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Near-Death Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Near-Death</subentry></indexentry>
	  The player must make rolls on the Near-Death table for the character
	  each round until the condition is removed of their character dies.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Prone</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Prone Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Prone</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is on the ground.  Perform physical checks at -3.
        </description>    
        
        <term>Poisoned</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Poisoned Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Poisoned</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is suffering from terrible pain in the stomach or some form of
          paralysis.  They must make a mettle check in order to perform any action.
        </description>    

        <term>Resistant[]</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Resistant[] Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Resistant[]</subentry></indexentry>
	  The character has all damage decreased by 50<percent/> of its normal damage.
	  For example, if a character is Resistant[Fire] and they take 6 points of
	  damage tagged with Fire then they would take an 3 fewer damage.  The 
	  damage is removed after any boon, bane or other modifier. 
        </description>    
	
        <term>Routed</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Routed Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Routed</subentry></indexentry>
          The character has been defeated in combat.  If they can Flee they do so.
          Otherwise they will Yield or do something desperate.  This occurs
          when the player has failed three morale checks in combat.
        </description>

        <term>Sick</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Sick Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Sick</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is feverish and light headed?  They perform a mettle
          check at the start of each turn in combat and if they fail they perform
          checks that turn at -3.
        </description>

        <term>Slowed</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Slowed Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Slowed</subentry></indexentry>       
          For some reason the character has trouble moving.  They must make
	  an Agility Check vs 10 or their move distance is reduced by 3.
        </description>

        <term>Stunned</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Stunned Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Stunned</subentry></indexentry>
	  The character is stunned and gets one action per round.  Save vs Endurance ends.
        </description>
	
        <term>Tired</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Tired Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Tired</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character is tired.  Make Strength, Endurance, Speed and Movement checks at -3.
        </description>
	
        <term>Unaware</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Unaware Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Unaware</subentry></indexentry>
	  See the description of Aware in the Surprise section on page<pageref>sec:aware</pageref>.
	  If a character is not Unaware they are Aware.
        </description>
        
        <term>Unconscious</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Unconscious Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Unconscious</subentry></indexentry>       
          The character has blacked out or been otherwise incapacitated due to a
	  stunning blow to the head or too much pain.  They are not necessarily in immediate
	  danger to their lives. They can perform no actions.
        </description>    

        <term>Very Inaccurate</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Very Inaccurate Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Very Inaccurate</subentry></indexentry>
	  Inaccurate weapons get -6 to hit.
        </description>
	
        <term>Vulnerable[]</term>
        <description>
          <indexentry>Vunerable[] Condition</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Vunerable[]</subentry></indexentry>
	  The character has all damage increased by 50<percent/> of its normal damage.
	  For example, if a character is Vulernable[Fire] and they take 6 points of
	  damage tagged with Fire then they would take an extra 3 damage.  The extra
	  damage is added after any boon, bane or other modifier. 
        </description>    
      </descriptions>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Condition<subentry>Save Ends</subentry></indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Save Ends</indexentry>
	At some point conditions may go away.  There may be a number of circumstances
	listed when the condition is applied as to when the condition ends.  One such
	way is when the character makes a save.  This is called <defn>Save Ends</defn>,
	and it will usually be stated in terms of what ability to use and supply a
	default DC.  For example text might say: If the character has a fishing net
	dropped on them	they are Prone Agility ends with a DDC of 12.  Saves are made at
	the end of the characters turn and, if they have multiple saves to make,  in any
	order the character wishes.
      </p>      
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Aspects</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        Role-playing is shared story-telling.  Conflict and struggle are central to a 
        good story.  Aspects are the mechanic that we use to represent facets of the 
        characters personality that can be used to create interesting, non-physical,
        internal or inter-personal conflict and character development within the game.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Aspect</indexentry> 
        Aspects are special tags that describe some part of a characters personality, 
        their system of beliefs, or their philosophy of life.  Each aspect has
        a difficulty and the player can be forced to make checks against that difficulty or
	be compelled to behave in accordance with the aspect.  The higher the difficulty
	the harder it is for the character to resist
        the aspect. For example Dourli might have the following aspects: <emph>Gold is my
        Lodestone 10</emph>, and <emph>My Word as a Dwarf 13</emph>.
      </p>

      <p>
        There are many types of aspects.  They fall loosely into the following categories:
      </p>
      
      <descriptions>
        <term>Personality Aspects</term>
        <description>
          <p>
	    describe some part of a characters personality or demeanour, their flaws and
	    foibles, their short-comings, their weaknesses and sometimes their strengths,
	    <eg/> Mama's Boy, As Exciting as Cold Oatmeal, Plagued by Self-Doubt.
          </p>
        </description>

        <term>Philosophy Aspects</term>
        <description>
          <p>
	    encode a character's beliefs and their moral compass: Defender of the 
	    Downtrodden, Man of the Book, Death before Dishonour.
          </p>
        </description>

        <term>Relationship Aspects</term>
        <description>
          <p>
	    Relationship aspects can be used to describe a close bond between the
	    character and an individual, a magic item, their god, a small group or even
	    a large population.  In the last case it comes in the form of fame, or
	    infamy, with aspects like The Heroes of Izenholme, Chosen of the Elvin Council,
	    Beholden to the Black Hand, or The Scourge of the Serpent People.
          </p>

          <p>
	    Discuss the role playing milieu with the GM.  Get a feel for the colour of 
	    the world and the NPCs and organizations within it.  Choose 
	    an aspect with the GM that ties your character to one of these 
	    NPCs or organizatio, or  one of the player characters.  Then choose a
	    Personality or Philosophy aspect for your character.
          </p>
        </description>        

        <term>Insanity, Curses, Diseases, and other effects</term>
        <description>
          <p>
	    other in game conditions can be represented by aspects such as insanity,
	    and various diseases.  Players need not worry themselves over these during
	    character creation.
          </p>
        </description>        
      </descriptions>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Choosing Good Aspects</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Aspects are used to drive conflict in the game.  If the character is
	  a <emph>Problem Gambler</emph> have the party visiting gambling dens so
	  the character has to suffer an internal struggle not to gamble and
	  have some thugs lean on the character to pay back his debts.
	</p>

        <p>
          Good aspects are evocative of the characters personality, their belief system 
          or their social status. They should not describe parts of the game already covered 
          by existing game mechanics.  For example, <emph>Greatest Swordsman Ever</emph> is 
          not a good aspect - it interferes with the game rules on combat.  <emph>Thinks He's
          the Greatest Swordsman Ever</emph> is much better because it establishes the 
          character as a braggadocio.  Remember that the Aspects should be chosen to create 
          conflict and problems for the characters to overcome.  If an Aspect does not 
          cause the character to overcome difficulties or make interesting decisions it
          is not a good aspect. As a general rule good aspects are phrases that when applied
	  require action from the character.  Additionally they should be neither too specific
	  nor too general.  For good example aspects see the FATE RPG or
	  Figure<ref>figure:random-aspect-table</ref> on
          page<pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}-random-aspects</pageref>.
        </p>
	{% include "docs/tables/random_aspect_table.xml" %}	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Aspect Creation</subsectiontitle>

        <p>
          <indexentry>Creating Aspects</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect Creation =9+d6</indexentry> 
	  After an aspect is chosen the starting difficulty of that aspect must be determined.
          The difficulty of an Aspect always lies in the range 10 to 15 inclusive.
          Aspects acquired during character creation have an initial difficulty of $9 + 1d6$. 
          Aspects whose difficulty falls below six are said to be <bold>diminished</bold> 
          and no longer apply to the character.  The aspect must be removed from the character 
          sheet or demoted to a tag.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Compelling and Resisting Aspects</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          <indexentry>Compelling an Aspect</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Compel</subentry></indexentry> 
          Any player, including the GM, may attempt to <defn>Compel</defn> any characters
	  aspect at any time, this includes a players own PC.  Compelling aspects involves
	  suggesting to a player that their character should follow a course of action in
	  keeping with one of their aspects.  The player who controls the character may
	  then choose to <bold>accept</bold> or <bold>resist</bold> the compel.  
        </p>

        <p>
          If the player <emph>accepts a compel</emph> for an aspect then they should have 
          their character behave in accordance with that aspect.
        </p>
        
        <p>
          <indexentry>Resisting an Aspect</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Resist</subentry></indexentry> 
          Alternatively, players may have their characters try to <emph>resist the 
          compel</emph> as follows:
	  <olist>
	    <li>Roll an unmodified 2d12 if the result is less than the aspects difficulty the character is compelled.</li>
	    <li>If the check fails, increase the aspects difficulty by one.</li>
	    <li>If the check succeeds, decrease the aspects difficulty by one.</li>
	    <li>If a bane is rolled, increase the aspects difficulty by one.</li>
	    <li>If a boon is rolled, decrease the aspects difficulty by one.</li>
	    <li>If the player compelled themselves then decrease the aspects difficulty by one.</li>
	    <li>If the aspects difficulty is less than ten, then it becomes ten.</li>
	    <li>If the aspects difficulty is greater than fifteen, then it becomes fifteen.</li>
	  </olist>
	</p>

	<!-- <p> -->
	<!--   A <emph>Boon</emph> when making an aspect check should reduce the aspects difficulty by a -->
	<!--   further one.  A <emph>Bane</emph> increases the aspects difficulty by an extra one.  Potentially -->
	<!--   cancelling out any change to the aspect DC. -->
	<!-- </p> -->

	<!-- <p> -->
	<!--   <emph>If the aspect was compelled by the player themselves they receive a -3 modifier to -->
	<!--   their check.</emph>  This is important, as it encourages players to compel their own aspects -->
	<!--   to manage their aspect DCs. -->
        <!-- </p>	 -->

	  <!-- They may perform a standard check against that Aspects difficulty.   -->
          <!-- If they fail the check, their character must perform an action that is congruous  -->
          <!-- with the aspect in question, <emph>and</emph> decrease the difficulty of the  -->
          <!-- aspect by one. Having given in to their aspect they find temporary relief from the -->
	  <!-- compulsion.   See Figure<ref>figure:compel-aspect-table</ref>.  If they -->
	  <!-- succeed in the Aspect check they increase their aspect difficulty as the compulsion, -->
	  <!-- while temporarily overcome, grows even more. -->
	  <!-- <figure position="!t" fullwidth="true"> -->
	<!--   <img id="compelling_aspects" scale="0.75"/> -->
	<!--   <caption>Compelling Aspects</caption> -->
	<!--   <label>figure:compel-aspect-table</label> -->
	<!-- </figure> -->

        <playexample>
          <p>
	    Dourli hears that someone has offered 20gp for information 
	    about one of Dourli's colleagues.  The GM might decide to try to compel Dourli as 
	    he has an aspect <emph>Gold is my Lodestone</emph>.  The player then decides 
	    whether he will accept the compel and provide the information about his associate
	    or resist the compel somehow.
          </p>
          
          <p>
	    He decides to resist.  So he has to check against the difficulty of that aspect, which is
	    currently 11.  He rolls 
	    2d12 (as aspect checks are standard checks) and rolls a total of 8.  He fails 
	    as his dice result, 8, is lower than the aspects difficulty, 11  So now Dourli has 
	    to provide the information about his associate in order to garner his well earned 
	    gold.  In addition, because he failed the aspect check he increases 
	    the difficulty of the aspect by one, to 12.
          </p>
          
          <p>
	    Dourli now  decides that he cannot, 
	    just hand over the information about his associate, like a despicable cad, and 
	    instead resolves to try and give them bogus information.  This action satisfies 
	    the compel as, if he succeeds, he still gets his gold.
          </p>
        </playexample>

        <p>
          A player may compel their own aspect in order to try to reduce the aspects difficulty,
	  provided the GM agrees to the compel.  When a player compels one of 
          their own characters aspects they roll the check as normal.  If they fail the aspect 
          binds the character.   If they succeed the check the aspect does not apply
          and the <emph>character must now reduce the difficulty of that aspect by one</emph>. 
        </p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Aspect Difficulty and Lifetime</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Aspects need not last the lifetime of the character.  
          There are a limited number of aspects a character may have at any one time.
          Characters grow and over time the beliefs that shape them change and aspects 
          they once described them may no longer apply.  For example, a character might 
          hold certain beliefs very strongly and, overtime, the strengths of those beliefs 
          may wane.  After some period, the character may become disenchanted with their 
          former philosophy and move on.   Perhaps they grow and realize the error of their 
          ways, or maybe they continue to believe but their passion for the idea has gone.
        </p>

        <p>
          Alternatively, the GM may at any time declare that a character loses an existing 
          aspect, gains a new one, or he may reword an existing aspect.  The GM should take
          care when doing this to keep the players vision of their character intact.
          You should consider modifying the characters aspects for one of the following
          reasons:
          <list>
	    <li>Manageability: if the character has too many aspects consider removing 
	    some, preferably starting with those with the lowest difficulties.</li>
	    <li>To satisfy the narrative imperative: if adding the aspect to the 
	    character would drive the story forward in interesting ways.  This might 
	    happen as the result of some traumatic event or epiphany.</li>
	    <li>To tweak an existing Aspect: if the aspect is constantly being exploited 
	    by the player then the aspect should be changed.  Remember a good aspect 
	    has to cause problems for the character occasionally</li>
          </list>
        </p>

        <p>
          Other aspects, such as physical aspects, are usually held for the lifetime of the 
          character.  For example, suppose Dourli loses a hand in a tragic, yet potentially 
          foreseeable, drunken axe juggling attempt.  He gains the <emph>Missing Left 
          Hand</emph> aspect.   Over time this may become much less problematic for him as 
          he adapts to his new condition however he will very likely retain that aspect until 
          his death.  Alternatively, the GM can rule that aspect can be diminished and 
          if Dourli manages to get the aspects difficulty down to 5 then it no longer 
          affects him in the usual course of play.  That aspect would then become a tag
          on the character -- just because it no longer effects him in a significant way.
        </p>

	<p>
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Lifecycle</subentry></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Ephemeral</subentry></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Chronic</subentry></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Permanent</subentry></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Ephemeral Aspect</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Chronic Aspect</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Permanent Aspect</indexentry> 
	  We distinguish three different Aspect lifetimes: Ephemeral, Chronic and Permanent.
	  Ephemeral aspects last until the aspects difficulty would be reduced below the minimum
	  aspect difficulty.   Unless otherwise stated new aspects are assumed to be Ephemeral.
	  Chronic Aspects are active until their difficulty would be reduced
	  below some minimum difficulty, at which point the Aspect becomes dormant for some period
	  of time.  Dormant aspects cannot be compelled.  Dormant aspects become active again when
	  the GM decides.  Permanent Aspects last indefinitely and are always active.   The lifetime
	  and effects of all aspects regardless of life-cycle are ultimately determined by the GM,
	  but should be negotiated between players and the GM.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Aspect Advantages</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          When a player seeks to compel one of their own characters aspects they do so 
          in the hopes of weakening the hold of that aspect upon their character.
	  The idea is that it is far better for a character to decide when their
	  aspect applies to their character than leaving it up to the GM or fellow players
	  to choose a time that may be very inconvenient.
        </p>

        <playexample>
          <p>
	    Suppose Dourli is fighting an ogre, and a large amount of treasure is 
	    at stake if Dourli can win.  The ogre is nearly defeated but Dourli fails 
	    his morale check.  Dourli's player might try to compel his 
	    <emph>Gold is my Lodestone</emph> aspect to try to get the GM to give 
	    Dourli some bonus to his morale check in that fight.  He rolls a 5.
	    Well under the aspects difficulty and so is bound by the aspect.
	    The GM decides that Dourli gets a +3 bonus to his morale check as his
	    greed overcomes his sense of self-preservation.
          </p>
        </playexample>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Conflicting Aspects</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
          Sometimes a characters aspects conflict with one another.  In such cases 
          someone can compel one aspect to try and gain a bonus on a second
          aspect check, <eg/> suppose the GM tries to compel Dourli's <emph>Gold is 
          my lodestone</emph> aspect to make Dourli sell out one of his companions.
          The player may counter that Dourli has sworn friendship with the 
          companion while imbibing and that the GM's compel conflicts with his other 
          aspect <emph>My word as a dwarf</emph>.  If Dourli <emph>fails</emph> the 
          check against <emph>My word as a Dwarf</emph> then he is bound by that aspect
          and the GM should grant him a bonus in the check against 
          <emph>Gold is my lodestone</emph> as Dourli's word is worth more to him than
	  a small amount of gold (though maybe not a large amount of gold).
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Vetoing an Aspect</subsectiontitle>
        <p>
	  At the end of the day the players character is his own.  The GM and other
	  players should not force the player to make his character do something that
	  they do not want their character to do.  The player may always veto newly
	  proposed aspects for their character or suggested actions for a compelled
	  aspect.  Players should use this veto power only when they really dislike
	  the outcome of a compelled aspect.
        </p>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Combat</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:combat</label>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Combat Overview</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Combat<subentry>Rounds</subentry></indexentry>     
        Combat is central to the game and has its own specific set of rules.
        Combat starts with an optional <emph>Initiative</emph>,
	<emph>Surprise</emph>, or <emph>Ambush</emph> check, and then a series of
        <defn>Combat Rounds</defn>.  Every character gets one Turn per Combat Round.
	You can remember this with the mnemonic <emph>Take one turn every time you
	go round the table</emph>.	
      </p>      
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Initiative, Surprise, and Ambush</sectiontitle>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Initiative</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
          <indexentry>Turn Order</indexentry>
	  By default, we use Group Initiative where all the members of one group take
	  their turn, then all the members of the next
	  group take their turn, and so on until all the groups involved in the combat have
	  taken their turn.  There will typically be one group of PCs and maybe one to three
	  groups of monsters.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  The order that groups act in is dependent on context and determined by the GM.
	  In mundane combat encounters the <emph>GM can just choose</emph>.  If the
	  monsters start the fight then perhaps they should have initiative.  Otherwise
	  the GM should consider just allowing the PCs to go first.  This keeps the game
	  moving and gives the PCs agency.  Remember the PCs are supposed to represent heroic
	  individuals who are destined by fate to perform great things.  If the check is not going to
	  add interest to the game the GM should not bother with it.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Optionally, a check can be made to determine which order the groups act in.
	  The GM should force these checks when the narrative dictates, to mix-up
	  the combat a little or to punish the PCs for poor strategic decisions.
	  In this case we use one of a number of checks; Initiative, Surprise,
	  and Ambush; to determine the order in which groups act.
	</p>

	<p>
          <indexentry>Initiative Check</indexentry>
	  An <defn>Initiative Check</defn> should be made using an ability chosen by the GM,
	  and based on context.  Some abilities that could be used to make the initiative check
	  are Perception, Speed, Listen, Notice, and Scout.  We use the term <defn>Initiative Check</defn>
	  to refer to this check irrespective of what underlying ability was used to make the
	  check.  <emph>Initiative is a group delegate check using one PC's ability checks against
	  the other groups initiative DC</emph>.  Groups take their turns in order from highest
	  initiative to lowest.
	</p>
	
	<p>
          Members within groups can act in any order. The players may choose the
	  order in which they act, within their group, or just take turns
	  acting in clockwise order around the table.
	</p>	
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Surprise</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
	  <label>sec:surprise</label>
          <indexentry>Surprise</indexentry>
          It is possible for some groups within a fight to be unprepared for battle or 
          completely taken off guard.  For game purposes we say that a group of characters are
	  <defn>Surprised</defn> when they are attacked and they are unaware of their attackers
	  at the start of the combat.  If both groups or if neither of the groups are unaware
	  then no surprise occurs.
	</p>	

	<p>
	  <label>sec:aware</label>	  
	  What does it mean to be <defn>Aware</defn> for the purposes of determining surprise?
	  Ultimately, the GM makes the call as to whether one group is aware of the other or
	  not.  <emph>Typically groups will be aware of one another unless one side has
	  approached the other stealthily</emph>.  If the GM wishes, the PCs can make an 
	  <defn>Awareness Check</defn> which is a delegate group check using an appropriate
	  ability to see if they are aware of other parties, see
	  Table<ref>table:{{ doc_name }}-awareness</ref> on page<pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}-awareness</pageref>
	  for suggestions about the appropriate ability check to use.  The awareness check can
	  be modified if individuals have the Alert Condition see page<pageref>condition:alert</pageref>
	</p>
	
	<playexample>
          <p>
            Dourli, attempts to surprise two gang members in the city by attacking them from behind
	    under the cover of darkness.  Dourli is aware of his opponents already, but do the
	    gang members become aware of Dourli?  Looking at
	    Table<ref>table:{{ doc_name }}-awareness</ref> we see that the appropriate ability
	    to use is Sneak.   Dourli makes a Sneak check against his opponents perception DC.
	    If successful he will surprise the gang members, if he fails to surprise them he
	    probably should still go first in the initiative, since he is a player character
	    and he initiated the attack.
          </p>
	</playexample>
	
	<p>
	  <emph>
	    <emph>When a group is surprised it gets no actions for the first round of combat,
	    and then must make a morale check.  The attackers gain advantage on Std Checks
	    during a Surprise Roll.  Additionally, whether the surprise attempt
	    is successful or not the would be surpriser goes first during combat as if they
	    had won initiative.</emph>
	  </emph>
	</p>
	
        {% include "docs/tables/awareness.xml" %}
      </subsection>

      {% include "docs/tables/initiative.xml" %}
      
      <figure position="!b">
        <img id="rackham_sea_serpent" scale="0.37"/>
      </figure>      
      
      <subsection>
        <subsectiontitle>Ambush</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
          <indexentry>Ambush</indexentry>
	  Ambush is special case of surprise roll that occurs when the ambusher has enough
	  time to plan their initial attack well. In order for an ambush to occur the ambushee
	  must move into the ambush zone.   The ambushers otherwise may have the time to
	  set traps and snares, prepare actions, cast non-combat spells <etc/> at the GMs discretion.
	  <emph>Players receive a +6 modifier to their surprise when ambushing, and they receive a -6 modifier
	  to their surprise roll when being ambushed.   The effects of being ambushed are the same as
	  those for being surprised.</emph>
	</p>	
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Combat Rounds</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <defn>Combat rounds</defn> represent about ten seconds of time in-game.  During a
	round every member of the combat takes a single <defn>Turn</defn>.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Actions</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Standard Action</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Move Action</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Minor Action</indexentry>
	<emph>In a characters Turn the character has time to perform a Standard Action, a Move
	Action and a Minor Action</emph>.  Actions can be demoted from a Standard Action to a Move
	or Minor Action, and from a Move Action to a Minor Action.  These actions can be
	performed in any order	within a combat	round and they are all optional.   
      </p>

      <figure position="h">
	<img id="rackham_divider" scale="2.0"/>
      </figure>    
      
      <p>
        There are a few extra complications to combat: Immediate Actions,
	Reactions, Free Actions, Miscellaneous Actions, and Prepared Actions which we
	discuss later.
      </p>

      <figure position="t">
        <img id="death_comes_calling" scale="0.085"/>
      </figure>
      
      <!-- <figure position="b"> -->
      <!--   <img id="footer" scale="0.4"/> -->
      <!-- </figure> -->

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Standard Action</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Standard actions are the main combat actions that are used for most
	  physical attacks and many spells.  Examples are Sword Strike, Axe Strike
	  and Run actions.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Move Action</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  Move actions allow the character to move, <eg/> using the Move, Run, Charge or
	  Flee abilities.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  Most combat actions also implicitly include some optional movement.  When a
	  character attacks it is understood to involve a movement to close the distance to
	  their opponent.  On a grid the distance the character may move is up to the
	  characters movement.  Note that there is also a Run action that essentially just
	  allows the character to move twice their normal distance, a Charge action for
	  attacking at a run, and a Flee action.  In addition, the characters movement
	  options may be curtailed if they have failed one or more Morale Checks.
	</p>
      </subsection>
      

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Minor Action</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  A minor action is any operation that can be performed in very short period of time,
	  <eg/> grabbing an item from your belt, opening a door, picking an item up
	  <etc/>.
	</p>
      </subsection>
           
      <subsection>
      	<subsectiontitle>Free Actions</subsectiontitle>
      	<p>
      	  A <defn>Free Action</defn> is an optional extra action that the character performs
	  in his turn and that does not count against their limit of actions for their round.
      	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Immediate Actions</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  An <defn>Immediate Actions</defn> are Free Actions that the characters can perform
	  once, <emph>at any time</emph> during the round.  Examples of Immediate Actions
	  are using Leadership to try and cause a halt to combat to allow negotiation,
	  and Fleeing.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Multi-Turn Actions</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
          <indexentry>Full Turn Action</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Multi Turn Action</indexentry>
	  Some tasks require longer than a standard action to perform, typically either one
	  or more whole turns.  We call these full-turn or multi-turn actions.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  A <defn>Full Turn Action</defn> take a whole turn to complete.  That is one standard
	  action, one move action and one minor action.  These actions can be performed in any
	  order and they can be started in one turn and finished in another.  <defn>Multi Turn
	  Actions</defn> require some number of full turn actions.  For example, a Two-Turn Action
	  requires two standard actions, two move actions and two minor actions to complete.
	</p>

	<p>
          <indexentry>Collective Action</indexentry>
	  Collective actions allow multiple characters to contribute actions towards a goal.
	  In these cases all characters that contribute must have the appropriate ability.
	  The character that contributes the last required action rolls for the check.
	  Collective actions should have the <defn>collective</defn> tag.
	</p>

	<p>
          <indexentry>Interuptable Action</indexentry>
	  Long Actions may or may not be <defn>interuptable</defn>.  If an action is <emph>interuptable</emph>
	  characters can perform some part of the action, then do something else, and the return
	  to the action and continue performing the action without losing previous progress.
	  If an action is <emph>not interuptable</emph> then any interuption will cause the
	  action to fail and any progress will be lost.   Multi-turn actions should be assume
	  <emph>not</emph> to be interruptable unless otherwise stated.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Reactions</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  <indexentry>Reactions</indexentry>
	  Under certain circumstances a character will be able to perform an additional
	  <defn>Reaction</defn> during someone else's action or when a special triggering
	  event occurs.

	  Reactions are actions that the GM deems may be performed as a Reaction in a given
	  context, or any abilities specially labelled as such, <eg/> Shield Block,
	  Sword Parry, Cloak Fighting and Dodge.  A character may perform at
	  most one reaction per round.  If two or more characters want to react to an action the
	  GM decides the reaction order, possibly using an opposed Speed check.
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Miscellaneous Actions</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  <indexentry>Miscellaneous Actions</indexentry>
	  Miscellaneous actions refer to things that characters do during combat
	  for which no explicit rules exist, <eg/> reading the runes that close
	  a magic portal, releasing a portcullis, mounting a horse, quaffing a potion,
	  pushing a load of barrels over and so on.
	</p>

	<p>
	  For many miscellaneous actions the GM will just have to make a ruling as
	  to the check required and the type of action; standard, move or minor: as 
	  it would infeasible for us to provide rules for the myriad of
	  miscellaneous actions that might occur.  We suggest that the GM rule that
	  these are minor actions if they can as it encourages strategic thinking and
	  more variety during combat.  You could estimate the time required and work
	  out the actions required as follows.. whole turn is 10 seconds, a standard action
	  is six seconds, a move action is three seconds, and a minor action is one second.
	  Then, if an action will take thirty seconds to perform it will need three whole
	  rounds to complete.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Prepared Actions</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  If the character knows that a combat is imminent they may declare that they
	  prepare an action.  At that point, at the GMs discretion, the action gains
	  a +3 check modifier, <eg/> a prepared arrow shot triggered when someone enters a room
	  would gain a +3 bonus to succeed.
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Boons and Banes</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
          <indexentry>Combat<subentry>Boons</subentry></indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Combat<subentry>Banes</subentry></indexentry> 
	  Since combat is such a major part of the game the characters will be rolling
	  Boons and Banes quite often.  The standard Boon for martial abilities
	  is double damage.  The standard Bane for martial abilities is half damage.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  Some suggested boons and banes for use during combat checks
	  can be found in Tables <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}-to-hit-boons-and-banes</ref>
	  and <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}-to-hit-boons_and_banes</ref>.
	</p>
	{% include "docs/tables/attack_boons_and_banes.xml" %}
	{% include "docs/tables/defence_boons_and_banes.xml" %}
      </subsection>
      
      
      <playexample>
	<p>
	  The thugs have returned to the cellars.  Dourli and Roslyn have been unable to 
	  escape and now a fight looks inevitable.  It's still dark and our heroes have 
	  managed to hide from the thugs so far.  Dourli attacks the thugs from his 
	  hidden position attempting to ambush them.  The GM notes that the Thugs will
	  be expecting trouble, they are Alert, and so decides the bonus to ambush the
	  thugs is reduced to +3.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Dourli tries to get advantage from the <emph>dark</emph> tag of the cellars and
	  prepares an attack.   The GM agrees and gives the adventurers a <emph>+1</emph>
	  arguing that the fact that the thugs were expecting to find Dourli down here would
	  somewhat negate that advantage. Dourli agrees.
	</p>

	<p>
	  As this is a group delegate check the GM chooses Roslyn to check her Sneak versus
	  the thugs Perception DC.  If Roslyn succeeds then the Thugs are ambushed, Roslyn
	  and Dourli win initiative and get a free round of attacks, the first attack
	  from Dourli gains a bonus to succeed as a prepared action and the thugs must
	  make a morale check.
	</p>
      </playexample>        

      <playexample>
	<p>
	  Dourli and his ally Roslyn, have been cornered by the local gang leader Fenton 
	  One-Eye and two of his thugs.  A fight in the cellar of the Inn has been 
	  underway for some number of rounds.  During the fight a few kegs of whisky 
	  have been smashed and there is a shallow pool of whisky on the ground.  
	</p>

	<p>
	  One of the thugs attacks Dourli with an Axe Strike I.  Dourli defends with a
	  Shield Block 3, since he has rank 3 so he rolls 2D12 with a +3 bonus to his
	  block, the attack has a DC of 13 + 1 for the Axe Strike rank.  He needs an
	  11 or more on his roll to succeed.  He roll double fours.  That is a failure
	  and also a boon.  The GM declares that Dourli takes half damage which for an axe
	  is 3 hit points.  That has used Dourlis one reaction for the round.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The second thug tries to stab Dourli with his dagger.  Dourli has no reactions
	  left so he has to defend with an Armour save.
	</p>
      </playexample>      
    </section>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Movement and Range</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Miniatures vs Theatre of the Mind</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  <indexentry>Movement</indexentry>
          <indexentry>Miniatures</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>Theatre of the the mind (TOTM)</indexentry> 
          <indexentry>TOTM (Theatre of the the mind)</indexentry> 	  
	  Combat may either be performed on a table with miniatures using a map with a
	  <defn>Grid</defn>, or purely narratively using the <defn>Theatre of the Mind</defn>, <aka/>
	  <defn>TOTM</defn>.
	</p>

	<p>
	  If the combat takes place on a grid then the map determines 
	  the distances for movement, spell area of effect, missile weapon range etc. 
	  On a map a run is simply a double movement, a charge is a movement + d6 extra 
	  squares then an attack if the enemy is in range.  Fleeing characters move twice 
	  their movement rate +d6 extra squares.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Movement is halved over <defn>difficult terrain</defn>. 
	  Difficult terrain includes: muddy ground, rocky ground, and generally any terrain
	  with a lot of debris, brambles etc.
	</p>        

	<p>
	  <indexentry>Range</indexentry>
	  Missile weapons and some spells are ranged actions.  Up to that range the action
	  is made without any modifiers.  If the attack occurs at a distance greater than the
	  range and less than or equal to twice the range then that attack suffers a -3
	  <defn>Long Range</defn>  modifier.  Beyond twice their range the action cannot be
	  taken effectively and will automatically fail.
	</p>

	{% include "docs/tables/combat_modifiers.xml" %}    

	<p>
	  <indexentry>Cover</indexentry>
	  Cover provides modifiers to checks for most missile weapons and for melee combat.
	  <defn>Light Cover</defn> afforded by bushes and the like 
	  gives a -3 check modifier, <defn>Hard cover</defn>, such as a half wall, 
	  provides a -6 check modifier.  
	  <defn>Full Cover</defn> makes hitting the target impossible.  The GM should feel 
	  free to choose a check modifier that fits the cover available to the characters.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Zones and Attacks of Opportunity</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  If characters or monsters move past opponents during combat they may
	  grant an attack of opportunity which is a standard action made as a reaction
	  to the movement.  Disengaging from combat and moving away from combat does
	  <emph>not</emph> grant an attack of opportunity.  Allowing characters to
	  move away from combat without granting an attack of opportunity allows
	  more strategic combat and is perhaps a little more realistic.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  When playing with TOTM the GM determines whether attacks of opportunity occur.
	  When playing on a grid we need a more precise definition.  We start with defining
	  zones.  We define a <defn>Zone</defn> as the one square perimeter around the character,
	  See Figure<ref>figure:zones</ref>.  Given this definition a character grants
	  an <defn>Attack of Opportunity</defn> every time the they move from one cell
	  in an opponents zone of control into another cell in any opponents zone of
	  control.  The attack of opportunity is granted to the opponent whose cell the
	  character moves to.  Do not forget the limit of at most one reaction per
	  character per Turn.  In Figure<ref>figure:opportunity_attack</ref>, monster A gives
	  attacks of opportunity whenever he moves along the arrows in the diagram.
	</p>	
	
	<figure position="h">
	  <img id="zones" scale="1.00"/>
	  <caption>Zone of Control</caption>
	  <label>figure:zones</label>	
	</figure>	

	<figure position="h">
	  <img id="opportunity_attacks" scale="0.9"/>
	  <caption>Attacks of Opportunity</caption>
	  <label>figure:opportunity_attacks</label>	
	</figure>	
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Flanking <label>sec:flanking</label></subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  When playing using theatre of the mind, whether or not a character is flanked
	  is determined by role-playing and GM fiat, <eg/> the GM might require the character
	  makes a check to leap over a table to get into a flanking position.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  When playing on a grid a character is said to be <defn>Flanked</defn> if he is
	  being attacked by two or more opponents from an angle of greater than 90 degrees.
	  Attacks on flanked characters gain a +3 check modifier, see
	  Figure<ref>figure:flanking</ref>
	</p>

	<figure position="!b">
	  <img id="flanking" scale="0.9"/>
	  <caption>Flanking Examples</caption>
	  <label>figure:flanking</label>	
	</figure>	
      </subsection>           
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>
	Non-Lethal Combat <label>sec:non-lethal-combat</label>
        <indexentry>Combat<subentry>Non-Lethal Combat</subentry></indexentry> 	
      </sectiontitle>
      
      <p>
	There are two categories of combat: Lethal and Non-Lethal.  In Non-Lethal 
	combat the participants are not actively trying to kill their opponents, but 
	rather trying to subdue them or drive them off.  
      </p>

      <p>
	There is no difference between Lethal and Non-Lethal combat until an opponents
	stamina reaches zero and someone becomes <defn>Bloodied</defn>.  
	At that point a decision has to be made as to whether the combat is lethal or
	non-lethal.  If the combat is non-lethal then the bloodied
	opponent has to willingly withdraw from the combat or make a morale check to
	convert the combat to a Lethal Combat.  So it is possibly for a non-lethal combat
	to become lethal at some point during the combat.  Ultimately the GM decides what
	type of combat is occurring, but as a guide combat between civilized humanoids,
	particularly in	places with established legal systems and prohibitions against
	violence, will be assumed to be non-lethal, at least initially.  Combat against
	monsters and uncivilized humanoids should be considered to be lethal be default.
      </p>

      <p>
	There is a case where, during a non-lethal combat, a character may have 
	lost most of their stamina,  and are then hit with a big hit and lose all their
	remaining health.  In such a case the normal rules for reduction of health to zero
	apply.  This will probably result in either the combat becoming lethal, or the
	opponents running away.  Weapons tagged non-lethal reduce the opponents health to
	one in this case.
      </p>

      <p>      
	Examples of typical non-lethal combat encounters include fights with the local 
	guards, bar-room brawls, fights with gangs of thugs and bandits.  There are 
	many reasons to use non-lethal combat: killing people is often a capital crime 
	in human society, there are severe social implications when an individual 
	becomes known as a killer, potentially the players might wish to interrogate 
	an opponent, and bandits might want to make money selling people into slavery.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Healing <label>sec:healing</label></sectiontitle>
      <p>
	<indexentry>Refreshes</indexentry>     
	<indexentry>Sleep<subentry>Healing</subentry></indexentry>
	<indexentry>Rest<subentry>Healing</subentry></indexentry>
	<indexentry>Healing</indexentry>
	Characters may heal by taking a long or a short rest.  A <defn>Short Rest</defn> is
	a ten minute or more length of time that the characters perform no strenuous activity.
	At the end of a short rest the characters regain all their Stamina 
	and may refresh one dice pool at their dice pool refresh rate.
      </p>

      <p>
	A <defn>Long Rest</defn> is a six hour or more length of time that the characters
	sleep.  At the end of a long rest the characters regain all their Stamina, regain
	Health at their Health Heal rate, and refresh dice into their dice pools at twice
	their dice pool refresh rate.   Previously unused short rests can be taken at the
	same time as a long rest.
      </p>
    </section>
    
    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Morale Checks <label>sec:mettle-checks</label></sectiontitle>      
      <p>
	<indexentry>Morale Checks</indexentry>
	Both player characters and monsters may, from time to time, be forced to make a 
	morale check.  In order to make life more manageable, the GM and player characters
	make morale checks differently.  The difference between the two checks is that
	the GM checks for groups of monsters while the PCs check on a per character basis.
      </p>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Player Character Morale Check</subsectiontitle>       
	<p>
	  <indexentry>Breaking</indexentry>
	  <label>sec:breaking</label>	  
	  For player characters <defn>Morale Checks</defn> are a <emph>Mettle Check</emph>
	  with a target of 5.  When a character fails a morale check another
	  <bold>two</bold> characters must make a check.  Morale checks continue until
	  there are no more fails or everyone has made a morale check.  Morale Checks do not
	  count as an action.
	  <equation>
	    <line>Break if:</line>
	    <line>Mettle Pool <ltsymbol/> DC 5</line>
	  </equation>      
	</p>

	<p>
	  As characters fail morale checks they gain conditions that limit what they can
	  do during combat, see Table<ref>table:break-difficulties</ref> on
	  page<pageref>table:break-difficulties</pageref> for a list of morale check
	  difficulties and conditions.
	</p>

	<p>
	  For example, looking at the table, the first time a character fails a morale check
	  they gain the Checked condition.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The GM should feel free to modify the break difficulty as he pleases, <ie/>
	  to reflect being attacked at night, being vastly outnumbered, the horrible
	  visage of the characters opponents, the party being in good spirits etc.
	</p>    

	{% include "docs/tables/break_table.xml" %}    

	<p>
	  Morale checks for players should be made at the GMs discretion.  But some
	  suggested times to make morale checks are:
	  <list>
	    <li>When any party member becomes bloodied,</li>
	    <li>When the party enters combat against a fear causing opponent,</li>
	    <li>Whenever the party is surprised or ambushed.</li>
	  </list>
	  Ultimately, however, it is up to the GM to decide when the players should make a 
	  morale check and the GM should feel free to force morale checks sooner or later
	  in the combat to satisfy the narrative imperative.	  
	</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Monster and NPC Morale Checks</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Monsters make Morale Checks as a group.
	  Morale checks for monsters and opposing NPCs should be made when:
	  <list>
	    <li>After a third of the monsters have died,</li>
	    <li>After two thirds of the monsters have died,</li>
	    <li>Whenever the monsters are surprised.</li>
	  </list>          
	  When monsters fail their morale checks they should attempt to break off combat,
	  yield, negotiate or flee, at the GMs discretion.
	</p>
	
      </subsection>
    </section>
    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Fighting in Groups</sectiontitle>
      <p>
	It is possible to fight in groups.  While fighting in a group the
	front row provides hard cover to the back row.  The front row must
	have at least as many people in it as the back row.  To make melee
	attacks from the back row you must be using a weapon with reach.
	It is possible for a group to have two front rows, i.e. to be fighting
	on two fronts, provided that the number of people in each front row
	is greater than or equal to the number of people in the back row.
	Furthermore, characters in the back row add a temporary bonus die to
	their morale checks.
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>


  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>The Laws of Magic<label>ch:magic</label></chaptertitle>
    {% include "docs/fragment_magic.xml" %}
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Abilities</chaptertitle>
    <label>ch:abilities</label>

    <!-- <section> -->
    <!--   <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle> -->
      <p>
  	This chapter describes abilities available to characters in the game.
  	<indexentry>Abilities</indexentry>
  	Each character has a set of <defn>Abilities</defn>.
  	Abilities may be used in a variety of ways depending on the ability in question.
  	Some abilities allow the player to perform <defn>Actions</defn> or
  	<defn>Ability Checks</defn> while others provide the player with passive advantages.
      </p>
      
      <p>
  	Abilities are tags and like other tags, they may be used by the player
  	to gain an advantage in an appropriate context.
      </p>

      <p>
  	Abilities have ranks.  Some abilities start with an untrained rank, often 0 or -3.
	Abilities that have an untraind rank can be attempted without training.  All characters
	automatically have all untrained abilities but we do not usually bother to write these
	down on the character sheet until they reach rank one.
      </p>

      <p>
  	<indexentry>Mastering an Ability</indexentry>
  	<indexentry>Ability<subentry>Mastery</subentry></indexentry>
  	Some abilities have prerequisites.  You cannot learn an ability unless you have
  	satisfied the prerequisites for that ability.  A prerequisite for all ability ranks
  	is mastery of the previous rank of the ability.  That is, in order to gain rank 2
  	of an ability, rank 1 must first be mastered.  In order to master the ability the
  	player must have successfully used the ability three times.
  	If a skill requires another ability rank as a prerequisite that ability rank must
  	also first be mastered.  Every time an unmastered ability rank is used the character
  	should mark off the success on their character sheet.
      </p>

      <p>
  	When the character goes up a level they gain promotions in certain classes of abilities
  	up to certain ranks.  For example a character might gain the following promotions:
  	Martial<leqqsymbol/>3, Hammer<leqqsymbol/>4, Transport or Craft<leqqsymbol/>6.  What
  	this means is that the character can raise the rank of any one ability from the Martial
  	section up to a maximum rank of 3 provided that they have satisfied all of that
  	ability ranks prerequisites.  The only time prerequisite requirements are waivered is
  	when the text states that the character gains an ability at a given rank.
      </p>

      <p>
  	All abilities have a type.  The type of the ability is mainly used to determine when
  	and if an ability can be used during combat.  All abilities have one of the following
  	types: reaction, standard, minor, move, immediate, non-combat, tag.  We discuss ability
  	types further in the section on combat.
      </p>

      <p>
  	<indexentry>Default Difficulty</indexentry>
  	<indexentry>Passive Skill</indexentry>
  	<indexentry>DDC (Default Difficulty)</indexentry>
  	<indexentry>Skill<subentry>DDC</subentry></indexentry>
  	<indexentry>Skill<subentry>Passive</subentry></indexentry>
  	<indexentry>Skill<subentry>Default Difficulty</subentry></indexentry>
  	All abilities have a Default Difficulty, DDC.  This is a completely non-binding
  	suggestion to the GM for the difficulty that might be used for checks associated with
  	this skill.  Abilities with a DDC of 0 are passive.  This means that the the effects of
  	the ability always apply, and that their is no way to successfully make checks with
  	this ability.  It follows that there is no way to promote such abilities.  Most DDC 0
  	abilities are reserved for monsters.
      </p>
    <!-- </section> -->

    
    {% from "docs/macro_ability.xml" import build_ability with context %}

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Primary Abilities <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Primary</subentry></indexentry>
      </sectiontitle>
      {% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_primary_family() %}
      <subsection>
  	<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
  	{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

  	{% if ability_group.has_abilities() and ability_group.draw_skill_tree() %}
  	<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  	  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
  	  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
  	  <label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
  	</figure>
  	{% endif %}
	
  	{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
  	{{ build_ability(ability) }}
  	{% endfor %}
      </subsection>
      {% endfor %}
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>General Abilities</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>General</subentry></indexentry>
  	These abilities represent trade-craft and creative abilities: Smithing,
        Animal Handling, Playing Music, Hunting and so on.
      </p>

      {% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_general_family() %}
      <subsection>
  	<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
  	{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

  	{% if ability_group.has_abilities() and ability_group.draw_skill_tree() %}
  	<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  	  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
  	  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
  	  <label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
  	</figure>
  	{% endif %}
	
  	{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
  	{{ build_ability(ability) }}
  	{% endfor %}
      </subsection>
      {% endfor %}
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Lore Abilities</sectiontitle>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Lore</subentry></indexentry>
        represents the ``book-learning'' a character has received, how much knowledge
        they have accumulated.  Lore is used to purchase skills like Antiquarian,
  	Natural History, Alchemy, and the like.
      </p>

      {% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_lore_family() %}
      <subsection>
  	<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
  	{{ ability_group.get_description() }}
	
  	{% if ability_group.has_abilities() %}
  	<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  	  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
  	  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
  	  <label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
  	</figure>
  	{% endif %}
	
  	{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
  	{{ build_ability(ability) }}
  	{% endfor %}
      </subsection>
      {% endfor %}
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Martial Abilities </sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Martial</subentry></indexentry>
        represents combat related physical skills, e.g. Axe Strike, Shield Block.
      </p>


      <p>
        <indexentry>Opponents<subentry>Defence</subentry></indexentry>
  	Many martial abilities have a DC based on the Opponents Defence, this means
  	the targets Block, Parry, Armour or other defensive ability check amount or difficulty.
        <indexentry>Opponents<subentry>Attack</subentry></indexentry>  Other
  	martial abilities are checked against a DC based on the opponents attack.
  	This represents that attack skill check result or DC for the opponent.	 For
  	example a monster may attack a character with a Sword with an attack with DC 15.
  	The PC then uses the monsters attack DC as the Opponents Attack DC in any defensive
  	skill the character uses against the attack.
      </p>

      
      {% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_martial_family() %}
      
      <subsection>
  	<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
  	{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

  	{% if ability_group.has_abilities() %}
  	<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  	  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
  	  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
  	  <label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
  	</figure>
  	{% endif %}
	
  	{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
  	{{ build_ability(ability) }}
  	{% endfor %}
      </subsection>
      {% endfor %}
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Magic Abilities</sectiontitle>
      <p>
  	Magic abilities involve the use of the characters magic pool and
  	are only available to certain archetypes.
      </p>

      {% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_magic_family() %}
      <subsection>
  	<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>

  	{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

  	{% if ability_group.has_abilities() %}
  	<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  	  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
  	  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
  	  <label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
  	</figure>
  	{% endif %}

  	{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
  	{{ build_ability(ability) }}
  	{% endfor %}
      </subsection>
      {% endfor %}
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Equipment</chaptertitle>


    {% include "docs/fragment_equipment_list.xml" %}

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Encumbrance<label>sec:encumbrance</label></sectiontitle>
      
      <p>
  	<indexentry>Encumbrance</indexentry>
  	<indexentry>Check<subentry>Encumbrance</subentry></indexentry>
  	Encumbrance is an optional rule.  The characters total encumbrance is a
  	difficulty that tests may be made against.  For example, characters
  	climbing a mountain may be made to make an Endurance check against their
  	encumbrance or become exhausted.   A character leaping from one roof
  	to another who gets a bane in their check may be forced to roll
  	a speed or agility check against their encumbrance or drop some equipment
  	into the streets below.  Encumbrance does not simply represent weight,
  	it also represents the unwieldiness of the item; how awkward it is to move
  	while carrying the item.
      </p>

      <p>
  	In order to use encumbrance you should be using the standard character sheets.
  	In the equipment section of the character sheet, marked against the side, are
  	encumbrance values for each class of item (small, medium and large) and values
  	for armour and coin.  The total of these values is the characters encumbrance.
  	Note that you do not count items twice (<eg/> a shield may be a large object in
  	practice but its encumbrance is counted separately because of the encumbrance
  	values for armour)
      </p>

      <p>
  	If used, it is important that this rule does not become a long-winded exercise in
  	accounting.  First roll the check, then calculate the encumbrance (if required).
  	Secondly, don't worry about getting the value exactly right - it will take to long.
  	Just eye-ball it.
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  {% if add_index_to_core %} 
  <index/>
  {% endif %}  
</book>

