<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<book>
  <titlepage>
    <title>Malleus Deum</title>
    <img id="mj_phb_title" scale="0.12"/>
    <author>Blaize A. Rhodes</author>
    <version>{{ db.version }}</version>
  </titlepage>
  
  <tableofcontents/>
  <listoffigures/>
  <listofart/>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Introduction</chaptertitle>
    <section>    
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>
      <p>
	<emph>
	  The enemies are at the gates, brothers!  We are assailed on all sides.
	  Go, tell them in the cities that these fiends had no satisfaction while we
	  stood. They that seek to destroy us, shall rue this day, for we shall reap
	  upon them a terrible price for their presumption.  Mithras grant us strength!
	</emph>
      </p>
      
      <p>
        Malleus~Deum is a player-facing, low-fantasy, pen and paper,
	tabletop role-playing game (TTRPG) set in a grimdark, late medieval setting.
	It is distributed under the CC-By Creative Commons license.
      </p>
      <img id="mj_myrmidon" scale="0.25"/>

      <p>
        <indexentry>Player Character</indexentry>
	TTRPGs like Malleus Deum are games of collaborative story-telling. During the game, most players
	control	an individual character, hero, or avatar, called a <defn>Player Character or PC</defn>.
	Each player creates their own PC.  Each PC has a <defn>Character Sheet</defn> that describes the
	character's abilities, strengths and weaknesses.
      </p>

      <p>
        <indexentry>GM</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>NPC</indexentry> 
        <indexentry>Non-Player Character</indexentry>
        <indexentry>Character</indexentry>
        One of the players assumes the role of <defn>Game Master or GM</defn>,
        acting as the referee or narrator in the game.
	The GM controls the rest of the worlds events, and all the other characters
	within the story.  GM controlled characters and monsters are referred to as <defn>Non-Player Characters or 
        NPCs</defn>.  We use the term <defn>Character</defn> to denote both player characters,
	non-player characters.  The process of creating characters is described in Chapter <ref>ch:character-creation</ref> on
	page<pageref>ch:character-creation</pageref>
      </p>

      <p>
	Most interesting narrative decisions within the game are made
        by players rolling dice to make <defn>Checks</defn> against <defn>Abilities</defn>.
	The character sheets list the abilities available to each PC.  The process by which checks are laid out in
	Chapter <ref>ch:checks</ref> on	page<pageref>ch:checks</pageref>.  There is a list of available abilities
	in Chapter <ref>ch:abilities</ref> on page<pageref>ch:abilities</pageref>.
      </p>

      <img id="mj_dourli" scale="0.165" title="Dourli, Dwarven Fyrdzwerg"/>


      <p>
	Keywords and conditions are game concepts designed to tie informal descriptive elements of the game to
	formal rules.  For instance a room might be dark, a keyword, and a character might be blinded, both a keyword
	and a condition.  Keywords and Conditions are described further in Chapter <ref>ch:keywordsandconditions</ref>
	on page<pageref>ch:keywordsandconditions</pageref>.
      </p>
      

      <playexample>
  	<p>
  	  Throughout the rest of this book we shall illustrate game mechanics using blocks of example text
	  such as this one.  We will use two PCs in these examples: Dourli, intrepid dwarven warrior; and
	  Rozlyn, shadowy cutpurse and sometime dabbler in the dark arts.
  	</p>

	<p>
	  In order to avoid verbage, we will take Dourli to mean either the PC Dourli,
	  or the Player who is running Dourli.  It is up to the reader to distinguish which of the
	  two meanings is intended from the context.
	</p>
      </playexample>

      <p>
	The details of how this all fits together, how to create a
	character, how to make checks, and more is covered in the next few chapters.
      </p>

    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Character Creation<label>ch:character-creation</label></chaptertitle>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Character Overview</sectiontitle>
      <p>
        <indexentry>Character</indexentry>
        Each Player Character has a list of statistics that describe what that character
        can do and how well they can do it, as follows:
        <list>
          <li>An <bold>Archetype</bold> and a <bold>Level</bold>.</li>
          <li>Two Hit Point Pools:  <bold>Stamina</bold> and <bold>Health</bold>.</li>
          <li>Three other Main Point Pools:  <bold>Magic</bold>,
	  <bold>Mettle</bold>, and <bold>Luck</bold>.</li>
          <li>Six Primary Abilities: <bold>Strength</bold>, <bold>Endurance</bold>,
	  <bold>Agility</bold>, <bold>Speed</bold>, <bold>Perception</bold> and <bold>Willpower</bold>.</li>
          <li>Four or more Defensive Abilities: <bold>Armour</bold>, <bold>Dodge</bold>, <bold>Block</bold>
	  and <bold>Parry</bold>.</li>
          <li>A set of <bold>Common Abilities</bold>,</li>
          <li>A set of <bold>Specialized Abilities</bold>,</li>
          <li>A set of <bold>Aspects</bold>,</li>
	  <li>Some optional <bold>Supplementary Statistics</bold>, and</li>
          <li>An optional <bold>Backstory</bold></li>
        </list>
      </p>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Archetype</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
          <indexentry>Archetype</indexentry>
	  Each character has an archetype which describes their race, profession, and the set
	  of abilities available to them, for example a character might choose to be a Red Mage
          or a Halfling Rover.  Archetypes define which abilities a character may have
  	  or learn, and how hard it is for them to acquire that ability.
	</p>
	
	<design>
          Archetypes are indivisible because it makes them more modular and allows us to
	  balance one archetype without effecting existing archetypes.
	</design>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Level</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
          <indexentry>Level</indexentry>
          A characters level represents the characters competence and experience.  The character's
	  level usually starts at one, and increases when the GM decides that
  	  it is appropriate.  As a rule of thumb, characters should gain levels at the end
	  of a story arc or when the players have accomplished something noteworthy in the game.
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Point Pools</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Point pools represent some finite resource that the character might have to spend during
	  the game, which will run out if overused.  When any of the pools is reduced to zero special things happen.
	  Player Characters have five main <defn>Point Pools</defn>:
	  Stamina, Health, Mettle, Magic and Luck.	  
	</p>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Hit Points: Stamina and Health</subsubsectiontitle>
	  
	  <p>
            A characters physical well-being is represented by a combination of their
	    Stamina and Health point pools, collectively called their
	    <defn>Hit Points</defn><indexentry>Hit Points</indexentry>.
	  </p>
	  
	  <descriptions>
            <term>Stamina</term>
            <description>
              <indexentry>Stamina<subentry>see Hit Points</subentry></indexentry>
              <p>
		<indexentry>Stamina</indexentry>
		is the characters freshness, their energy, their vigour, and their ability to
		shrug off minor wounds, bruising, scratches, glancing blows,
		near misses and the like.  Damage to stamina leaves the character breathless,
		a little stunned, bruised and battered but not physically too badly hurt.
		As the character's Stamina decreases their ability to avoid serious damage
		from attackers decreases and the danger of getting really physically hurt
		increases.  Stamina is recovered quickly.
              </p>
            </description>

            <term>Health</term>
            <description>
              <indexentry>Healing<subentry>Health</subentry></indexentry>
              <p>
		represents the characters brawn, their physical capacity to take damage.
		Damage to health takes the form of lacerations, deep bruising, sprained joints.
		Wounds that take time to heal, so it takes time to restore health. The character
		gains Health back slowly, at their Rest Rate when they Sleep.
              </p>
            </description>
	  </descriptions>

	  <p>
            <indexentry>Health</indexentry>
            <indexentry>Zero Health</indexentry>
            Characters can take damage to either of these stats as the result of an in-game event.
	    For example, when a character takes damage during combat they will usually take it from
	    their Stamina first and then their Health. Other damage, such as falling damage, applies
	    directly to Health irrespective of the current Stamina.
	  </p>

	  <playexample>
            <p>
              Dourli, our amiable dwarven friend has somehow managed to find himself
              in a brawl with some of the towns thugs.  Dourli is stabbed by one of the thugs 
              for 4 damage.  He only has 3 Stamina remaining so his Stamina
              is reduced to 0, his Health is reduced by 1, he gains the Bloodied keyword, and has to
	      make a Mettle Check. He fails his Mettle Check and gains the Checked Condition.
            </p>
	  </playexample>

	  <figure>
            <img id="mj_gothic_city" scale="0.123"/>
	  </figure>
	  
	  <p>
	    Both Stamina and Health have a minimum value of zero, they cannot be
	    negative numbers.  A character with zero Stamina gains the <defn>Bloodied</defn> condition.
	    A character with zero Health gains the <defn>Near-Death</defn> condition,
	    see page<pageref>sec:conditions</pageref> for more information on conditions.  Characters
	    who are Near-Death are effectively too hurt and too weak to defend themselves or do too
	    much and are in danger of dying, see Section<ref>sec:death</ref> on
	    page<pageref>sec:death</pageref> of the GMG.	Hit points may be regained in a number of ways,
	    see Section<ref>sec:healing</ref> on page<pageref>sec:healing</pageref> for information
  	    on Healing.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>

	
	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Luck, Magic and Mettle</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
            The other point pools are as follows:
	  </p>	
	  
	  <descriptions>	  
            <term>Magic</term>
            <description>
              <indexentry>Pools<subentry>see Magic</subentry></indexentry>
              <p>
		Casting magic uses a points from the Magic Point Pool.
		Casting spells has many special rules, and is described in
		Section<ref>ch:magic</ref> on page<pageref>ch:magic</pageref>.
              </p>

  	      <p>
  		Not all characters are able to cast spells, but all characters have a magic pool.
  		This pool represents their animus, their spark of life, and can be use to resist
  		spells.
  	      </p>
            </description>
	    
            <term>Mettle</term>
            <description>
              <indexentry>Pools<subentry>see Mettle</subentry></indexentry>
              This pool measures the characters morale and their current confidence in their
	      situation.
            </description>
	    
            <term>Luck</term>
            <description>
              <indexentry>Pools<subentry>see Luck</subentry></indexentry>
              <p>
		<indexentry>Luck Pool</indexentry>
		Characters have a Luck Pool that represents the players manifest destiny, their fate.
              </p>
            </description>
	  </descriptions>
	</subsubsection>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Abilities</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  <indexentry>Ability Rank</indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Rank - Ability</indexentry>
	  <defn>Abilities</defn> represent the characters talent, skill, or proficiency in a particular area.
	  Each Ability has a <defn>Rank</defn>.  The higher the ability rank the easier it is for the character
	  to succeed making checks against that ability.  Ability ranks are written after
	  the ability.  So, for example, we might say that Dourli has <emph>Axe Cleave 3</emph>, which
	  means that he has Axe Cleave at rank 3.  
	</p>

	<p>
	  <indexentry>Ability Specialization</indexentry>
	  Characters can have abilities with a <defn>Specialization</defn>.  In this case the specialization will
	  follow the ability name and be written in square brackets, <eg/> <emph>History[Westreich] 2</emph>.
	  The template indicates that the knowledge is narrower than the ability name alone suggests.  The
	  GM can choose whatever template values they like for templated abilities.
	</p>
	
	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Primary Abilities</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
            All characters share a set of <defn>Primary Abilities</defn> that describe the
	    characters physical capabilities.  These provide a bonus to certain checks and may
	    be prerequisites for other abilities.   In Malleus Deum primary abilities are
	    treated like all other abilities, see Section<ref>sec:primary_abilities</ref>
	    on page<pageref>sec:primary_abilities</pageref>.
	  </p>

	  <descriptions>
            <term>Strength</term><description>physical power</description>
            <term>Endurance</term><description>toughness, fitness and physical robustness</description>
            <term>Agility</term><description>nimbleness and fine motor control</description>
            <term>Speed</term><description>swiftness and fleetness of movement</description> 
            <term>Perception</term><description>insight and ability to notice things</description>
            <term>Willpower</term><description>stubbornness, determination and tennacity</description>
	  </descriptions>

	  <figure fullwidth="true">
            <img id="mj_ogre" scale="0.082"/>
	  </figure>
	</subsubsection>


	<playexample>
          <p>
            Dourli, our amiable dwarven friend has somehow managed to find himself
            in a brawl with some of the towns thugs.  Dourli is stabbed by one of the thugs 
            for 4 damage.  He only has 3 Stamina remaining so his Stamina
            is reduced to 0, his Health is reduced by 1, he gains the Bloodied keyword, and has to
	    make a Mettle Check. He fails his Mettle Check and gains the Checked Condition.
          </p>
	</playexample>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Defensive Abilities</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Defence Check</indexentry>
	  <p>
            Defensive abilities represent how difficult a character is to hit.  When an NPC tries to
  	    hit a PC in combat the player makes a defensive ability check against the difficulty
  	    of the NPC's attack.  There are a number of defensive abilities but the three most common are
	    Armour on page<pageref>ability:armour</pageref>,
	    Dodge on page<pageref>ability:dodge</pageref>, and Block on
	    page<pageref>ability:block</pageref>.  Some weapon classes also allow the user to parry
	    blows with those weapons, <eg/> see Staff Parry on page<pageref>ability:staff.parry</pageref>,
	    and Sword Parry on page<pageref>ability:sword.parry</pageref>.  	
	    We use the term <defn>Defence Check</defn> <indexentry>Defence Check</indexentry>
            to refer to these ability checks irrespective of the underlying defensive ability the
	    player chooses to make the check.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Common Abilities</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Common Abilities</indexentry>
	  <p>
	    Common abilities are a set of abilties that are shared by all characters and used frequently.
	    These include abilities like Lore, Brawl and Swim.  Every character can attempt these abilities	
	    but some archetypes have a higher possibility of success.
	  </p>      
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Specialized Abilities</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Specialized Abilities</indexentry>
	  <p>
            All characters have the same set of Primary, Defence and Common abilities.  In addition,
	    each character has a range of <defn>Specialized Abilities</defn> which represent more uncommon or
	    esoteric skills that most other characters do not have,
	    <eg/> Mighty Blow, Alchemy, Pick Locks, and Phantasmal Leech.
	  </p>

	  <p>
            A character's initial abilities are determined by their archetype.  The characters
  	    archetype assigns a number of abilities for the player to choose from.
	    Abilities have a rank, and might also have one or more specializations.  These complications
	    are described further in Chapter<ref>ch:abilities</ref> on page<pageref>ch:abilities</pageref>.
	  </p>
	  
	  <!-- <p> -->
	  <!-- 	<indexentry>Ability[Templates]</indexentry> -->
	  <!-- 	<indexentry>Template - Ability</indexentry> -->
	  <!-- 	Some abilities may be templated.  In this case the template will follow the ability name -->
	  <!-- 	and be written in square brackets, <eg/> History[Westreich] 2.  The template indicates that -->
	  <!-- 	the knowledge is narrower than the ability name alone suggests.  The GM can choose whatever -->
	  <!-- 	template values they like for templated abilities. -->
	  <!-- </p> -->

	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Aspects</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
            Aspects are a special type of ability that describes some facet of the characters personality,
	    relationships, philosophy or oaths <eg/>: Silent Outcast, Naive Appeaser, Dipsomaniac.  Aspects tie
	    those descriptions to game mechanics and allow checks to be made against them, and so have
	    real consequences within the game.  Mechanically, Aspects are just another type of Ability,
	    and are	defined in detail in Chapter<ref>ch:aspects</ref> on page<pageref>ch:aspects</pageref>.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Character Creation</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    Creating a character in Malleus Deum should, hopefully, be relatively straightforward.
	    <bold>To create a Player Character a player</bold>:
	    <olist>
	      <li>first chooses an archetype, then</li>
	      <li>follows the detailed steps for character creation in that archetype's handbook.</li>
	    </olist>
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Backstory</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Optionally, players may create a background or backstory for their character.  At least
          some of the players background should be fleshed out at character creation time.  The
          background helps to tie characters to one another and to give them a purpose and a
          feeling for how they fit in the world.  This should be done collaboratively with the
	  GM and possibly with the other players as well to ensure compatibility with the
	  milieu and other character backgrounds.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Supplementary Statistics</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  The player might want to include any supplementary statistics: Height, Weight, Age, Hair Colour
	  and so on.
	</p>
      </subsection>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Leveling Up<label>sec:leveling_up</label></sectiontitle>
      <p>
	At some point in the game the GM will notify the characters that they have leveled up.
	The archetype document describes the changes available to the character
	for their new level.
      </p>

      <p>
	Changes are of the following types.
	<descriptions>
	  <term>New Level</term><description>The player should modify the level for their
	  character on the character sheet.</description>
	  <term>Increased Stamina or Health</term><description>The player increases the
	  amount of the relevant hit points on their character sheet.</description>
	  <term>Gain Ability</term>
	  <description>
	    <indexentry>Ability<subentry>Gaining</subentry></indexentry><indexentry>Gaining an Ability</indexentry>
	    <p>
	      The character may gain a completely new ability.  The character must be able to learn
	      the ability, and the character must have already gained any prerequisite abilities.
	      Abilities are divided using keywords into a number of categorizes. For example, the Axe Strike
	      ability is has keywords: Weapon, Heavy, Martial, Axe.  This means that if the character gains a
	      martial ability when they go up a level they may take the Axe Strike 1 ability or any of the
	      other ability with the keyword <emph>martial</emph> of the given rank, e.g. Sword Strike 1.
	      If the character gains an Axe ability they may only choose from the abilities with the
	      <emph>axe</emph> keyword.  In order to take an ability the abilities prerequisites must be met.
	    </p>
	  </description>
	  <term>Ability Promotion</term>
	  <description>
	    <p>
	      <indexentry>Ability<subentry>Promotions</subentry></indexentry>
	      <indexentry>Promoting an Ability</indexentry>
	      An <bold>Ability Promotion</bold> allows the character to increase the rank of an already
	      mastered ability by one.
	    </p>
	  </description>
	  <term>Ability Specialization</term>
	  <description>
	    <p>
	      <indexentry>Ability<subentry>Specialization</subentry>
	      </indexentry><indexentry>Gain an Ability</indexentry>
	      An ability promotion allows the character to increase the rank of an already
	      mastered ability by one.
	    </p>
	  </description>
	</descriptions>	
      </p>
    </section>
  </chapter>



  

  
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Checks<label>ch:checks</label></chaptertitle>

    <p>
      <indexentry>Check</indexentry>
      In this chapter we describe <emph>Checks</emph>, the core mechanic
      of the game. Checks are used to determine whether a character can
      perform any non-trivial and narratively interesting actions, like
      climbing a wall, closing a protective circle, blocking an attack,
      casting a spell, or jumping a horse over a fence.
    </p>
    

    <figure position="h">
      <img id="geir-king_in_yellow" scale="1.40"/>
    </figure>

    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Making Checks <label>sec:checks</label></sectiontitle>


      <p>
	<indexentry>Check</indexentry>
	
	Whenever a character tries to perform a challenging action a <defn>Check</defn>
	must be made to determine the outcome.  To perform a Check the GM determines the
	Difficulty (DC) of the check, then the player rolls dice to get a Result,
	and compares the Result to the DC.  If the Result is greater than or equal
	to the DC then the Check succeeds.
      </p>


      <p>
	Check Succeeds if:
	<img id="check_formula" scale="0.05"/>
      </p>

      <p>
	<indexentry>Modifier</indexentry>
	<indexentry>Check<subentry>Modifiers</subentry></indexentry>
	The GM calculates the <defn>Difficulty (DC)</defn> for the check by determining the
	underlying <emph>Raw DC</emph> for the check, and applying any situational <emph>Modifiers</emph>.
      </p>

      
      <p>
	<indexentry>Check<subentry>DDC</subentry></indexentry>
	Ultimately the <defn>Raw DC</defn> for the check is determined by GM fiat, their decision is based
	on their interpretation of the difficulty of the task, the current environment and any other factors that
	might apply.  In most cases, there will be a <defn>Default Difficulty</defn>, or <defn>DDC</defn>
	this number represents a <emph>non-binding, suggested Raw DC</emph> for the GM, for a
	<emph>typical</emph> check for this ability.  The GM can refer to Table<ref>table:check-dcs</ref>
	on page<pageref>table:check-dcs</pageref> when selecting a DC for a check.
      </p>

      <p>
	Situational Modifiers modify the Difficulty or the Result based on the context in which the check is made.
	For example modifiers might be caused by having oil all over the floor, being in rough terrain, or having the
	Stunned condition.  The default value for modifiers is zero.  It is frequently the case that no modifiers apply
	and so they can be ignored when determining the outcome of a check.	
	Note that <emph>modifiers are subtracted when calculating the DC but added when calculating
	the Result</emph>.  That means that modifiers for the players that are good for the characters are
	always positive, modifiers that are bad for the characters are always negative.  
	The modifiers may be different for different characters, <eg/> a character might be
	temporarily blinded and so makes combat attacks against
	an opponent with a negative modifier that does not apply to other characters attacking the same opponent. 	
      </p>
      
      <p>
	To calculate the <defn>Result</defn> the <emph>Player</emph> rolls two different coloured d12s
	and adds the dice value to the Rank of the ability being used to make the check, and
	any adds situational modifiers that might apply.  One of the d12s used must be clearly
	<emph>lighter in colour</emph> than the other.  The sum of the 2d12 is called the
	<defn>Face Value</defn>.
      </p>

      <figure>
        <img id="mj_crow" scale="0.21"/>
      </figure>            

      <playexample>
        <p>
  	  Dourli tries to hit an assassin with his axe using his Axe Strike 2 ability.
	  First the GM determines the DC for the check.  In combat Raw DCs for attack checks are
	  determined by choosing one of the opponents Defence DCs.  In this case the GM chooses the
	  assassin's Dodge Raw DC of 14.  No situational modifiers apply to either side, so the DC
	  for the check is 14.  Now Dourli rolls 2d12 and gets a Face Value of 15, he adds +2
	  for his rank in Axe Strike, to get a Result of 17.  Since the Result, 17, is greater than
	  or equal to the difficulty, 14, Dourli succeeds and hits the assassin with his axe.
	</p>
      </playexample>


      {% include "docs/tables/check_dcs.xml" %}

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Interpreting the Result</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  The outcome of a check is not a simple binary succeed or fail.  There are a number of
	  other results that may change the way the result is interpreted as follows.
	</p>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Doubles Are Boons or Banes</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Boon</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Bane</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Doubles</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Check<subentry>Boon</subentry></indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Check<subentry>Bane</subentry></indexentry>
	    When rolling Checks, <defn>Doubles</defn> are special results and may trigger unusual effects.
	    If Doubles are rolled and the check succeeds the outcome is called a <defn>Boon</defn>,
	    if Doubles are rolled and the check fails the outcome is called a <defn>Bane</defn>.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Boon</indexentry>
	    A Boon connotes some additional bonus to the character rolling.  This bonus may
	    be specified by the ability being used or by the GM.  For commonly abilities
	    used in fairly specific contexts the result of a boon may be suggested in the


	    Whether the check succeeds or not, through skill or luck, the character
	    has gained some advantage.  When the character gains a <bold>boon</bold>
	    the GM may negotiate with the player to determine the result.  For
	    example, the opponent could be pushed back, drop the scroll they are carrying, or
	    be forced to make a morale check.  As always the GM is the final arbiter of
	    whether a players call is reasonable and he may temper the results of the
	    success, as he chooses.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Bane</indexentry>
	    When the character gains a Bane, something has gone wrong.  The GM should
	    describe some additional bad outcome for the check, or roll on one of the
	    failure tables for inspiration.
	    For example, the character may have struck with the flat of the blade
	    (requiring the weapon to make a save), they may have lost their footing,
	    left themselves open to attack or dropped some item they were carrying.
	    In other words, some adverse affect applies.  The GM should decide
	    on an appropriate bane for the character, or roll on
	    one of the bane tables for inspiration.
	  </p>


	  <playexample>
	    <p>
	      Dourli has to make a quick getaway from a burning stable surrounded by
	      a crossbow wielding gang.  The one horse inside the stable is panicking
	      because of the fire.
	    </p>

	    <p>
	      Dourli attempts to mount the horse and ride to freedom.  Dourli doesn't
	      have Horsemanship or Animal Husbandry but he does have a fairly good 
	      Strength.  So Dourli attempts to control the horse using a Strength Ability
	      Check.  The GM decides that the task has a difficulty of 14, so Dourli must
	      roll a 14 or more in order to get the horse under control.  Dourli has a
	      Strength 2, <ie/>he has the Strength ability at rank 2, and so he gets a
	      bonus to his role of +2.  Dourli rolls a pair of
	      fives on his 2d12, for a total of 10 and adds his Strength Rank of 2 to get 12
	      which isn't enough to make the 14 required to control the horse.   In addition,
	      because he rolled double odds he suffers a bane.  The GM declares that the
	      horse bolts, smashing through the burning stable doors and running into the night.
	    </p>
	  </playexample>
	</subsubsection>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Noteworthy Outcomes</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Face Value</indexentry> 
	  <indexentry>Solid Outcome</indexentry> 
	  <indexentry>Righteous Outcome</indexentry> 
	  <indexentry>Exalted Outcome</indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Outcomes<subentry>Solid</subentry></indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Outcomes<subentry>Righteous</subentry></indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Outcomes<subentry>Exalted</subentry></indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Check<subentry>Noteworthy</subentry></indexentry>

	  <p>
	    When a character <emph>succeeds in a check and rolls high</emph>, that result is called
	    a <defn>Noteworthy Result</defn>.  There
	    are three types of Noteworthy Results.  A <defn>Solid Result</defn>
	    occurs when Face Value of <bold>19</bold> or more is rolled for the Check.  A
	    <defn>Righteous Result</defn> occurs when a Face Value greater than or equal to
	    <bold>21</bold> occurs, and an <defn>Exalted Result</defn> occurs when a Face
	    Value greater than or equal to <bold>23</bold> is rolled.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    These different types of results may be used to trigger secondary abilities when making checks.
	    Each ability which is triggered by these results will describe how these outcomes relate to
	    that ability.  These outcomes can only be used to trigger one ability.  If two or more abilities are
	    triggered by a roll then the player must choose one to apply.  For the purposes of
	    triggering special conditions a Righteous Result also counts as a Solid Result, and an Exalted
	    Result also counts as a Righteous and Solid Result.
	  </p>

	  <design>
	    The probability of getting these results for Ranks 1 to 3 are about 19-38<percent/>,
	    10-25<percent/> and 4-15<percent/> respectively.  Note that they'll be a higher probability
	    when you only consider successes.
	  </design>
	</subsubsection>



	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Critical Success and Failure</subsubsectiontitle>

	  <p>
	    When Double 12s are rolled they always succeed and this result is called
	    a <defn>Critical Success</defn><indexentry>Critical Success</indexentry>.
	    In addition this result is also a Boon and an Exalted Result.  It may trigger
	    additional special behaviour defined by the ability or the GM may confer some
	    additional bonus, possibly in consultation with the character.  Also the characters
	    Lucky ability triggers.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    Double 1s are a <defn>Critical Failure</defn><indexentry>Critical Failure</indexentry>
	    and  always automatically fail the check.   A Critical Failure is also a Bane.
	    In addition the character receives a significant additional negative effect from the GM.
	  </p>	  
	</subsubsection>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Blessed and Sinister Results</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Blessed Results</indexentry> 
	  <indexentry>Sinister Results</indexentry> 
	  <indexentry>Results<subentry>Blessed</subentry></indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Results<subentry>Sinister</subentry></indexentry>

	  <p>
	    An <defn>Blessed Result</defn> is one where the lighter die is strictly greater than the darker die.
	    A <defn>Sinister Result</defn> is one where the lighter die is strictly less than the darker die.
	    For example double 11s is neither a Bless'd nor a Sinister result since neither die is greater than
	    the other.  These results can be used to trigger special abilities.
	  </p>

	  <design>
	    The probably of getting either of these results is 5/12 or 42%.  Should be used with success/failure..
	    e.g. an Blessed Success, or a Sinister Failure, a Auspicious Righteous Success etc.
	  </design>
	</subsubsection>
      </subsection>



      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>When to Check?</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  As a GM when should you require that your players make a check?  Make sure that
	  you only require players to check when: <emph>the outcome is uncertain and failure
	  makes the game more interesting</emph>.  Many tasks are easy enough that they
	  can be completed automatically.  In this case no check is required to perform the
	  action. Harder variants of the task might require a check though.  For example,
	  opening a door might be considered an easy task that automatically succeeds,
	  while opening a door quietly might require a check.  Similarly breaking down a
	  door might require a check to perform quickly but can be done automatically given
	  enough time and given that one of the characters has an axe.
	</p>
      </subsection>      

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>How often can you Check?</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Check Once</subentry></indexentry>
	  In the usual course of play each character can perform a check once - twice if a
	  reroll is used.  For example,  Dourli might try opening a box quickly by picking
	  locks.  If Dourli fails he might check to open the box with his axe but he can't
	  try picking the lock again.  The GM may consider that Dourli has used all the time
	  available in his attempt to pick the lock and so no other characters may attempt
	  to do so, or that there is further time available and someone else can try and
	  pick the lock.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The GM should use their commonsense to determine what constitutes a new check,
	  an attempt to quickly open a lock is one check.  However Dourli may be able to
	  make multiple checks to see if he can shoot a lever on the other side of a room
	  as each shot is it's own new and unique check.
	</p>

	<p>
	  <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Taking Time</subentry></indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Taking Time</indexentry>
	  Many tasks can be automatically completed given enough time.  For example,
	  for a mundane lock the GM might rule that Dourli automatically unlocks the box
	  if he spends a few hours tinkering with it.  This process is called
	  <defn>Taking Time</defn>.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Who Checks?</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  <indexentry>Group Checks</indexentry>
	  <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Group</subentry></indexentry>
	  The most common form of check are Individual Checks, where the character
	  performing the action makes the check.  However, sometimes checks have to
	  be made by a group of characters.  In Malleus Deum there are two ways of doing this:
	  Everyone Checks, and Delegate Checks.
	</p>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Everyone Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Everyone Checks</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Everyone</subentry></indexentry>
	    Sometimes everyone in a group has to make a check.  For example, if the party is
	    attacked using poisonous gas everyone in the group has to make a check to save individually.
	    When <defn>Everyone Checks</defn>, each group member makes a separate check
	    independent of the rest of the group and each individual suffers any
	    repercussions separately if they fail.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Delegate Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Delegate Checks</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Delegate</subentry></indexentry>
	    In a delegate check one player character is <bold>delegated</bold> by the GM
	    to make a check on behalf of the whole group.  If that check fails then the
	    whole group fails the check. The GM may choose the delegate at random or at
	    their own discretion. Some examples of Delegate Checks are Initiative, Stealth,
	    Perception, Ambush and Surprise rolls.  But more on these later.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Passive Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Checks<subentry>Secret</subentry></indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Passive Check<subentry>see Secret Check</subentry></indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Passive Perception Check<subentry>see Secret Check</subentry></indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Perception Check, Passive<subentry>see Secret Check</subentry></indexentry>
	    Sometimes the GM wants to make a check without the players knowing whether
	    a check has been made.  A common example of this is the <defn>Passive Perception Check</defn>.
	    The only difference between Passice Checks and other sorts of Check is that the GM
	    rolls the dice for the check instead of the player, and the GM does not let the
	    players know what he is doing or the results of the check.
	  </p>

	  <playexample>
	    <p>
	      Dourli wanders into an alley looking to find an old acquaintance.   Unbeknownst
	      to Dourli there are a bunch of cutthroats have hauled the acquaintance away a few hours
	      earlier.  The GM decides to make a secret Passive Perception Check to see if Dourli
	      notices that there has been a struggle here.  The GM chooses a DC of 13 for check, by fiat.
	      Then, using Dourli's Perception 1 ability, the GM rolls two 9s and adds +1 for Dourlis
	      Perception Rank.  Since 19 is greater than the DC of 13, Dourli succeeds and notices that
	      a struggle has occurred.  However, since a Bane was rolled the GM determines that Dourli
	      cannot determine how long ago the stuggle occurred or any other useful information.
	    </p>
	  </playexample>      
	</subsubsection>    

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Player vs Player Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    When PCs want to make checks against other PCs the checks may be made using
	    any of the methods for making checks against NPCs, but there is an issue on
	    what to do with ties.  If in an opposed check both players roll the same value
	    then who succeeds?  The answer is that in this case the GM dictates the result,
	    either some <emph>draw</emph> type result occurs, or the characters can reroll.
	  </p>	
	</subsubsection>    
      </subsection>





      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>What Ability should be used to Check?</subsectiontitle>
	<p>

	  There are many different types of Check.  When choosing which ability to check there are
	  two rules of thumb:
	  <olist>
	    <li><emph>use the check most specific ability to the task at hand.
	    The less relevant an ability is to a task the harder the DC should be to perform
	    that task</emph>.  If there is one ability specifically for performing the task at hand,
	    use that ability.  For example, when swimming use the Swim ability.</li>
	    <li>When there is some overlap then the player may choose whichever ability they prefer,
	    and the GM should apply modifiers to the Check to reflect the appropriateness of the ability
	    to the current task.  For example when trying to recall information about a nobles lineage,
	    one character might make a check using History, while another might use Lore/Heraldry</li>
	  </olist>
	</p>
      </subsection>





      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Complications</subsectiontitle>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Optional Rules<daggersymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Optional Rules<daggersymbol/></indexentry>
	    <indexentry><daggersymbol/> Optional Rules</indexentry>	    
	    Optional rules are denoted by the dagger symbol <daggersymbol/>.  The GM
	    can decide whether or not they want to use these rules depending on the context,
	    or not at all.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>
	

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Rerolls</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Rerolls</subentry></indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Rerolls</indexentry>
	    Sometimes the players will get a chance to Reroll a Check.  There are a number of rules
	    about rerolling:
	    <olist>
	      <li>No check can be rerolled more than once for any reason</li>
	      <li>When rerolling all dice used to determine the initial result must be rerolled.</li>
	      <li>If the player rerolls the check they must take the result from the second roll.</li>
	      <li>Assume that all checks are able to be rerolled unless the ability states otherwise.
	      Luck based checks cannot be rerolled.</li>
	    </olist>
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Rounding</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Rounding</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Check<subentry>Rounding</subentry></indexentry>
	    Some rules require numeric values to be halved, quartered and so on. When rounding
	    the rule is <emph>always round up</emph>, <eg/>  So half of 7 is 4, and a quarter
	    of 7 is 2.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Untrained Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    Many abilities can be used even if the PC has no rank in that ability.  When using an
	    untrained ability the character uses the Untrained Rank of the ability in the check.
	    The untrained ability rank is often -3, but you need to check the ability for more
	    information.   Everyone is trained in their Primary Abilities.
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>

	
	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Hidden Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Check<subentry>Hidden</subentry></indexentry>

	  <p>
	    In a Hidden Check when the character makes a check the GM rolls for the opposing ability
	    check and keeps the result secret.  Hidden DC checks are used when the GM does not want
	    the player to have more uncertainty about the success or failure of their check.
	  </p>

	  <playexample>
	    <p>
	      Dourli searches a wooden box for traps.  The chest/trap has a Decieve 3 ability.  Dourli does
	      not have the Trapwork skill so he checks with a -3 untrained bonus.  The GM secretly rolls
	      a 4 and an 11, +3 for the Rank in Decieve, for a total of 18 for the box.  Dourli rolls two 10s,
	      with -3 for the untrained rank bonus, for a total of 17.  Dourli does not find the trap,
	      but because of the Boon rolled, the GM decides that Dourli hears a soft clicking sound
	      from within, whenever the box is turned upside down.
	    </p>
	  </playexample>
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Hidden DC Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Check<subentry>Hidden DC</subentry></indexentry>

	  <p>
	    In a Hidden DC check the GM does not tell the players what the DC of the check is.
	    Hidden DC checks are used when the GM does not want the player to have complete
	    certainty about the success of their check.  
	  </p>

	  <playexample>
	    <p>
	      Dourli attempts to tell Emrich, the head of the local thieves guild, that he has no
	      idea about a gemstone that recently went missing, the GM decides that this will be
	      hard with a DC of 16 but keeps this secret because this is a Hidden DC Check, Dourli
	      makes checks his Decieve 2 ability and rolls a 4 and a 10. Dourli does not know whether
	      he succeeded but knows his check was not too bad.  However, Emrich is the sort that
	      plays his cards close to his chest.  Had Dourli rolled a total of 3 then he could be
	      reasonably sure he failed, similarly had he rolled a 20 he could be reasonably sure he
	      succeeded.
	    </p>
	  </playexample>      
	</subsubsection>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Random DC Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <indexentry>Check<subentry>Random DC</subentry></indexentry>

	  <p>
	    In a <defn>Random DC Check</defn>, when the character makes a check the GM rolls to get
	    an opposing DC and keeps the result hidden.  Random DC checks are used when the GM wants
	    the player to have even more uncertainty about the success or failure of their check, or
	    when the GM wants to allow the players some chance of success.
	  </p>

	  <playexample>
	    <p>
	      Dourli searches a wooden box for traps.  The chest/trap has a modifier of -3.  Dourli does
	      not have the Trapwork skill so he checks with a -3 untrained bonus.  The GM rolls
	      a hidden 6 - -3, for a final DC of 9 for the box.  Dourli rolls 13,
	      with -3 for the untrained rank, for a total of 10.  Dourli finds the trap,
	      but because of the Boon rolled, the GM decides that Dourli hears a soft clicking sound
	      from within, whenever the box is turned upside down.
	    </p>
	  </playexample>      
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Player vs Player Checks  (PvP)</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    When PCs want to make checks against other PCs then both players roll
	    and calculate their final outcomes which are used as the DC for their opponent.
	    However the question arises about the result when both players have the same final
	    outcome.  In this case the Fate die acts as a tie-breaker with the higher Fate die
	    determining who succeeds.   If the Fate dies are also tied then the GM dictates
	    the result, or some <emph>draw</emph> type result occurs, or the characters can reroll.
	  </p>

	  <playexample>
	    <p>
	      Dourli wants to convince the Mage Guilds Presidium that Rozlyn's
	      Maester has been involved in nefarious dealings.  Rozlyn wants to
	      stop him.  Dourli tries to negotiate with the Presidium to convince them.
	      In this context Negotiate is an Opposed Ability Check.  The players role-play
	      the presentation of their characters arguments and evidence and the GM then,
	      optionally, awards bonuses to the check based on the characters role-playing.
	      Finally, both Dourli and Rozlyn roll and add their negotiate rank and
	      any additional contextual bonus the GM awarded.  Whoevers modified outcome is
	      higher wins.  Ties draw.
	    </p>
	  </playexample>	  
	</subsubsection>



	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Point Pool Checks</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <label>sec:point-pool</label>
	    <indexentry>Point Pool Check</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Check<subentry>Point Pool</subentry></indexentry>
	    Point pools represent some finite resource that will run out if overused,
	    <eg/> for PCs these are Stamina, Health, Magic, Mettle and Luck, but monsters, magic items,
	    and other things can have point pools as well.  
	  </p>
	  
	  <p>
	    Some abilities are interact with particular point pools.  These abilities have a
	    cost in points that the character must pay from the pool to use the ability.  <emph>The default
	    cost of an ability is 2 points.</emph> 
	    
	    Checks made with those
	    abilities may increase or reduce the point pool,
	    see Table<ref>table:point-pool-checks</ref> on
	    page<pageref>table:point-pool-checks</pageref>.  If the point pool would be reduced
	    <emph>below</emph> zero, then it the point becomes zero and a <emph>Default</emph> occurs.
	    Any checks made with a point pool of zero automatically fail.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    The number of points in a character's point pools are defined by their archetype, level
	    and abilities.   For character point pools like Luck, Magic and Mettle the point pools
	    will have a rest rate which allows the player to regain points for each point pool over
	    time when they rest or through the use of other special abilities.
	  </p>
	  
	  <p>
	    Some point pools can never have their points restored, <eg/> some magical items.  While 
	    other point pools can regain their points in a variety of different ways, specified on a
	    case by case basis.
	  </p>
	  
	  {% include "docs/tables/point_pool_checks.xml" %}
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Converting from Ranks to DCs</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    It is often useful for the GM to convert back and forth between a Check DC and a
	    Check Bonus.  In this way the GM can quickly change who rolls the die for a check,
	    and can make opposed checks between two abilities.  It is the GM's prerogative how a
	    check is made, and who rolls for a check.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    To convert from an Ability to a DC we simple add 13 to the Ability Rank, since the
	    average value of 2d12 roll is 13.  Alternatively, we can convert from a DC back to
	    an Ability Bonus we deduct 13 from the DC.   
	    
	    Table<ref>table:check-dcs</ref> on
	    page<pageref>table:check-dcs</pageref>.	  
	  </p>	
	</subsubsection>

	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Advantage and Disadvantage<daggersymbol/></subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    <indexentry>Advantage</indexentry>
	    <indexentry>Disadvantage</indexentry>
	    The GM can allow the players to make checks at Advantage or at Disadvantage, when special
	    factors apply making the check particularly easy or hard.
	    When making a check with <defn>Advantage</defn> the player rolls three d12s and chooses
	    the highest two results.  When making a check with <defn>disadvantage</defn> the player
	    rolls three dice and chooses the lowest two.
	  </p>

	  <design>
	    Advantage is equivalent to about +3 for a DC of 13, and +2 for DCs getting up towards 20.
	    The same spread applies for disadvantage, by symmetry.
	  </design>	
	</subsubsection>
      </subsection>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Generic Checks</sectiontitle>
      <p>
	Generic checks are a catch-all check, when no ability really applies to the situation.
	The player simply rolls a Check against a DC chosen by the GM, applying no Rank bonus.
      </p>      
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Ability Checks</sectiontitle>
      <p>
	Ability Checks are any checks made using an ability.  For example attack rolls are a
	type of ability check using an appropriate weapon abiliy, as are spell casting checks
	using the appropriate magic ability.  For these checks the dice used, the modifier
	and a suggested default difficulty are provided in the ability description.  
	<indexentry>To Hit Check</indexentry>
	<indexentry>Checks<subentry>To Hit</subentry></indexentry>
      </p>


      <p>
	Ability Checks are any checks made using an ability.  For example attack rolls are a
	type of ability check using an appropriate weapon ability, <eg/> Sword Strike, as are
	spell casting checks using the appropriate magical spell ability.  
      </p>


      <playexample>
	<p>
	  Dourli attempts to strike a thug with his axe using his Axe Strike 2 ability.
	  He rolls 2d12+2, where the +2 comes from his ability rank, and the difficulty
	  in this case is the thugs defence DC.  
	</p>
      </playexample>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Primary Ability Checks</sectiontitle>
      <p>
	<indexentry>Checks<subentry>Ability</subentry></indexentry>
	<indexentry>Ability Check</indexentry>
	<indexentry>Primary Ability Check</indexentry>
	Primary Ability Checks are ability checks, made using one of
	the characters primary abilities, Strength, Endurance, Agility, etc.   Primary Ability
	checks are usually used when no more specific check can be applied, <eg/> a character
	might check using their Agility when trying to catch a falling object as there is no catch ability.
	A check whether a character can  make it to shore from a sinking ship should be made using
	the Swim ability and not the endurance primary ability, since the Swim ability is more specific
	in this case.
      </p>

      <playexample>
	<p>
	  Dourli tries to shift a large wine barrel that is sitting on a trap door
	  in a cellar.  The GM declares that in order to do so Dourli must make a Strength
	  Check with a difficulty of 12.  The player rolls a 9 for their Outcome.
	  Dourli has Strength 2, and so gets a total of 11.  Dourli
	  fails to move the wine barrel.  If he had a Strength 3 he would have succeeded.
	</p>
      </playexample>

      <figure position="!b">
	<img id="rackham_giant_frogs" scale="0.38"/>
      </figure>
    </section>






    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Encumbrance Checks<daggersymbol/></sectiontitle>
      <p>
	<indexentry>Checks<subentry>Encumbrance</subentry></indexentry>
	<indexentry>Encumbrance Check</indexentry>
	Encumbrance is an optional rule.  The characters Encumbrance is a DC that
	players can be forced to check against when the characters are doing something
	where the weight of their pack could be a problem, <eg/> characters climbing a
	mountain may have to make an Endurance check against their encumbrance or
	become exhausted.  Encumbrance does not simply represent weight, it also represents
	the unwieldiness of the items being carried; how awkward it is to move while
	carrying the item.	  
      </p>

      <playexample>
	<p>
	  FIXME
	  
	  Dourli tries to walk across a rope between two buildings.  He rolls a success
	  with a bane.  The GM rules that Dourli falls, but catches the rope under his
	  arms.  The GM decides that Dourli must now make an Agility Check against his
	  Encumberance DC or drop an item.  Dourli rolls a 2 and 1, +0 for his Agility Rank,
	  and fails miserably.  There is no point calculating Dourli's Encumberance, he has
	  clearly failed.  The GM rules that this means that unfortunately, Dourli drops
	  the gemstone he has just acquired into the canal below.
	</p>
      </playexample>

      <p>
	In order to use encumbrance you should be using the standard character sheets.
	In the equipment section of the character sheet, marked against the side, are
	encumbrance values for each class of item (small, medium and large) and values
	for armour and coin.  The total of these values is the characters encumbrance.
	Note that you do not count items twice (<eg/> a shield may be a large object in
	practice but its encumbrance is counted separately because of the encumbrance
	values for armour)
      </p>

      <p>
	If you are going to use Encumberance then it is important that this rule does
	not become a long-winded exercise in accounting.  First roll the check, then
	calculate the encumbrance (if required). Secondly, don't worry about getting
	the value exactly right - it will take to long. Just eye-ball it.  Finally
	only bother calculating encumberance on demand, when the value is required.
      </p>	
    </section>




    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Attack <ampersand/> Defence</sectiontitle>
      <p>
	In Malleus Deum we try and make the players do all the rolling.
	So when a PC is attacked by an NPC the PC makes a defence check against the NPCs attack DC.
	When a PC attacks an NPC they make an attack check against the NPCs defence DC.
	When one PC attacks another PC the first PC makes an attack check, the second PC makes a defence check.
      </p>


      <playexample>
	<p>
	  Dourli attacks a preternaturally large rat.  He uses his Axe Strike 2 ability against the
	  rats defensive DC of 13.   He rolls an outcome of 12 with the additional +2 for ranks in Axe Strike
	  he gets a 14 which hits since it's greater than rats defensive DC.  The rat takes the standard axe
	  damage to his hit points.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Then it is the rats turn to attack.  The rat has an attack DC of 15.  Dourli uses Shield Block 3
	  to defend himself (using his reaction).  Dourli rolls another 12 then adds 3 for his rank in Shield
	  Block to get a total of 15.  He successfully blocks the attack.
	</p>
      </playexample>
    </section>

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Initiative, Surprise and Ambush</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	These checks are described in the chapter on combat in sections <ref>subsec:initiative</ref>,
	<ref>subsec:surprise</ref> and <ref>subsec:ambush</ref>, respectively.
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Weapon Checks<daggersymbol/></sectiontitle>
      <p>
	Under certain circumstances the players may have to check that their
	weaponry does not break.  The Outcome is compared with the Weapons Break DC
	using the following table.
      </p>

      {% include "docs/tables/weapon_checks.xml" %}	

      <p>
	Each weapon has a spirit forged into it when it is created.  A weapon's spirit
	may not be immediately obvious to an observer, and is different	from it's
	construction quality.  Cheap weapons made by unskilled artisans tend to have
	a Poor weapon spirit.  Weapons made by skilled artisans with great care might have
	a Superior weapon spirit. Weapons have one of the following Spirit levels:
	<descriptions>
	  <term>Poor</term><description>+3 Break DC</description>
	  <term>Standard</term><description>Default Break DC</description>
	  <term>Superior</term><description>-1 Break DC</description>
	  <term>Named Weapon</term><description>-2 Break DC, +1 Damage</description>
	  <term>Magic Weapon</term><description>-2 Break DC, +2 Damage, GM to elaborate on extra abilities</description>
	  <term>Relic</term><description>-2 Break DC, +3 Damage, GM to elaborate on extra abilities</description>
	</descriptions>
      </p>
    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Armour Checks<daggersymbol/></sectiontitle>
      <p>
	While weapons have a spirit, armour has a Telos.
	Under certain circumstances the players may have to check that their
	armour or weaponry does not break.
      </p>

      {% include "docs/tables/armour_checks.xml" %}

      <p>
	<descriptions>
	  <term>Poor</term><description>+3 Break DC</description>
	  <term>Standard</term><description>Default Break DC</description>
	  <term>Superior</term><description>-1 Break DC</description>
	  <term>Armour of Salvation</term><description>-2 Break DC, +1 AC</description>
	  <term>Magic Armour</term><description>-2 Break DC, +2 AC, GM to elaborate on extra abilities</description>
	  <term>Relic</term><description>-2 Break DC, +3 AC, GM to elaborate on extra abilities</description>
	</descriptions>
      </p>
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Aspect Checks</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	Role-playing is shared story-telling.  Conflict and struggle are central to a 
	good story.  Aspects are the mechanic that we use to represent facets of the 
	characters personality that can be used to create interesting, non-physical,
	internal or inter-personal conflict and character development within the game.
      </p>

      <p>
	<indexentry>Aspects</indexentry> 
	Aspect checks are a special type of Ability Check.  They describe some part of a
	characters personality, their system of beliefs, or their philosophy of life. There are many
	types of aspects.  They fall loosely into the following categories:
      </p>

      <descriptions>
	<term>Personality Aspects</term>
	<description>
	  <p>
	    describe some part of a characters personality or demeanour, their flaws and
	    foibles, their short-comings, their weaknesses and sometimes their strengths,
	    <eg/> Mama's Boy, As Exciting as Cold Oatmeal, Plagued by Self-Doubt.
	  </p>
	</description>

	<term>Philosophy Aspects</term>
	<description>
	  <p>
	    encode a character's beliefs and their moral compass: Defender of the 
	    Downtrodden, Man of the Book, Death before Dishonour.
	  </p>
	</description>

	<term>Relationship Aspects</term>
	<description>
	  <p>
	    Relationship aspects can be used to describe a close bond between the
	    character and an individual, a magic item, their god, a small group or even
	    a large population.  In the last case it comes in the form of fame, or
	    infamy, with aspects like Hero of Bad Dunmharaiodh, Emissary of the Elf Council,
	    Beholden to the Black Hand, or The Scourge of the Serpent People.
	  </p>
	</description>        

	<term>Insanity, Curses, Diseases, and other effects</term>
	<description>
	  <p>
	    other in game conditions can be represented by aspects such as insanity,
	    and various diseases.  Players need not worry themselves over these during
	    character creation.
	  </p>
	</description>


	<term>Oath</term>
	<description>
	  <p>
	    Some characters have sworn Oaths.  An oath is an aspect.  Oaths may be broken,
	    and when they are there are consequences for the character.	    
	  </p>
	</description>
      </descriptions>

      


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Choosing Good Aspects</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Aspects are used to drive conflict in the game.  If the character is
	  a <emph>Problem Gambler</emph> have the party visiting gambling dens so
	  the character has to suffer an internal struggle not to gamble and
	  have some thugs lean on the character to pay back his debts.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Good aspects are evocative of the characters personality, their belief system 
	  or their social status. They should not describe parts of the game already covered 
	  by existing game mechanics.  For example, <emph>Greatest Swordsman Ever</emph> is 
	  not a good aspect - it interferes with the game rules on combat.  <emph>Thinks He's
	  the Greatest Swordsman Ever</emph> is much better because it establishes the 
	  character as a braggadocio or self-delusional.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Remember that the Aspects should be chosen to create conflict and problems for the
	  characters to overcome.  If an Aspect does not cause the character to overcome
	  difficulties or make interesting decisions it is not a good aspect. As a general
	  rule good aspects are phrases that when applied require action from the character.
	  Additionally they should be neither too specific or too general.  For good example
	  aspects see Figure<ref>figure:random-aspect-table</ref> on
	  page<pageref>table:{{ doc_name }}-random-aspects</pageref>.
	</p>
	{% include "docs/tables/random_aspect_table.xml" %}	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Aspect Creation</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  <indexentry>Creating Aspects</indexentry> 
	  <indexentry>Aspect Creation</indexentry> 
	  Before choosing aspects we suggest discussing the role playing milieu with the GM.
	  Get a feel for the colour of the world and the NPCs and organizations within it.  Then
	  <emph>with the other players, together as a group</emph>, choose one aspect with the GM
	  that ties your character to one of these NPCs or organizations, or one of the player
	  characters.  Then choose a Personality or Philosophy based aspect for your character.
	  You just write these on your character sheet in the Aspects section with a starting rank
	  of 1.
	</p>      
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Compelling and Resisting Aspects</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  <indexentry>Compelling an Aspect</indexentry> 
	  <indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Compel</subentry></indexentry> 
	  Any player, including the GM, may attempt to <defn>Compel</defn> any characters
	  aspect at any time, this includes a player compelling their own PC.  Compelling aspects
	  involves suggesting to a player that their character should follow a course of action in
	  keeping with one of their aspects.  The GM should agree that the aspect can be compelled
	  in the given context, and then the player may choose to <bold>accept</bold> or
	  <bold>resist</bold> the compel.
	</p>

	<p>
	  If the player <emph>accepts a compel</emph> for an aspect then they should have 
	  their character behave in accordance with that aspect.  Alternatively, players may
	  have their characters try to <emph>resist the compel</emph>.  When doing so they roll
	  a Check against a default DC of 15.  
	  If the check is successful they <emph>resist the compel</emph>, their character's
	  behaviour is not bound by the aspect, and they gain a Rank in that Aspect.  If they do
	  <emph>not</emph> resist the compel then their character's behaviour is bound by the
	  compel.
	  <equation>
	    <line>Aspect Check:</line>
	    <line>2d12 + Aspect Rank<geqqsymbol/> 13</line>
	  </equation>


	  REF THE ASPECT CHECK in CORE

	</p>     


	<p>
	  Theurgic Magic requires the use of a special Theurgic Oath,
	  that is represented in game by an Aspect,
	  for example "I shall be the shield of the downtrodden, and the
	  sword of the suffering".   Some theurgic abilities will reduce the
	  strength of that oath.
	</p>
	

	<p>
	  When the check is successful the Character who makes the successful
	  check promotes this aspect, and  whoever compelled the aspect may recharge a
	  die into their Luck or Mettle Pool.
	</p>

	<p>
	  When a Boon is rolled in an aspect check the following things happen something fortuitous
	  happens.  When a Bane is rolled something bad happens.
	</p>

	<playexample>
	  <p>
	    Dourli hears that Emrich, of the Red Knives, has offered 20gp for information 
	    about one of Dourli's colleagues.  A second player might decide to try to compel Dourli,
	    as Dourli has an aspect <emph>Gold is my Lodestone 1</emph>.  The player then decides 
	    whether he will accept the compel and provide the information about his associate
	    or try to resist the compel.
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    He decides to resist.  So he has to make an Aspect Check.  He rolls 
	    2d12 and rolls two 4s, plus 1 for the aspects rank, for a total of 9.  Dourli fails 
	    the check, as the total is lower than the DC for Aspect Checks of 15.  So now Dourli has 
	    to provide the information about his associate in order to garner his well earned 
	    gold.  
	  </p>

	  <p>
	    Dourli now decides that he cannot, 
	    just hand over the information about his associate, like a despicable cad, and 
	    instead resolves to try and sell them bogus information.  This action satisfies 
	    the compel as, if he succeeds, he still gets his gold.  Whether this approach
	    succeeds or not is resolved separately, perhaps using a Deceive check.  Because
	    Dourli rolled a Boon during his check, something good happens, the GM might rule
	    that the Emrich is receptive to Dourli's false information, maybe due to
	    confirmation bias? This might be reflected by giving the Decieve check a lower
	    DC, or maybe granting Dourli advantage on the Decieve check.
	  </p>
	</playexample>


	<subsubsection>
	  <subsubsectiontitle>Oath Breaking</subsubsectiontitle>
	  <p>
	    FIXME
	  </p>
	</subsubsection>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Reevaluating Aspects</subsectiontitle>
	<indexentry>Reevaluating Aspects</indexentry> 
	<indexentry>Aspect<subentry>Reevaluation</subentry></indexentry>

	<p>
	  Aspects can be <defn>Reevaluated</defn> for two reasons.  The first is that
	  the Aspect is not working in the game in a way that makes the GM or the player happy,
	  <eg/> this might be because the Aspect is never used, or the behaviour the aspect compels
	  do not align with the players view of their character.  The second reason is that
	  the Aspect has reached a Rank of 4.  <bold>Aspects must be reevaluated when the Aspects
	  Rank reaches 4.</bold> At this point the character has concluded this stage
	  of their character arc.  If the Aspect was interesting then a new Aspect can be chosen
	  based on the original aspect, that has the character evolve and grow over time.
	</p>

	<p>
	  When reevaluating aspects any number of aspects can be retired, reworded, replaced with
	  a new, completely different aspect, or perhaps the character simple gains a new
	  additional aspect entirely.
	</p>

	<p>
	  When reevaluating aspects remember that the point of aspects in the game is to drive
	  the story and character development.  If an aspect is not being used frequently, or if
	  it is being overused, or abused, if it has just become a little tired, if there is an
	  opportunity to represent character growth or move the character through some character
	  arc, then now is the time to consider making changes to the characters aspects.
	</p>

	<playexample>
	  <p>
	    Much later, Dourli's aspect <emph>Gold is my Lodestone 4</emph> finally reaches a rank of 4.
	    At this point the aspect should be reevaluated.  If his aspects are working
	    well in the game, leading to enjoyable game play, then Dourli might make a subtle change to
	    the aspect, maybe softening the wording of this aspect to, something like,
	    <emph>If you give a Man a Sword he can Rob a Bank, if you give him a Bank he can Rob the
	    World 1</emph>, which is a little less proscriptive.
</p>

<p>
  Maybe Dourli has had an epiphany?  He has realized the error of his ways, wasting his life
in the pursuit of filthy lucre, and so he replaces the <emph>Gold is my Lodestone 4</emph>
aspect with a new aspect, <emph>I am a River to My People 1</emph>.
</p>

<p>
  Finally, Dourli might decide to choose a new aspect altogether.  Maybe choosing a new
  aspect all together <emph>You Must be the Change you Wish to See in the World 1</emph>.
</p>

<p>
  In any case the decision should be opened up to the table for input and debate.
</p>
</playexample>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Conflicting Aspects</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  Sometimes a characters aspects conflict with one another.  In such cases 
  someone can compel one aspect to try and gain a bonus on a second
  aspect check.
</p>

<playexample>
  <p>
Suppose the GM tries to compel Dourli's <emph>Gold is My Lodestone 1</emph>
aspect to make Dourli sell out one of his companions.  Dourli may counter that
he has sworn friendship with the companion while imbibing and that the
GM's compel conflicts with another one of his aspects <emph>My Word as a Dwarf 2</emph>.
In such cases the GM should grant the player some advantage to the
<emph>Gold is My Lodestone 1</emph> check.  As a general rule, it is not a good idea
to allow a character to have aspects that are too contradictary.
</p>
</playexample>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Vetoing an Aspect</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  At the end of the day the player's character is his own.  The GM and other
  players should not force the player to make his character take an aspect,
  or behave in a way they do not want.  The player may always veto newly
  proposed aspects for their character or suggested actions for a compelled
  aspect.  Players should use this veto power only when they really dislike
  the outcome of a compelled aspect.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Permanent Aspects</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  Some disabilities or afflications can be modelled, in game, using aspects.
  These aspects may or may not be permanent.  For this kind of aspect the GM
  can rule that the aspect is never reevaluated.  Permanent aspects have some
  maximum rank beyond which the character cannot improve.  The upper limit for
  the rank of permanent aspects should be determined by the GM on a per aspect
  basis.  The higher the maximum rank the less of an impediment the aspect will
  become with time.
</p>

<playexample>
  <p>
    Dourli comes into some unexpected wealth.  He decides to go and celebrate
    at the local tavern.  The GM asks him to roll a Generic Check to give an
    indication of what happens.  Unfortunately Dourli rolls a double 1.  The
    GM decides that Dourli looses his left hand in an unfortunate axe throwing
    incident.  Dourli gains the <emph>Missing Left Hand 1</emph> aspect.  The GM
    determines that this is a permanent aspect and that it has a maximum rank of
    7.
</p>

<p>
  Later Dourli, finds himself climbing over a roof.  He fails the Climb roll and
  starts to slip.   The GM determines that now might be a good time to make a
  <emph>Missing Left Hand 1</emph>  check.  Dourli fails and so slips off the roof.
  He makes a last minute Agility Check and is left hanging from the gutter by his
  right hand.
</p>
</playexample>      
</subsection>
</section>


<section>
<sectiontitle>Luck Checks<label>sec:luck-checks</label></sectiontitle>

<p>
<indexentry>Luck Checks</indexentry>
<indexentry>Checks<subentry>Luck</subentry></indexentry>
Whenever the GM  finds themselves in a situation where they turn to a player and ask 
<emph>Do you feel lucky?</emph> then perhaps the player should be making a
Luck Check. A <defn>Luck Check</defn> is a check made against the Luck Pool.
</p>

<playexample>
  <p>
    Dourli is sitting in a corner tied up by the Black Mark, waiting on an uncertain fate.
    A lone guard, in his cups, watches over him.  Dourli wonders whether the guard might
    need to leave momentarily to relieve himself.  The GM determines that
    since Dourli has been tied up for a long time and the the guard is drinking, chances are high 
    that the guard will leave the room for a short time at some point.  So he sets an easy
    DC for the check of 7.   The GM asks Dourli whether he's feelling lucky?  Dourli's current
    Luck Pool is 1.  He rolls and gets a 17.  Dourli's Luck pool is reduced by one to zero.
    Dourli takes his opportunity when the guard leaves and bolts for it, his arms still tied.
</p>

<p>
  REF THE LUCK CHECK in CORE
  
  XXXX
  Had Dourli rolled a 19/1 he would have initially succeeded, then since his Luck Pool would
  have been reduced below zero, it's set to zero and he fails the check for want of Luck.
</p>
</playexample>
</section>


<section>
<sectiontitle>Mettle Checks<label>sec:mettle-checks</label></sectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Mettle Checks</indexentry>
<indexentry>Checks<subentry>Mettle (PCs)</subentry></indexentry>
Characters may, from time to time, be forced to make a Mettle Check.
Mettle Checks occur when characters have to face their fears.
</p>

<p>
  A <defn>Mettle Check</defn> is a check made against the Mettle Pool.  It has a Toll of 1
  and a DDC of 6.  When a character fails a Mettle Check another neraby character,
  chosen at random or by the GM, must also make a Mettle Check.  Mettle checks can continue
  to cascade until someone succeeds or everyone has failed a Mettle Check.  Mettle Checks are
  free actions.
</p>

<p>
  The GM should feel free to modify the Mettle Check DC as he pleases, <ie/>
  to reflect being attacked at night, being vastly outnumbered, the horrible
  visage of the characters opponents, the party being in good spirits etc.
  As characters fail Mettle Checks the party starts to lose dice from their Mettle
  Pools and their fighting options become somewhat diminished.
</p>

<p>
  Some suggested times to make Mettle Checks are:
  <list>
<li>Whenever a party member becomes Bloodied,</li>
<li>When the party enters combat against a Fear causing opponent,</li>
<li>Whenever the party is Surprised or Ambushed.</li>
</list>
Ultimately, however, it is up to the GMs discretion to decide when the players should
make a Mettle check and the GM should feel free to force Mettle Checks sooner or later
in the combat to satisfy the narrative imperative.
</p>

<p>
  The first time the group collectively fails a Mettle Check then everyone gains the Checked
  Condition see page<pageref>condition:checked</pageref>, after the second time everyone fails
  a Mettle Check everyone gains the Broken Condition, see page<pageref>condition:broken</pageref>.
  The third time the group fails their Mettle Check they gain the Routed Condition, see
  page<pageref>condition:routed</pageref>.
</p>

<playexample>
  <p>
    Dourli and Rozlyn have been fighting a running battle with the Black Mark and it's starting
    to take its toll on the two.  Rozlyn is hit with an arrow, dropping her Stamina to zero, giving
    her the bloodied condition, and
</p>

<p>
  Had Dourli rolled a 19/1 he would have initially succeeded, then since his Luck Pool would
  have been reduced below zero, it's set to zero and he fails the check for want of Luck.
</p>
</playexample>


<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Opposed Mettle Checks</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  Some abilities target the opponents Mettle, <eg/> Banish, and Howl of the Hunt. In these
  circumstances the character makes a check against their targets Mettle, and if successfully
  deducts a cost, specified by the ability being used, from their opponents Mettle pool.
</p>
</subsection>  
</section>



<section>
<sectiontitle>Magic Checks</sectiontitle>

<p>
<indexentry>Magic</indexentry>
Magic infuses this and all worlds.  It links and binds all things, tying entities
together and creating invisible bonds between the planes.  The utilization of magic
is concerned with controlling the flow of thaumaturgical energies along these paths.
Magic appears to be goverened by well known principles and is as much a science
as Physicks, Mathematics, Theosophy, Astrology, Phrenology or even Biology.  However,
due to the chaotic nature of thaumic energies the application of these laws
is unreliable, and frequently dangerous.
</p>

<p>
  The basic principles of magic are as follows:
</p>
<descriptions>
<term>Law of Potentials</term>
<description>
  In order for magic to occur there must be a difference in thaumaturgical
  potentials, a high potential and a low potential.
</description>

<term>Law of Flux</term>
<description>
  Magic occurs when thaumaturgical energies flow from a high potential to a
  low potential along a line of flux.
</description>

<term>Law of Conductivity</term>
<description>
  Lines of magical flux may be created, broken or enhanced using a variety of techniques.
  Different materials conduct magical energies better than others.
</description>

<term>Law of Contagion</term>
<description>
  As magic shapes all things it follows logically that similar things are linked by the
  lines of flux that created them.  The relationship between things can be used to gain
  more control over magic.
</description>

<term>Law of Knowledge</term>
<description>
  The more you know about a subject the greater your knowledge about the
  lines of flux that bind them, and the more power you have over them.  This can be
  considered to be a corollary of the Law of Contagion.
</description>
</descriptions>

<p>
  Later in this chapter we explore in more depth how the fundamental laws of magic effect casting.
</p>

<figure position="!b">
  <img id="rackham_frogs" scale="0.38"/>
</figure>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Magic Checks -- Casting Spells</subsectiontitle>

<p>
<label>sec:magic-dice</label>
Mechanically, magical spells are abilities.  Casting magic uses a pool of magic dice, and
magic checks are dice pool checks.  Characters that do not cast spells also have a magic pool
that represents their life-energy, their animus.  Non-casting characters will have no
magic abilities that use their magic pool.  However their magic pools can be used as a
a defence against certain magical effects.  Specialized magic casting characters will have
larger magic dice pools, greater energy, and a variety of skills that allow them to use that pool.
</p>

{% include "docs/tables/magic_modifiers.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/overcharge_effects.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/overcharge_effects_pt2.xml" %}
</subsection>


<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Principles of Magic<daggersymbol/></subsectiontitle>

<p>
  Magical checks are affected by the complex, chaotic nature of thaumaturgic
  energies.  We now explain the laws of magic, which describe how magic is effected by
  context and circumstance.  But the reader should beware; magic is a dark art; those
  who play with the devil's toys will be brought by degrees to wield his sword.
</p>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>The Law of Potentials</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
The first law of magic is that <indexentry>Rules of Magic<subentry>First</subentry></indexentry>
<emph>magic requires a potential difference in energy levels as a prerequisite</emph>.
Furthermore, <indexentry>Rules of Magic<subentry>Second</subentry></indexentry>
<emph>the productive use of magic requires the construction of a thaumaturgical
conduit between potentialities</emph> through which magical energies can flow.
</p>

<p>
  There are many different sources of thaumaturgical potentialities, such as the
  potential difference between planes of existance, energy from stored thaumaturgical
  sources, the animus (a person or animals spark of life) and so on.  We examine the most
  important, and the most widely used, of these potentialities here.
</p>

<subsubsubsection>
<subsubsubsectiontitle>Raw/Planar Magical Sources</subsubsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Planar Magicks are those that use the raw potential differences between two
  planes directly, these so-called Protinus magics, are the most powerful, the
  most volatile, and most dangerous of the magical sources to use.  Casters
  attempt to harness the flow from planes of higher energy to planes of
  lower energy.  There are two main dangers to using this form of thatumaturgical
  energy.  The first is its volatility. Casters using this energy source are more
  likely to overcharge their spells.  The second danger are the lurkers in the dark.
  There are a myriad of creatures lurking in the frigid abyssal planes who hunger
  eternally to escape to higher planes and feed indiscriminately.  They wait for the
  opportunity a miscast might provide.
</p>

<p>
  <defn>Elemental Magic</defn> is a subset of planar magic that uses the potential
  between a particular set of well-known planes of existance, the so-called
  elementatal planes.  The advantage of this energy source is that these planes are
  comparatively stable and their behaviour is fairly well-understood.  Unfortunately,
  elemental magic is less versatile than, the more general, planar magic.
</p>

<p>
  If a magical act uses extra-planar differentials, and the flow of energies
  is from this plane to some other lower
  potential plane then energies are expended from this plane, the temperature
  drops, lights dim and ice may form.  We call such an action an endothaumic
  reaction.  In contradistinction, if energy flows to this plane from some higher
  plane then the magic is of a type named exothaumic and the tell-tale side effects
  of such practice are bright lights, heat are sometimes smoke of a sulfurous nature.
  No other magic sources have such side-effects.
</p>
</subsubsubsection>
</subsubsection>

<figure position="!" fullwidth="true">
  <img id="skull" scale="0.34"/>
</figure>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Magic Items and their Power Sources</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Magical items typically use thaumaturgical energies stored within the device itself.
  Magic by its very nature is evanescent - it has a tendency to dissipate after
  a period of time.  Magical items, therefore, tend to be made of thaumic insulating
  materials in order to minimize the rate at which magic is dissipated.
</p>

<p>
  In game, this stored magical potential is representated by some magical devices
  having their own magic pool and refresh rates.  The item used to store magical energies
  may be one use, rechargeable or self recharging.  One use magic items will have no
  refresh rate.  When a one-use items dice pool is depleted the device is spent.
</p>

<descriptions>
<term>Runic Magic</term>
<description>
  <p>
    are essentially spells that automatically cast
    themselves when a certain triggering event occurs, <ie/> the runes are read or
    touched.  The effects of runic magic are typically limited to the vicinity of the
    runes.
</p>

<p>
  The small amount of magic required to cast the runespell is stored in the runes
  themselves when they are created.  Overtime this magic will leach from the rune
  and it will no longer be viable, but may still be replenished by a skilled
  Runemaster.  Depleted runic magic will have limited or even no effect.
  For this reason runes are typically carved into materials which are
  highly thaumaturgically non-conductive such as ferrous metals or rock.  Once the
  runespell is cast it behaves as any other spell, drawing the energy for the spell
  itself from some second source.  For runes carved in stone, glass and steel this
  is almost always from the elemental planes of earth as the spells powers are
  enhanced by the contagious nature of the substrate.
</p>

<p>
  Magical swords, armour, rings and the like are typically runic in nature.
See Section<ref>sec:attunement</ref> on page<pageref>sec:attunement</pageref>
for information on using magic items and attunement.
</p>
</description>

<term>Scrolls</term>
<description>
  <p>
    contain the written incantations that must be entoned to cast a spell <label>sec:scrolls</label>.
    They often also contain background thaumic theory, notes on the casters experiences with casting
    the spell, other bits of information relevant to the spell, and sometimes bits of information
    completely irrelevant to the spell.  Unlike runes they do not contain any magical energies with
    which to automatically trigger or power the spell instead drawing their energy from
    the readers magic pool.  Most scrolls are written in Inochian, though some
    are written in languages like Aquillonian, Lagashi, and Fey, and the caster must be able to read
    from the scroll to cast it.  These requirements make scrolls difficult for non-casters to use.
</p>

<p>
  Scrolls may be used in the following ways: a caster may cast a spell from a scroll, or
  they may learn that spell from that scroll, or both.
</p>

<p>
  <emph>When casting a spell from a scroll the caster must first make a successful language
  check in the language that the scroll is written in to read the scroll</emph>.  If they
  fail then the spell is not cast and no magic energy is
  expended.  If they fail with a boon they receive +3 to the next attempt.  If they
  fail with a bane they must expend an extra magic die after the spell is cast.  If they
  succeed with a boon they may add or subtract 3 to their roll or return a magic die exhausted
  in the casting to their magic pool.  <emph>After reading the scroll
  the spell is cast normally using the casters own magic pool as a a rank 0 ability</emph>.
  Casting spells at 0 rank overrides the spells normal rank so if a spell has a
  minimum rank of 1 then it can still be cast at 0 rank from a scroll.
</p>

<p>
  A caster may learn a spell from a scroll given time to study it, and with the use of an
  ability promotion of the appropriate rank.
</p>

<p>
  Scrolls may be reused unless they become damaged, or the creator has written some
  limiting clause into the scroll.  This may be done in order to reduce the danger
  of misuse or limit competition with the creator.  A common example of scroll
  limitation is to include a glyph of destruction in the scroll so that it may not
  be used more than once and cannot be learned.  Another example, are cursed scrolls
  designed as a trap to protect the author's trade secrets from others.  Note that the
  proliferation of magic is seen as a dangerous thing.  Their unfettered use is frowned
  upon and policed by both the College of Mages and the Witchhunters.
</p>
</description>

<term>Potions</term>
<description>
  store thaumic energy in liquid form.  The magic is enfused in a liquid
  solvent, and contained within a glass flask with binding magical inscriptions.
  At the best of times potions have a limited shelf-life.  However, the energy stored
  in a potion begins to escape rapidly as soon as the flask is opened.  Potions
  are generally created by magic users for the use of non magic users as potions
  are easy to use and moderately easy to create.
</description>

<term>Wands</term>
<description>
  are slight batons made from thaumic conducting materials that are used to
  better focus and control raw thaumic energy. Wands are not intrinsically magical
  but are instead tools to better focus and control magic.
  See Section<ref>sec:wands</ref> on page<pageref>sec:wands</pageref>.
</description>

<term>Rods</term>
<description>
  A rod is a short, <measurement><metric>60cm</metric><imperial>2'</imperial></measurement>,
  heavy baton that is used to store and direct the flow of thaumic energy.  Casters who
  use rods recharge the energy stored within them on a regular basis.
  See Section<ref>sec:rods</ref> on page<pageref>sec:rods</pageref>.
</description>

<term>Staffs and Spears</term>
<description>
  Staffs and spears may be used to ground out magic.   Like wands, staffs do not need
  to be intrinsically magical to be used in this manner.
  See Section<ref>sec:staves</ref> on page<pageref>sec:staves</pageref>.
</description>

<term>Holy Symbol</term>
<description>
  Holy symbols use contagion to increase the strength of the conduit between a
  theurgical caster and their sponsor.  They need not be inherantly magical.
</description>
</descriptions>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>The Animus</subsubsectiontitle>

<p>
<indexentry>animus</indexentry>
Every living creature is imbued with a store of thaumic energy within and of
themselves, their <emph>Animus</emph>.  This is why even non-magical archetypes
have a magic pool.   This energy is used by a number of
forms of magic, the most widely know examples are: necromantic draining, blood
magic, death curses, and human sacrifices.
</p>

<p>
  It has been postulated that the phenomenon of life is the flow of magical power
  from some higher plane through to some lower plane.  In such a model the body is
  the conduit through which magical energies flow.  An alternate
  model holds that living creatures are wellsprings of magical energies, <ie/> that
  they are the sources of magical energies themselves.  A third model holds that both
  of the first two models hold true.  Which of these models, if any, are correct
  remains an extremely contentious area of debate amongst scholars of the dark arts.
  In any case, it is widely believed that their exists an animatic flow that is
  replenishes the animus from some source.
</p>

<p>
  The rate of the animatic flow is proportional to the strength of emotions that
  the living creature is feeling.  For this reason many thaumatergical predators
  will enhance these emotions while feeding.
</p>

<p>
  Further, it has been hypothesized that apparations, ghosts, banshees and other
  spiritual manifestions are the remnants of powerful residual animatic flow.  They
  are the eddies in the animatic flow, left by the passing of highly magical or highly
  emotive creatures.
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>The Biome</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Rather than draw magical power from a particular animus, some animistic casters,
  such as	Druids, are able to draw very small amounts of magic from all surrounding
  living creatures.  While very powerful these magics can be difficult to use if the
  biome is not in balance.
</p>

<p>
  Wild magic is effected by the environment in which it is cast.  In biomes with a
  great deal of balanced animistic energy, forests, swamps etc, Wild Magic spells
  receive a +1 DC modifier.  In cities and deserts wild magic suffers a -1 DC
  modifier.
</p>
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Channelled Magic</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Theurgic, Channelled, or Sponsored Magic is magic whose power has been channelled
  from a third party one of the so-called ``gods'', demons or celestial agents.  It is
  assumed that the caster of channeled magic is using a shared ``holy'' symbol to
  establish or strengthen the conduit between a caster and the third-party source.  In
  this type of magic the caster typically acts as	an agent for the third-party, allowing
  the third-party to project their power and their influence.  See
Section<ref>sec:holy-symbol</ref> on page<pageref>sec:holy-symbol</pageref>
</p>

<p>
  Those with an enquiring mind may be wondering where the third-party gets their
  energy from.  It seems clear that many gain their power from planar magics.
  For these 'gods' it has been surmised that the act of prayer forms a
  conduit with the god through which some small part of the devotees animus travels.
  Thus people pray to a god,  the god gains animus,  the god grants power to clerics
  to project the gods interest, the clerics use this power to protect those of their
  faith and convert new devotees, .. and so on.  Though, this is just a theory and
  such musings are clearly not meant for mere mortals such as ourselves.  Many
  religions have also practiced sacrifice as a faster and simpler way of providing
  animatic energies to their deity.
</p>

</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>The Law of Flux</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  In order for magic to happen thaumic energies must flow, as water must flow for
  a water mill to grind flour.
</p>

<p>
  Stopping the flow stops the magic.  Hindering the flow hinders the magic.
  <bold>To use magic there must be a potential difference and a flow.</bold>  Certain
  magical symbols, chiefly the pentagram and the circle, when carved, drawn or laid out
  upon the ground in salt will stop the flow of magic (salt is used because it is
  non-conductive, granular, common, cheap, and white.. which makes it easier to see
  any discontinuities in the symbols).
</p>

<p>
  An alternate problem happens when there is too much conductivity.  In practice
  this happens most often when there is too much water around, e.g. when it rains, or
  when the caster is standing in water.  Here the caster is likely to dissipate more
  energy than they otherwise would.  In practice this means that dice are exhausted
  on rolls higher than the usual value.  In rain the exhaust value increases by one,
  if you are standing in water (above your ankles) the exhaust value increases by two,
  if you are swimming the exhaust value increases by three.  For example, typically,
  magic dice are exhausted on a roll of 1 or 2.  If the character is standing knee-deep
  in "water" in a sewer they exhaust dice on a roll of 4 or less.  If they cast a four
  dice spell and rolled 1, 3, 4, 6 they would exhaust three dice.
</p>
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>The Law of Conductivity</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Magic shapes and binds all things.  Objects that share similarities are linked by
  magical ties.  These ties can be used to strengthen magical spells.  For example, having
  the blood or hair of a person can be used to strengthen certain spells when used upon
  that subject.
</p>

<wrapimg position="r" id="demon" scale="0.14"/>

<p>
  Different materials affect the flow of magic differently.  Natural and biological
  materials such as flesh, wood, and water conduct magic very well.   Ferrous metals
  glass, and rock do not conduct magic well and can interfere with its casting in
  unpredictable ways.
</p>

<p>
  Iron interferes with the flow of magic.  Magical creatures,
  particularly the Fey, do not like it.  In contrast non-ferrous metals.. Platinum,
  Gold, Silver, Copper, conduct magic, though scholars are in disagreement as to why
  these do so, given iron does not.  Silver, is a particularly excellent conductor and
  so adversely affects those possessed by extra planar entities such as the undead and
  lycanthropes.
</p>

<p>
  Magical circles break conductivity (and therefore also break contagion).
  What the circle is made of generally doesn't matter.  Though there are specialized
  protective circles for the protection of particular beings that while more
  powerful require special ingredients, (e.g. salt for vampires).
</p>

<p>
  Ferrous armour disrupts the flow of magical energies and adversly affects
  grounding.  It is impossible to ground-out magic when wearing armour.
  Similarly, if using a wooden shafted spear with a ferrous head then only the
  lowest die may be removed as the metal head interferes with the thaumaturgical
  conductivity of the shaft.
</p>

<p>
  Water, and particularly running water, is an excellent magical channel.
  Characters casting magic in standing water or casting in the rain exhaust dice
  from their result on a roll of a 1 or 2.  In running water they exhaust dice on a
  result of 1-3.  In addition, running water breaks contagion.
</p>
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>The Law of Contagion</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Magical contagion refers to the conduits that exist between similar things.
  All things are bound by magic, and magic binds all things.  But some things
  are much more closely bound than others.  These sympathetic ties effect the
  casting of spells for good or ill.
</p>

<!-- <subsubsection> -->
<!-- 	<subsubsectiontitle>Blood Magic</subsubsectiontitle> -->
<!-- 	<p> -->
<!-- 	  The power of <defn>Blood Magic</defn> is derived from thaumaturgical contagion between -->
<!-- 	  the blood and the animus of the subject.  Blood magic drains the animus from the subject. -->
<!-- 	  This allows necromancers and the like to use someone elses magic pool in spells -->
<!-- 	  without	their consent (see the rules for shared magic pools).  Blood for this purpose has to be -->
<!-- 	  fresh - remember magic is evanescent.  Casting blood magic without a specially prepared -->
<!-- 	  sacrificial dagger, an atham, is done with a -2 DC Modifier.  You do not have to be a -->
<!-- 	  caster to cast blood magic.  Some shamen use their own blood as a potential pool of energy. -->
<!-- 	</p> -->

<!-- 	<figure position="h"> -->
<!-- 	  <img id="jordan_cultist" scale="0.18"/> -->
<!-- 	</figure> -->
<!-- </subsubsection> -->


<subsubsubsection>
  <subsubsubsectiontitle>Symbolic Contagion</subsubsubsectiontitle>
  <p>
    Similar symbols form flux lines connected by contagion.  Ritual use of special
    patterns can form an association to other locations and other realms.  Holy symbols
    form conduits between theurgic source, a deity or demon, and the caster.  Shared
    symbols carved into portals tie one portal end point to another.  Contagion is
    the motivation for the use of all symbology in magic. .
</p>
</subsubsubsection>


<subsubsubsection>
<subsubsubsectiontitle>Magical Ingredients</subsubsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Magical ingredients are used to bind a spell to its target or purpose
  or bind a spell to previous castings of that spell.  Theurgical magic users
  rarely need or use magical ingredients.	Non-theurgical magic
  casters are assumed to have a small cache of reasonably general purpose
  spell casting ingredients about their person at most times (mistletoe,
  salt, spiders web, mandragora, iron powder, coffin nails, adders tongue
  and the like).  There are enough suitable substitutes for most ingredients
  that we can assume that the caster is reasonably well stocked with something
  that will do at any time.  If however the magic caster has had his stock
  of ingredients removed then his spells will be cast with a -1 DC Modifier.
  If the ingredients exhibit strong and unusual contagion with the spell in
  question the GM might grant a +1 DC Modifier to the check.
</p>
</subsubsubsection>


<subsubsubsection>
<subsubsubsectiontitle>Somatic Hand Gestures</subsubsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Spells are usually cast using somatic hand gestures.  These gestures tie
  the spell to other castings of the same spell in the past and in the future,
  increasing their power.  Magic Checks are performed with a -3 DC Modifier if
  the caster does not use somatic hand gestures when casting.
</p>
</subsubsubsection>


<subsubsubsection>
<subsubsubsectiontitle>Words of Power</subsubsubsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Words of Power</indexentry>
Words are the key to magic.  When the first great spell casters,
monumentally powerful inter-planar beings, cast their spells they
did so while intoning in Innochian, the language of magic.  Intoning
the same words forms a contagious link with the original castings
and other castings of this spell through time. Magic words may also
be used to train the invokers thoughts and to gain the attention of
other worldly beings, like ringing a bell in the dark.  Casting a
spell without verbally intoning the correct words of power
is done so at a -1 DC Modifier.
</p>

<p>
  Truely powerful creatures are very strongly bound to their true
  names.  Knowing the true name of a being is a powerful connection
  when it comes to casting spells that target that indivdual.
</p>
</subsubsubsection>


<subsubsubsection>
<subsubsubsectiontitle>Temporal Contagion</subsubsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Events that occur at the same time are connected by contagion.  This allows
  casters to draw on the power of great celestial and planar events, <eg/>
  eclipses, syzygy, and aniversaries are all potent times due temporal contagion,
  in order to increase the power of specific spells.
  Similarly, various times of the year are more auspicious for the casting
  certain rituals because of the contagion with the castings of the
  spell at the same time of in prior years, <eg/> the solstices.  The GM
  should feel free to apply modifiers to casting as they see fit at such times.
</p>
</subsubsubsection>


<subsubsubsection>
<subsubsubsectiontitle>Proximal Contagion</subsubsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Things that are close to one another are linked by proximal contagion.
  This is why many spells have a range.  Beyond that range it becomes
  difficult to form a decent conduit.  Magic at great distance is very difficult.
  If something has been close to the subject of a spell for a long time then
  that item might make a good spell component.
</p>
</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection>
<subsubsubsectiontitle>Portals</subsubsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Portals are ethereal pathways between or within planes that allow travel
  or projection through those portals.   A portal, once established, allows the caster
  to overcome many of the barriers of proximal contagion.  Portals are geographically
  distributed points bound by powerful contagious energies.
  There are two types of porta, those that are known as Greater Portals, True Portals or
  simply just Portals, through which corporeal travel is possible, and Lesser Portals,
  sometimes called conduits, which are purely magical conduits through which spells may
  be cast. Opening a portal of any size is such a difficult and dangerous practice that
  it usually requires assistance at the destination.
</p>

<p>
  Greater portals require huge amounts of thaumaturgical energy to create and to keep
  open.  Once open they allow beings to physically pass from one plane to another.
</p>

<p>
  Lesser portals are used for communication.  Devils and demons may create a simulacrum
  of themselves through a lesser portal.
  Their facsimile is created by congealling ectoplasm from the environment.
  When the lesser portal is shut this breaks any link through the portal.  However,
  the simulacrum remains linked with their parent by contagion for some time afterwards.
  Possession is also made possible by lesser portals.
</p>

<p>
  Opening portals is extremely dangerous as their are countless beings lying
  in wait, in a manner not to disimilar to the way the monstrous glowing demon fish
  hungrily await their hapless prey in the cold and the dark of the deep oceans.
</p>
</subsubsubsection>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>The Law of Knowledge</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Thaumaturgical fluxes bind all things.  The better a caster understands a subject,
  the better he understands the contagious influences that effect that subject, and
  the easier it is for the magic user to cast spells that effect the subject.
  The greater the knowledge the magical practitioner has about his subject the more
power they have over that subject <indexentry>Rules of Magic<subentry>Third</subentry>
</indexentry>, knowledge is power.
</p>

<p>
  The GM, at their discretion, should apply modifiers to the DC if the caster can
  demonstrate deep or special knowledge about the subject.  Similarly, having an accurate
  physical or mental model or representation of the target of a spell may grant an
  additional modifier.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>True Name</indexentry>
Over time and with repetition the name of a being forms a contagious conduit with the
being.  The names of truely ancient or powerful beings are spoken many many times and
their name comes to hold significant power over them.  Knowing the True Name of a magical
being grants an additional modifiers to the spell, at the GMs discretion and proportional
to the beings age and power.  It is for this reason that many of these beings shroud
themselves in the shadows of anonymity, and why many great casters seek solitude.  This
is why it pleases the creatures of the night to be known by many names.  It is also why
clerics invoke the names of their deities when casting.  The True Name of a creature is
a Word of Power bound to that creature.
</p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>


<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Other Rules</subsectiontitle>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Assisting a Cast</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  It is possible to cast spells cooperatively.  In order to do so the caster and one or
  more assistants simultaneously perform a Shared Dice Pool Check.  The result is the sum
  of all the dice rolled.  In order to assist a conduit must exist between any assistants and
  the caster, for example via physical contact, or some other magically conductive path (e.g.
  a staff).  Only the caster may ground out any magic.  Any assistants exhaust
  dice on a 3 or less, by default, as the conduit from assistant to caster is leaky.  In the
  event of an overcharge, any assisting casters will also be effected by the overcharge
  unless they make a Speed DC 14 Check to break the conduit with the caster.
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Rituals</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Magic<subentry>Ritual Casting</subentry></indexentry>
<indexentry>Ritual Casting</indexentry>
Rituals are spells cast cooperatively over a long period of time.  A ritual is cast by
one or more participants over a period of hours.  There is always one leader of the spell
who controls the magic.  The participants in a ritual must be casters or blood magic
practioners.  Every hour each participant contributes one die towards a shared pool, one
die per hour.  For every hour after the first the participants must
make a Willpower DC 9 check.  If they fail they lose concentration and can no longer contribute
magic to the ritual though they cannot break the circle.  Every participant who has can cast
the ritual spell must add their spell rank to the result.
</p>

<p>
  Only the ritual leader may exhaust dice or use items during a spell.  Ritual magic may
  also gain a modifiers from the use of effigies, prepared casting circle, items linking them
  to the destination by contagion etc.
</p>

<p>
  Ritual casting is a special rule for certain spells tagged <emph>Ritual</emph>.  Spells are
  usually cast <emph>Extemporaneously</emph>.  If a spell is not tagged as a ritual then it is
  assumed to be cast extemporaneously.  Some spells can be cast either as a ritual or extemporaneously.
<indexentry>Magic<subentry>Extemporaneous Casting</subentry></indexentry>
<indexentry>Extemporaneous Casting</indexentry>
</p>
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Influence, Possession and Domination</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Magic items embued with essence of other beings may come to exert pressure on
  the bearer of the item.  There are three levels of control a magic item may have
  over a PC: influence, possession, and domination.  Influence are purely story
  based effects.  The character has dreams or nightmares and feels the urge to do certain
  things or is drawn to certain people or locations.   Possession is represented
  in game by the character gaining a new Aspect to reflect the control of the item
  over the character.  If the character is dominated then the GM takes the characters
  sheet and runs the character, usually for a short period of time. The character may
  or may not be allowed a will-power save against these effects, depending on the item.
</p>
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Interaction of Magical Items</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Controlling magic during the casting of spells is a difficult process
  at the best of times.  Doing so with multiple casting aids is nearly impossible.
  For example, a caster should not use a wand and a rod in the same casting, or
  a wand and a staff.  The caster may carry and even hold multiple
  items but using more than one at a time is very difficult.  Woe betide the fool
  who attempts to make play things of such dark and potent energies.
</p>
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Holy Symbols <indexentry>Holy Symbols</indexentry></subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
<label>sec:holy-symbol</label>
Holy symbols use contagion to increase the strength of the conduit between a
theurgical caster and their sponsor.  It is assumed that theurgical casters have a
magical symbol.  If a theurgical caster is not using a holy symbol they suffer a
-2 DC Modifier.  This is reduced to a -1 DC Modifier if the caster has time to
improvise a holy symbol.
</p>
</subsubsection>



<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Staves, Spears and Groundig</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Grounding - Staffs/Spears</indexentry>
Because Staves and Spears are constructed from wood, a magically conductive material, they can be
used to ground out spells, to mitigate the effects of overcharging.
</p>

<p>
  After a spell has overcharged the caster may be able to <emph>ground</emph> out some extra
  overcharge energy.  This involves disipating some of the magical energy by creating a conduit for
  magic to flow into the earth.  Grounding
  allows the caster to exhaust any single die from the check before the results of the check are
finalized. <indexentry>Grounding</indexentry>
<indexentry>Spell Casting<subentry>Grounding</subentry></indexentry>.
</p>

<p>
  The process of grounding requires a well controlled magical flux.  This flux is highly sensitive
  to metal.  Metal adversely effects the flow of magic and casters wearing armour have difficulty grounding
  dice with as much finnesse as they might otherwise be able to.   A character is only able
  to ground dice with face values greater than or equal to the sum of their grounding modifiers, see
  Table<ref>figure:{{ doc_name }}-magic-modifiers</ref>.  For example a mage with a staff and no armour
  may ground a die with any face value, <ie/> with a face value greater than zero, a mage wearing
  heavy metal armour, <eg/> chain mail, and using a spear can only ground out dice with a face value of
  six.
</p>

<table>
<tablecategory>Figure</tablecategory>
<tablespec>
<fixed>0.33</fixed>
<fixed>0.33</fixed>
</tablespec>
<tabletitle>Grounding Table</tabletitle>
<tablelabel>table:{{ doc_name }}-grounding</tablelabel>

<tableheaderrow>
<td>Equipment</td>
<td>Grounding Modifier</td>
</tableheaderrow>

<tablerow>
<td>Staff</td>
<td>+0</td>
</tablerow>

<tablerow>
<td>Spear</td>
<td>+1</td>
</tablerow>

<tablerow>
<td>Spear</td>
<td>+1</td>
</tablerow>

<tablerow>
<td>Light Metal Armour</td>
<td>+2</td>
</tablerow>

<tablerow>
<td>Heavy Metal Armour</td>
<td>+4</td>
</tablerow>
</table>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Wands</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Using a wand allows the caster to modify the face value of their spell dice by one,
  that is a six can be converted to a five, or a three could be converted into either a
  two or a four.
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Rods</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Rods are
  constructed from a thaumically conductive core encircled in an outer thaumic
  insulating shell.  Typically, rods can store an extra die worth of thaumic
  energy.  Magical rods can be used in combat and are equivalent to a club.  Once used
  the caster needs to recharge the rod which they may do when they rest as if it were
  their own pool.  The die used for the rod in a spell check should be rolled separatly
  from the casters pool or be of a different colour (the dice in these pools exhaust independently).
</p>
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Attunement</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  Powerful magical devices may be embued with the residual animus of their
  creators, or tainted by the nature of their magical source.  In either case,
  this is represented in game by the item having one or more aspects that are applied
  to characters when they attune with the item.  The nature of the interaction
  required to transfer the items aspects to the character depends on the item,
  <eg/> the aspects might be applied when they touch the item, or when they have used
  the item a number of times, <etc/>.
</p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
</section>
</chapter>




<chapter>
<chaptertitle>Combat<label>ch:combat</label></chaptertitle>

<section>
<sectiontitle>Combat Overview</sectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Combat<subentry>Groups</subentry></indexentry>     
<indexentry>Groups<subentry>Combat</subentry></indexentry>     
Combat is a core part of the game and has its own specific set of rules.
Before combat starts all the combatants	are divided into groups by the GM,
typically there will be be one group of PCs, and one to three groups of
monsters/NPCs.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Initiative Order</indexentry>
<indexentry>Group Order</indexentry>
Malleus Deum uses <defn>Group Order</defn> to determine the order in which
these Groups act during combat.  When a Group acts, every member of the group
takes a turn.	Members of the group may take their turns in any order within
their group. So when the PC's group acts, the players may choose the order in
which their characters act, within their group, or just take their turns in
clockwise order	around the table.  Once all members of a group have taken their
turn, the next group in order acts.
</p>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Determining Group Order Before Combat</subsectiontitle>		
<p>
  In mundane combat encounters the <emph>GM should just choose the Group Order</emph>.
  If the monsters start the fight then perhaps they should have initiative.  Otherwise
  the GM should consider just allowing the PCs to go first, they are supposed to be
  the heroes after all.  This makes combat faster, keeps the game moving and gives
  the PCs agency.
</p>

<p>
  If the GM wishes one of a number of different checks may be used before combat to
  determine group order.  These checks are: <emph>Initiative</emph>,
  <emph>Surprise</emph>, and <emph>Ambush</emph>.  
</p>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Initiative<label>subsec:initiative</label></subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  The GM should consider getting the players to make an initiative check in any of the following
  circumstances:
  <list>
<li>The narrative dictates, <eg/> when confronting "boss" monsters, or</li>
<li>When the stakes are high, when inititiative order might be strategically important
to the outome of the combat, or</li>
<li>To punish the PCs for poor strategic decisions, or </li>
<li>To punish the PCs for bad luck when executing their plans.</li>
</list>
</p>

<p>	    
<indexentry>Initiative Check</indexentry>
<emph>Initiative is an Opposed Group Delegate check.  One member of each group is chosen
by the GM to roll an ability check to determine their groups Initiative Result.  During
combat the groups act in order from highest initiative result to lowest.</emph>.
</p>

<p>
  An <defn>Initiative Check</defn> is made using an ability chosen by the GM,
  and based on context.  Some abilities that could be used to make the initiative check
  are perception, speed, Listen, and Scout.  We use
  the term <defn>Initiative Check</defn> to refer to this check irrespective of what
  underlying ability was used to make the check.  Different groups may use different
  abilities for an Initiative Check. 
</p>	
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Surprise<label>subsec:surprise</label></subsubsectiontitle>	  
<p>
<label>sec:surprise</label>
<indexentry>Surprise</indexentry>
Under certain circumstances it is possible for one group to surprise another group.
For this to happen two conditions must be satisfied:
<olist>
<li>The GM rules that Surprise is possible, and</li>
<li>One group must succeed at a Surprise Check</li>
</olist>
</p>

<p>
  The GM should rule that <emph>surprise is possible</emph> when the situation and narrative
  allow it.  For example it may be impossible for one group to surprise another on barren plains
  where there is no cover for miles around, or when two groups approach each other down a light
  corridor.  The GM should ensure that it is very hard to surprise groups expecting to be
  attacked.
</p>	    

<p>
  A <defn>Surprise Check</defn> is a Group Delegate Check where one
  character from the surprising group checks their Stealth Result versus one of their
  opponents Perception or Listen Check Result.
</p>	  

<p>
  <emph>When a group is surprised it gets no actions for the first round of combat.  In
  addition the surprised group must make a Mettle Check.  The attackers gain advantage
  on any Checks during a Surprise Roll.  Additionally, whether the surprise attempt is
successful or not the would be surpriser automatically wins initiative.</emph>
</p>	  

<playexample>
  <p>
    Dourli, attempts to surprise two gang members in the city by attacking them from behind
    under the cover of darkness.  Dourli is aware of his opponents already, but do the
    gang members become aware of Dourli?  Dourli makes a Stealth check against his opponents
    Perception DC.  If successful his opponents will be unaware of him and he will surprise
    the gang members, if he fails to surprise them he probably should still go first in
    the initiative, since he is a player character and he initiated the attack.
</p>
</playexample>

</subsubsection>


<figure position="!b">
  <img id="rackham_sea_serpent" scale="0.37"/>
</figure>      

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Ambush<label>subsec:ambush</label></subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Ambush</indexentry>
Ambush is special subtype of Surprise that occurs when the ambusher has enough
time to plan their initial attack well.  For a successful ambush one group must be
be stationary waiting in ambush.  The other group must move into the ambush area.
</p>

<p>
  <emph>Players receive a +6 modifier to their surprise when ambushing, and they receive
  a -6 modifier to their surprise roll when being ambushed.   The effects of being
  ambushed are the same as those for being surprised.  In addition, the ambushers may
  have had time to set traps and snares, prepare actions, cast non-combat spells
<etc/> at the GMs discretion.</emph>
</p>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
  <sectiontitle>Combat Rounds</sectiontitle>
  <p>
    <defn>Combat rounds</defn> represent about ten seconds of time in-game.  During a
    round every member of the combat takes a single <defn>Turn</defn>.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Actions</indexentry>
<indexentry>Standard Action</indexentry>
<indexentry>Move Action</indexentry>
<indexentry>Minor Action</indexentry>
<emph>In a characters Turn the character has time to perform a Standard Action, a Move
Action and a Minor Action</emph>.  Actions can be demoted from a Standard Action to a Move
or Minor Action, and from a Move Action to a Minor Action.  These actions can be
performed in any order	within a combat	round and they are all optional.
</p>

<figure position="h">
  <img id="rackham_divider" scale="2.0"/>
</figure>    

<p>
  There are a few extra complications to combat: Immediate Actions,
  Reactions, Free Actions, Miscellaneous Actions, and Prepared Actions which we
  discuss later.
</p>

<figure position="t">
  <img id="death_comes_calling" scale="0.085"/>
</figure>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Standard Action</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  Standard actions are the main combat actions that are used for most
  physical attacks and many spells.  Examples are Sword Strike and Axe Strike.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Move Action</subsectiontitle>

<p>
  During combat there are a number of different movement actions available.
  A normal <defn>Move Action</defn> allows the character to move their normal move distance.
  A <defn>Run Action</defn> is performing two Move Actions in a Round, <eg/>
  the character Moves and then demotes their Standard Action to another Move Action, moving
  twice.
</p>

<p>
  The character may <defn>Flee</defn> which is a Run Action away from danger.  Fleeing
  characters gain an extra d6 movement, but must make a Morale Check to stop fleeing.
</p>

<p>
  Characters may also make a <defn>Charge</defn> Action.  In order to make a charge
  a character has to be greater than their movement away from the target of their
  charge.  First the charging character moves their movement towards their opponent.
  Then the Charging character must make a Mettle Check.  If they fail, they make an
  additional move towards their opponent but do not attack.   If they succeed they move
  an additional movement, with a +d6 bonus movement, and may then perform a melee attack.
</p>

<p>
  On a grid, the distance the character may move a number of squares up to the movement value
  on their character sheet.  Using TOTM the GM will dictate distances to the players.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Minor Action</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  A minor action is any operation that can be performed in very short period of time,
  <eg/> grabbing an item from your belt, opening a door, picking an item up
  <etc/>.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Free Actions</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  A <defn>Free Action</defn> is an optional extra action that the character performs
  in his turn and that does not count against their limit of actions for their round.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Immediate Actions</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  <defn>Immediate Actions</defn> are Free Actions that the characters can perform
  once, <emph>at any time</emph> during the round.  Examples of Immediate Actions
  are using Leadership to try and cause a halt to combat to allow negotiation,
  and Fleeing.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Multi-Turn Actions</subsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Full Turn Action</indexentry>
<indexentry>Multi Turn Action</indexentry>
Some tasks require longer than a standard action to perform, typically either one
or more whole turns.  We call these full-turn or multi-turn actions.
</p>

<p>
  A <defn>Full Turn Action</defn> takes a whole turn to complete.  That is one standard
  action, one move action and one minor action.  These actions can be performed in any
  order and they can be started in one turn and finished in another.  <defn>Multi Turn
  Actions</defn> require some number of full turn actions.  For example, a Two-Turn Action
  requires two standard actions, two move actions and two minor actions to complete.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Collective Action</indexentry>
Collective actions allow multiple characters to contribute actions towards a goal.
In these cases all characters that contribute must have the appropriate ability.
The character that contributes the last required action rolls for the check.
Collective actions should have the <defn>collective</defn> keyword.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Interuptable Action</indexentry>
Long Actions may or may not be <defn>interuptable</defn>.  If an action is <emph>interuptable</emph>
characters can perform some part of the action, then do something else, and the return
to the action and continue performing the action without losing previous progress.
If an action is <emph>not interuptable</emph> then any interuption will cause the
action to fail and any progress will be lost.   Multi-turn actions should be assume
<emph>not</emph> to be interruptable unless otherwise stated.
</p>
</subsection>



<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Reactions</subsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Reactions</indexentry>
Under certain circumstances a character will be able to perform an additional
<defn>Reaction</defn> during someone else's action or when a special triggering
event occurs.

Reactions are actions that the GM deems may be performed as a Reaction in a given
context, or any abilities specially labelled as such, <eg/> Shield Block,
Sword Parry, Cloak Fighting and Dodge.  A character may perform at
most one reaction per round.  If two or more characters want to react to an action the
GM decides the reaction order, possibly using an opposed Speed check.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Miscellaneous Actions</subsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Miscellaneous Actions</indexentry>
Miscellaneous actions refer to things that characters do during combat
for which no explicit rules exist, <eg/> reading the runes that close
a magic portal, releasing a portcullis, mounting a horse, quaffing a potion,
pushing a load of barrels over and so on.
</p>

<p>
  For many miscellaneous actions the GM will just have to make a ruling as
  to the check required and the type of action; standard, move or minor: as 
  it would infeasible for us to provide rules for the myriad of
  miscellaneous actions that might occur.  We suggest that the GM rule that
  these are minor actions if they can as it encourages strategic thinking and
  more variety during combat.  You could estimate the time required and work
  out the actions required as follows.. whole turn is 10 seconds, a standard action
  is six seconds, a move action is three seconds, and a minor action is one second.
  Then, if an action will take thirty seconds to perform it will need three whole
  rounds to complete.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Prepared Actions</subsectiontitle>
<p>
  If the character knows that a combat is imminent they may declare that they
  prepare an action.  At that point, at the GMs discretion, the action gains
  a +3 check modifier, <eg/> a prepared arrow shot triggered when someone enters a room
  would gain a +3 bonus to succeed.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Boons and Banes</subsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Combat<subentry>Boons</subentry></indexentry> 
<indexentry>Combat<subentry>Banes</subentry></indexentry> 
Since combat is such a major part of the game the characters will be rolling
Boons and Banes quite often.  The standard Boon for martial abilities
is double damage.  The standard Bane for martial abilities is half damage.
</p>

<p>
  Some suggested boons and banes for use during combat checks
can be found in Tables <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}-defence-fumble</ref>
and <ref>table:{{ doc_name }}-attack-fumble</ref> in the appendix.
</p>
</subsection>


<playexample>
  <p>
    The thugs have returned to the cellars.  Dourli and Roslyn have been unable to 
    escape and now a fight looks inevitable.  It's still dark and our heroes have 
    managed to hide from the thugs so far.  Dourli attacks the thugs from his 
    hidden position attempting to ambush them.  The GM notes that the Thugs will
    be expecting trouble, they are Alert, and so decides the bonus to ambush the
    thugs is reduced to +3.
</p>

<p>
  Dourli tries to get advantage from the <emph>dark</emph> keyword of the cellars and
prepares an attack.   The GM agrees and gives the adventurers a <emph>+1</emph>
arguing that the fact that the thugs were expecting to find Dourli down here would
somewhat negate that advantage. Dourli agrees.
</p>

<p>
  As this is a group delegate check the GM chooses Roslyn to check her Stealth versus
  the thugs Perception DC.  If Roslyn succeeds then the Thugs are ambushed, Roslyn
  and Dourli win initiative and get a free round of attacks, the first attack
  from Dourli gains a bonus to succeed as a prepared action and the thugs must
  make a morale check.
</p>
</playexample>        

<playexample>
  <p>
    Dourli and his ally Roslyn, have been cornered by the local gang leader Fenton 
    One-Eye and two of his thugs.  A fight in the cellar of the Inn has been 
    underway for some number of rounds.  During the fight a few kegs of whisky 
    have been smashed and there is a shallow pool of whisky on the ground.  
</p>

<p>
  One of the thugs attacks Dourli with an Axe Strike I.  Dourli defends with a
  Shield Block 3, since he has rank 3 so he rolls 2D12 with a +3 bonus to his
  block, the attack has a DC of 13 + 1 for the Axe Strike rank.  He needs an
  11 or more on his roll to succeed.  He roll double fours.  That is a failure
  and also a boon.  The GM declares that Dourli takes half damage which for an axe
  is 3 hit points.  That has used Dourlis one reaction for the round.
</p>

<p>
  The second thug tries to stab Dourli with his dagger.  Dourli has no reactions
  left so he has to defend with an Armour save.
</p>
</playexample>      
</section>


<section>
<sectiontitle>Movement and Range</sectiontitle>

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>Miniatures vs Theatre of the Mind</subsectiontitle>

<p>
<indexentry>Movement</indexentry>
<indexentry>Miniatures</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Theatre of the the mind (TOTM)</indexentry> 
<indexentry>TOTM (Theatre of the the mind)</indexentry> 	  
Combat may either be performed on a table with miniatures using a map with a
<defn>Grid</defn>, or purely narratively using the <defn>Theatre of the Mind</defn>, <aka/>
<defn>TOTM</defn>.
</p>

<p>
  If the combat takes place on a grid then the map determines 
  the distances for movement, spell area of effect, missile weapon range etc. 
  On a map a run is simply a double movement, a charge is a movement + d6 extra 
  squares then an attack if the enemy is in range.  Fleeing characters move twice 
  their movement rate +d6 extra squares.
</p>

<p>
  Movement is halved over <defn>difficult terrain</defn>. 
  Difficult terrain includes: muddy ground, rocky ground, and generally any terrain
  with a lot of debris, brambles etc.
</p>        

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Range</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Range</indexentry>
<indexentry>Long Range</indexentry>
<indexentry>Range, Long (-3)</indexentry>
Missile weapons and some spells are ranged actions.

Up to that range the action
is made without any modifiers.  If the ability or weapon has two ranges then the first
is the range at which no range modifiers apply.  The second range is <defn>long range</defn>
for that ability or weapon and the check suffers a <emph>-3 check modifier</emph>.  If
the ability has no second range specified then the ability or weapon cannot be used at
a range greater than the one specified and attempts to do so automatically fail.
</p>
</subsubsection>


{% include "docs/tables/ranges.xml" %}    

{% include "docs/tables/combat_modifiers.xml" %}    

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Cover</subsubsectiontitle>	
<p>
<indexentry>Cover</indexentry>
Cover provides modifiers to checks for most missile weapons and for melee combat.
<defn>Light Cover</defn> afforded by bushes and the like 
gives a -3 check modifier, <defn>Hard Cover</defn>, such as a half wall, 
provides a -6 check modifier.  
<defn>Full Cover</defn> makes hitting the target impossible.  The GM should feel 
free to choose a check modifier that fits the cover available to the characters.
</p>
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Zones of Control</subsubsectiontitle>

<p>
  When playing with TOTM the GM determines whether attacks of opportunity occur.
  When playing on a grid we need a more precise definition.  We define a
  <defn>Zone of Control</defn> as the one square perimeter around the character,
  See Figure<ref>figure:zones</ref>.  The Ogre A is in character X's zone of control,
  Ogre B is not.
</p>

<p>
  We suggest you use a scale where the length of one square in the grid corresponds to
  <measurement><metric>2m</metric><imperial>5'</imperial></measurement>.  This value
  is compatible with other TTRPGs and makes ranged combat sane approximately sane and
  consistent when converting from metric to imperial or vice versa.
</p>



<figure position="h">
  <img id="zones" scale="1.40"/>
<caption>Zones of Control</caption>
<label>figure:zones</label>	
</figure>	  
</subsubsection>

<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Attacks of Opportunity</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  If characters or monsters move past opponents during combat they may
  grant an attack of opportunity which is a standard action made as a reaction
  to the movement.  Disengaging from combat and moving away from combat does
  <emph>not</emph> grant an attack of opportunity.
</p>

<p>	
  A character grants an <defn>Attack of Opportunity</defn> every time the they move
  from one cell in an opponents zone of control into another cell in any opponents zone of
  control.  The attack of opportunity is granted to the opponent whose cell the
  character moves to.  Do not forget the limit of at most one reaction per
  character per Turn.  In Figure<ref>figure:opportunity_attack_simple</ref>, monster A gives
  attacks of opportunity whenever he moves along the arrows in the diagram.
</p>	

<figure position="h">
  <img id="opportunity_attacks_simple" scale="1.4"/>
<caption>Simple Attacks of Opportunity</caption>
<label>figure:opportunity_attacks_simple</label>	
</figure>	


<figure position="h">
  <img id="opportunity_attacks_complex" scale="1.4"/>
<caption>Complex Attacks of Opportunity</caption>
<label>figure:opportunity_attacks_complex</label>	
</figure>	
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Reach</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Reach</indexentry>
Reach weapons, such as spears, are melee weapons with a longer range than most. 
Weapons with reach have the advantage that they grant an Opportunity Attack
when an opponent moves into a characters zone of control.  For example, in
Figure<ref>figure:reach_weapons</ref>, Ogre A gives an attack of opportunity to Character
P whenever he moves along the arrows in the diagram <emph>if character
P is wielding a weapon with the Reach keyword</emph>.	    
</p>
<figure position="h">
  <img id="reach" scale="1.4"/>
<caption>Reach Weapons</caption>
<label>figure:reach_weapons</label>	
</figure>	
</subsubsection>



<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Flanking <label>sec:flanking</label></subsubsectiontitle>

<p>
  When playing using theatre of the mind, whether or not a character is flanked
  is determined by role-playing and GM fiat, <eg/> the GM might require the character
  makes a check to leap over a table to get into a flanking position.
</p>

<p>
  When playing on a grid a character is said to be <defn>Flanked</defn> if he is
  being attacked by two or more opponents from an angle of greater than 90 degrees.
  Attacks on flanked characters gain a +3 check modifier, see
Figure<ref>figure:flanking</ref>
</p>

<figure position="!b">
  <img id="flanking" scale="1.4"/>
<caption>Flanking Examples</caption>
<label>figure:flanking</label>	
</figure>	
</subsubsection>


<subsubsection>
<subsubsectiontitle>Formation</subsubsectiontitle>
<p>
  It is possible to fight in <defn>Formation</defn>.  While fighting in a formation the
  front row provides hard cover to the back row.  The front row must
  have at least as many people in it as the back row.  To make melee
  attacks from the back row you must be using a weapon with reach.
  It is possible for a group to have two front rows, <ie/> to be fighting
  on two fronts, provided that the number of people in each front row
  is greater than or equal to the number of people in the back row.
</p>

<figure position="!b">
  <img id="formation" scale="1.4"/>
<caption>Formation Examples</caption>
<label>figure:formation</label>	
</figure>	
</subsubsection>	
</subsection>           
</section>



<section>
  <sectiontitle>
Non-Lethal Combat <label>sec:non-lethal-combat</label>
<indexentry>Combat<subentry>Non-Lethal Combat</subentry></indexentry> 	
</sectiontitle>

<p>
  There are two categories of combat: Lethal and Non-Lethal.  In Non-Lethal 
  combat the participants are not actively trying to kill their opponents, but 
  rather trying to subdue them or drive them off.  
</p>

<p>
  There is no difference between Lethal and Non-Lethal combat until an opponents
  stamina reaches zero and someone becomes <defn>Bloodied</defn>.  
  At that point a decision has to be made as to whether the combat is lethal or
  non-lethal.  If the combat is non-lethal then the bloodied
  opponent has to willingly withdraw from the combat or make a morale check to
  convert the combat to a Lethal Combat.  So it is possibly for a non-lethal combat
  to become lethal at some point during the combat.  Ultimately the GM decides what
  type of combat is occurring, but as a guide combat between civilized humanoids,
  particularly in	places with established legal systems and prohibitions against
  violence, will be assumed to be non-lethal, at least initially.  Combat against
  monsters and uncivilized humanoids should be considered to be lethal be default.
</p>

<p>
  There is a case where, during a non-lethal combat, a character may have 
  lost most of their stamina,  and are then hit with a big hit and lose all their
  remaining health.  In such a case the normal rules for reduction of health to zero
  apply.  This will probably result in either the combat becoming lethal, or the
  opponents running away.  Weapons with the non-lethal keyword reduce the opponents
  health to one in this case.
</p>

<p>      
  Examples of typical non-lethal combat encounters include fights with the local 
  guards, bar-room brawls, fights with gangs of thugs and bandits.  There are 
  many reasons to use non-lethal combat: killing people is often a capital crime 
  in human society, there are severe social implications when an individual 
  becomes known as a killer, potentially the players might wish to interrogate 
  an opponent, and bandits might want to make money selling people into slavery.
</p>
</section>


<section>
<sectiontitle>NPCs and Monsters in Combat <label>sec:npc_combat</label></sectiontitle>

<p>
  NPCs and monsters behave differently from PCs during combat in the following ways:
  <list>
<li>PCs should automatically win initiative under normal circumstances.</li>
<li>NPC and Monster groups often share a Mettle Pool.</li>
</list>
</p>
</section>

<section>
<sectiontitle>Healing <label>sec:healing</label></sectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Refreshes</indexentry>     
<indexentry>Sleep<subentry>Healing</subentry></indexentry>
<indexentry>Rest<subentry>Healing</subentry></indexentry>
<indexentry>Healing</indexentry>
Characters may heal by taking a long or a short rest.  A <defn>Short Rest</defn> is
a ten minute or more length of time that the characters perform no strenuous activity.
At the end of a short rest the characters regain all their Stamina 
and may refresh one dice pool at their dice pool refresh rate.
</p>

<p>
  A <defn>Long Rest</defn> is a six hour or more length of time that the characters
  sleep.  At the end of a long rest the characters regain all their Stamina, regain
  Health at their Health Heal rate, and refresh dice into their dice pools at twice
  their dice pool refresh rate.   Previously unused short rests can be taken at the
  same time as a long rest.
</p>
</section>    



<section>
<sectiontitle>Other Combat Details<label>sec:combat-details</label></sectiontitle>

<descriptions>
<term>Counter Attack</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Counter Attack</indexentry> 
<label>counter-attack</label>
The character gains an immediate standard melee action as a free action.
</description>

<term>Friendly Fire</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Friendly Fire</indexentry> 
<label>friendly-fire</label>
The character shooting a ranged weapon into melee strikes an ally in that melee.
If there are no allies in the melee the target is involved in, then the attack simply
misses.  If there are more than one allies in the melee then one ally is targeted randomly.
The ally may make a defensive reaction if they have a reaction available.
</description>
</descriptions>
</section>
</chapter>








<chapter>
<chaptertitle>Abilities<label>ch:abilities</label></chaptertitle>

<p>
  This chapter describes abilities available to characters in the game.
<indexentry>Abilities</indexentry>
Each character has a set of <defn>Abilities</defn>.
Abilities may be used in a variety of ways depending on the ability in question.
Some abilities allow the player to perform <defn>Actions</defn> or
<defn>Ability Checks</defn> while others provide the player with passive advantages.
</p>

<p>
  Abilities are keywords and like other keywords, they may be used by the player
  to gain an advantage in an appropriate context.
</p>


<p>
<indexentry>Ability Rank</indexentry>
<indexentry>Rank - Ability</indexentry>
Abilities have ranks. The higher the ability rank the better the character is at that ability
and the easier it is for the character to succeed at those ability checks.  Ability ranks
are written after  the ability.  So, for example, we might say that Dourli has Axe Cleave 3, which means
that he has Axe Cleave at rank 3.  
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Ability Rank - Untrained</indexentry>
<indexentry>Untrained Ability Rank</indexentry>
<indexentry>Rank - Untrained</indexentry>
Some abilities start with an <defn>untrained rank</defn>, often
0 or -3.  Abilities that have an untrained rank can be attempted without training by any
character.  All characters automatically have all untrained abilities but we do not usually
bother to write these down on the character sheet until they reach rank one.

FIXME UNTRAINED ABILITIES (CHECKS?!) SHOULD ALL BE COMMON!!
</p>



<p>
<indexentry>Mastering an Ability</indexentry>
<indexentry>Ability<subentry>Mastery</subentry></indexentry>
You cannot learn an ability unless you have satisfied the prerequisites for that ability.
One prerequisite for gaining ability ranks
is mastery of the previous rank of the ability.  That is, in order to gain rank 2
of an ability, rank 1 must first be mastered.  In order to master the ability the
player must have successfully used the ability before.  All untrained abilities
are considered to be automatically mastered already as untrained means the character
has no experience in the ability. The first time an unmastered ability is used the
character should mark off the success on their character sheet.
</p>

<p>
  When the character goes up a level they gain promotions in certain classes of abilities
  up to certain ranks.  For example a character might gain the following promotions:
  Martial<leqqsymbol/>3, Hammer<leqqsymbol/>4, Transport or Craft<leqqsymbol/>6.  What
  this means is that the character can raise the rank of any one ability from the Martial
  section up to a maximum rank of 3 provided that they have satisfied all of that
  ability ranks prerequisites.  The only time prerequisite requirements are waivered is
  when the text states that the character gains an ability at a given rank.
</p>

<p>
  All abilities have a type.  The type of the ability is mainly used to determine when
  and if an ability can be used during combat.  All abilities have one of the following
  types: reaction, standard, minor, move, immediate, non-combat, keyword.  We discuss ability
  types further in the section on combat.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Default Difficulty</indexentry>
<indexentry>Passive Skill</indexentry>
<indexentry>DDC (Default Difficulty)</indexentry>
<indexentry>Skill<subentry>DDC</subentry></indexentry>
<indexentry>Skill<subentry>Passive</subentry></indexentry>
<indexentry>Skill<subentry>Default Difficulty</subentry></indexentry>
All abilities have a Default Difficulty, DDC.  This is a completely non-binding
suggestion to the GM for the difficulty that might be used for checks associated with
this skill.  Abilities with a DDC of 0 are passive.  This means that the the effects of
the ability always apply, and that their is no way to successfully make checks with
this ability.  It follows that there is no way to promote such abilities.  Most DDC 0
abilities are reserved for monsters.
</p>


{% from "docs/macro_ability.xml" import build_ability with context %}


{% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_primary_family() %}
<section>
<sectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}<indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Primary</subentry></indexentry>
</sectiontitle>
{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

{% if ability_group.has_abilities() and ability_group.draw_skill_tree() %}
<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
<caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
<label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
</figure>
{% endif %}

{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
{{ build_ability(ability) }}
{% endfor %}
</section>
{% endfor %}


<!-- {% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_common_family() %} -->
<!-- <subsection> -->
<!-- 	<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle> -->
<!-- 	{{ ability_group.get_description() }} -->

<!-- 	{% if ability_group.has_abilities() and ability_group.draw_skill_tree() %} -->
<!-- 	<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false"> -->
<!-- 	  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/> -->
<!-- 	  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption> -->
<!-- 	  <label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label> -->
<!-- 	</figure> -->
<!-- 	{% endif %} -->

<!-- 	{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%} -->
<!-- 	{{ build_ability(ability) }} -->
<!-- 	{% endfor %} -->
<!-- </subsection> -->
<!-- {% endfor %} -->


<section>
<sectiontitle>Scholarly Abilities</sectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Scholarly</subentry></indexentry>
represents the ``book-learning'' a character has received, how much knowledge
they have accumulated.  This includes abilities like Antiquarian,
Natural History, Alchemy, and the like.
</p>


{% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_lore_family() %}
<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

{% if ability_group.has_abilities() %}
<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
<caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
<label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
</figure>
{% endif %}

{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
{{ build_ability(ability) }}
{% endfor %}
</subsection>
{% endfor %}


{% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_wyrd_science_family() %}
<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

{% if ability_group.has_abilities() %}
<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
<caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
<label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
</figure>
{% endif %}

{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
{{ build_ability(ability) }}
{% endfor %}
</subsection>
{% endfor %}

</section>


<section>
<sectiontitle>Martial Abilities </sectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Abilities<subentry>Martial</subentry></indexentry>
represents combat related physical skills, e.g. Axe Strike, Shield Block.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Opponents<subentry>Defence</subentry></indexentry>
Many martial abilities have a DC based on the Opponents Defence, this means
the targets Block, Parry, Armour or other defensive ability check amount or difficulty.
<indexentry>Opponents<subentry>Attack</subentry></indexentry>  Other
martial abilities are checked against a DC based on the opponents attack.
This represents that attack skill check result or DC for the opponent.	 For
example a monster may attack a character with a Sword with an attack with DC 15.
The PC then uses the monsters attack DC as the Opponents Attack DC in any defensive
skill the character uses against the attack.
</p>


{% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_martial_family() %}

<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

{% if ability_group.has_abilities() %}
<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
<label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
</figure>
{% endif %}

{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
{{ build_ability(ability) }}
{% endfor %}
</subsection>
{% endfor %}
</section>

<section>
<sectiontitle>General Abilities</sectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Abilities<subentry>General</subentry></indexentry>
These abilities represent trade-craft and creative abilities: Smithing,
Animal Handling, Playing Music, Hunting and so on.
</p>

{% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_general_family() %}
<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>
  {{ ability_group.get_description() }}

  {% if ability_group.has_abilities() and ability_group.draw_skill_tree() %}
  <figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
    <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
<caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
<label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
</figure>
{% endif %}

{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
{{ build_ability(ability) }}
{% endfor %}	
</subsection>
{% endfor %}
</section>


<section>
<sectiontitle>Magic Abilities</sectiontitle>
<p>
  Magic abilities involve the use of the characters magic pool and
  are only available to certain archetypes.
</p>

{% for ability_group in ability_groups if ability_group.is_magic_family() %}
<subsection>
<subsectiontitle>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</subsectiontitle>

{{ ability_group.get_description() }}

{% if ability_group.has_abilities() %}
<figure position="h" fullwidth="false" sideways="false">
  <img src="./build/{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree.eps" scale="0.75"/>
  <caption>{{ ability_group.get_title() }}</caption>
<label>figure:{{ ability_group.get_id() }}_skill_tree</label>
</figure>
{% endif %}

{% for ability in ability_group.get_abilities()%}
{{ build_ability(ability) }}
{% endfor %}
</subsection>
{% endfor %}
</section>
</chapter>



<chapter>
<chaptertitle>Keywords and Conditions<label>ch:keywordsandconditions</label></chaptertitle>


<section>
<sectiontitle>Keywords</sectiontitle>
<p>
<indexentry>Keyword</indexentry> 
A <defn>Keyword</defn> is a tag, label or signifier attached to something in the game.
A cellar might be <emph>dark</emph> and <emph>musty</emph>, or a monster's attack
might be <emph>cold</emph>.  
</p>

<p>
  <indexentry>Keywords</indexentry>	
  The use of many keywords in game tends to be informal.
  If the GM describes a cellar as being dark then we say it has the keyword <emph>dark</emph>.
  Some keywords are more concretely defined.  A dwarven character has the keyword <emph>dwarf</emph>.
  Keywords form a bridge between informal narrative gameplay and the formal game rules.
</p>

<p>	
  Various rules apply only when certain keywords are in play.  Other events apply new keywords
  to characters, objects and scenarios in the game.  Characters may use keywords to gain
  an advantage in a check.  Keywords may also be prerequisites for using abilities, or used to describe
  weapon damage types, properties that effect magic use, monster classes <etc/>
</p>


<p>
  Some illustrative examples of keyword use follow:
</p>
<descriptions>
<term>Damage Types</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Damage Types</indexentry>
<eg/> fire, cold, crushing, iron <ellipsis/>
</description>


<term>Racial Categories</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Racial Categories</indexentry> 
<eg/> dwarf, elf, human, halfling, greenskin <ellipsis/>
</description>


<term>Environmental Descriptions</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Environmental Descriptions</indexentry> 
<eg/> damp, dark, cold, slimy, smokey, foggy <ellipsis/>
</description>
</descriptions>


<playexample>
  <p>
    Dourli hides from a local gang of thugs in a cellar.  The GM describes the 
    cellar as dark and dank and storing old barrels.  The thugs enter the cellar 
    and look around.   Dourli invokes the <emph>dark</emph> keyword from the GMs
    description of the cellar saying <emph>``They'll have trouble seeing me in the
    dark''</emph>.  The GM agrees and gives Dourli a bonus to his Stealth check.
</p>
</playexample>
</section>    




<section>
<sectiontitle>Common Conditions and Effects<label>sec:conditions</label></sectiontitle>

<p>
  A <defn>Condition</defn> is a type of keyword that has a well-defined game effect attached to it.
  All conditions are keywords, but not all keywords are conditions.  Conditions represent
  temporary modifications to things in game, often to characters, <eg/> Blind, or Dazed.
</p>

<p>
<indexentry>Condition<subentry>Save Ends</subentry></indexentry> 
<indexentry>Save Ends</indexentry>
Conditions have different lifetimes.  Some conditions typically last for the length of a combat,
or until a <bold>Save Ends</bold> the effects of the condition.  Other conditions might be ongoing
and terminate at different times. How and when a PC can save to end a condition should be
specified on a per condition, or per instance basis.  For example text might say:
If the character has a fishing net dropped on them they are Prone Agility Save ends with a
DC of 12.  Saves are made at the end of the characters turn and, if they have multiple
saves to make, in any order the character wishes.
</p>

<p>
  The following is a list of some common conditions.
</p>      

<descriptions>
<term>Alert</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Alert Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Alert</subentry></indexentry>
<label>condition:alert</label>
The character is alert for danger.  They are less likely to be surprised.
They gain +2 to Awareness checks.  It is difficult to stay alert for long periods
of time. PCs cannot claim to be alert for hours on end.  Something has to happen to
alert them.  For example, guards are typically not alert, infiltrators typically are alert.
If a group makes a lot of noise, <eg/> due to combat, then other groups nearby will
become alert.
</description>

<term>Aware</term>
<description>
<label>defn:aware</label>
<indexentry>Aware Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Aware</subentry></indexentry>
A character or group is Aware if they believe that they could come into confrontation imminently.


One character or group is Aware of another if they make a successful Perception or Listen check
against their opponents Stealth. or if the GM determines they are Aware.  If this check fails
then the character or group are Unaware.
<emph>Typically groups will be aware of one another unless one side has approached the other
stealthily, or unless one side is laying in ambush.  For groups the GM should use a Delegated
Group Check</emph>.  The awareness check can be modified if individuals have the Alert Condition
see page<pageref>condition:alert</pageref>
</description>

<term>Black-Powder</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Black-Powder</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Keywords<subentry>Black-Powder</subentry></indexentry>
<label>keyword:black-powder</label>
Black-Powder weapons misfire on a bane.
</description>

<term>Blind</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Blind Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Blind</subentry></indexentry>
The character cannot see.  Ambush, Surprise, Initiative, Attack Roles,
Dodge, Parry and Block receive a -6 modifier against all opponents.
</description>

<!-- <term>Cascade</term> -->
<!-- <description> -->
<!-- <indexentry>Cascade Keyword</indexentry>  -->
<!-- <indexentry>Keywords<subentry>Cascade</subentry></indexentry> -->
<!-- <label>keyword:cascade</label> -->
<!-- When a check with the <emph>cascade</emph> keyword is successful, -->
<!-- the check can be repeated any number of times within the round, -->
<!-- provided the action economy allows it. -->
<!-- </description> -->



<term>Bloodied</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Bloodied Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Bloodied</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has suffered damage to their Health.  When a character first
suffers health damage in a fight they must make a Mettle Check.
</description>    

<term>Broken</term>
<description>
<label>condition:broken</label>
<indexentry>Broken Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Broken</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has lost the will to fight and must withdraw from battle.
On their turn they may attack but may not move into melee combat unless
they have no other choice.  This condition occurs after a character
has failed two Mettle Checks in combat.
</description>

<term>Burning</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Burning Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Burning</subentry></indexentry>
The character is on fire.  They must attempt to put out the fire or make
a Mettle Check each round to resist doing so.
</description>

<term>Checked</term>
<description>
<label>condition:checked</label>
<indexentry>Checked Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Checked</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has lost momentum in a fight. The character must make a
Mettle Check to charge or pursue.  This condition occurs after the
character has failed a single Mettle Check in combat.
</description>

<term>Dazed</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Dazed Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Dazed</subentry></indexentry>	  
The character receives a -2 modifer to all Checks.
This often occurs when the character has suffered a nasty injury and are
suffering a great deal of pain.  Condition lasts for 3 rounds or until a
DC 13 Endurance Check is made.
</description>

<term>Distracted</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Distracted Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Distracted</subentry></indexentry>       
Something has caught the characters attention and they are not paying
attention to their surrounds.  They make Ambush, Surprise, Missile Attacks, and 
Perception Checks at -2.
</description>    

<term>Deaf</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Deaf Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Deaf</subentry></indexentry>       
The character cannot hear.  They make checks Ambush, Surprise,
Perception Checks at -2 and have some trouble communicating with others,
use Language Checks to determine success.	  
</description>

<term>Down</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Down Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Down</subentry></indexentry>
Characters who are down are effectively too hurt and too weak to defend themselves or do too
much and are in danger of dying.  Characters who are Down may make a Mettle Check to make a minor
action each turn.  Combatants will tend to leave Downed opponents alone until
the end of combat when they can be dispatched, eaten, saved for later, ransomed or sold into
slavery.  Most Down characters also have the Prone condition.
</description>	

<term>Drunk</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Drunk Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Drunk</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has had too much alcohol to drink.  They make Agility and Perception
checks at -2 and they make Luck Checks at +2.  A character that is very drunk makes
Agility and Perception checks at -4 and Luck Checks at +2.
</description>

<term>Enraged</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Enraged Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Enraged</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is wild with rage.  They must make a melee attack each round, if
they can.  If they fail to make a melee attack they are no longer enraged.
Otherwise, they must make a Mettle Check to lose this condition.
</description>

<term>Exhausted</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Exhausted Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Exhausted</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is very tired.  Make Strength, Endurance, Speed and Movement
checks at -2.
</description>

<term>Fast</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Fast Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Fast</subentry></indexentry>       
The NPC forces an Initiative Check when first attacked.  The GM should
not assume the PCs go first when fighting these characters with the Fast
condition.
</description>

<term>Fearless</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Fearless Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Fearless</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has no fear and automatically succeeds any Mettle Checks.
</description>    

<term>Flanked</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Flanked Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Flanked</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is being attacked from multiple sides simultaneously.
This drastically reduces their ability to defend themselves and they
suffer -2 to their Armour Checks while flanked.  See 
Section<ref>sec:flanking</ref> on page<pageref>sec:flanking</pageref>
</description>

<term>Focused</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Focused Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Focused</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is well prepared for a ranged attack. +3 to ranged attacks.
</description>

<term>Free</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Free Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Keywords<subentry>Free</subentry></indexentry>
Free checks have no point pool cost.
</description>    

<term>Held</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Held/Hold Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Keywords<subentry>Held/Hold</subentry></indexentry>
This condition refers to the magical effect, and not to physical restraint.
A Held creature may not make melee attacks against the Holder and they
may not move closer to the holder at any time while held.
</description>    


<term>Immune[Damage-Type-Keywords<ellipsis/>]</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Immune[] Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Immune[]</subentry></indexentry>
The character takes no damage if they are immune to that type of damage.
For example, if a character is Immune[Fire] and they take 7 points of
damage keyword with Fire then they take no damage.
</description>

<term>Immobilized</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Immobilized Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Immobilized</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has a great deal of trouble moving.  They must make
an Agility Check, Speed or Strength check vs DC 13 each round or they
cannot move.  Whether they succeed or fail, their move distance is reduced by 3.
</description>	

<term>Invisible</term>    
<description>
<indexentry>Invisible Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Invisible</subentry></indexentry>       
same as if others were blinded in actions that include the character.
Initiative, Attack Roles, Dodge, Parry and Block against this
character all receive a -6 modifier.
</description>

<term>Maintain</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Maintain Keyword</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Keywords<subentry>Maintain</subentry></indexentry>
<label>keyword:maintain</label>
This spell ability requires the character to expend a minor action 
round to maintain the effect for every subsequent round.
</description>


<term>Natural Sprinters</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Natural-Sprinter Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Natural-Sprinters</subentry></indexentry>
While slow to get moving, the character can build up a fair
amount of speed in a straight line over time.   The character gains
+1 move <emph>distance</emph> while running.
</description>    

<term>Near-Death</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Near-Death Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Near-Death</subentry></indexentry>
The player must make rolls on the Near-Death table for the character
each round until the condition is removed of their character dies.
Characters who are Near-Death also have the Down condition and usually
will have the Prone condition as well.
</description>

<term>Off-Guard</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Off-Guard Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Off Guard</subentry></indexentry>
The character is put off by events around them.  All melee combat rolls
for the next round are made by the character are made at disadvantage.
</description>


<term>Ongoing</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Ongoing Keyword</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Keywords<subentry>Ongoing</subentry></indexentry>
<label>keyword:ongoing</label>
When a check with the <emph>ongoing</emph> keyword is successful,
the check may be repeated every subsequent round until it fails.
</description>

<term>Prone</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Prone Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Prone</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is on the ground.  Performs physical checks at -3.
Melee attacks are made against the character with Advantage.
Missile attacks are made against the character at Disadvantage.
Standing up costs 3 movement.
</description>

<term>Pushed[N-Squares]</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Pushed Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Pushed</subentry></indexentry>
The character is pushed back N-Squares (N=1 square if not specified).
NPCs with Plot-Armour can make a DC 12 Strength Save to avoid the push.
</description>

<term>Poisoned</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Poisoned Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Poisoned</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is suffering from terrible pain in the stomach or some form of
paralysis.  They must make a mettle check in order to perform any action.
</description>    

<term>Resistant[Damage-Type-Keywords<ellipsis/>]</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Resistant[] Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Resistant[]</subentry></indexentry>
The character has all damage decreased by 50<percent/> of its normal damage.
For example, if a character is Resistant[Fire] and they take 6 points of
damage keyword with Fire then they would take an 3 fewer damage.  The 
damage is removed after any boon, bane or other modifier. 
</description>    

<term>Routed</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Routed Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Routed</subentry></indexentry>
The character has been defeated in combat.  If they can Flee they do so.
Otherwise they will attempt to yield or do something desperate.  This occurs
when the player has failed three Mettle Checks in combat.
</description>

<term>Sick</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Sick Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Sick</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is feverish and light headed?  They perform a mettle
check at the start of each turn in combat and if they fail they perform
checks that turn at -3.
</description>

<term>Slowed</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Slowed Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Slowed</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has trouble moving.  They must make
an Agility Check, Speed or Strength check vs DC 11 each round or their
move distance is reduced by 3.
</description>

<term>Stunned</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Stunned Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Stunned</subentry></indexentry>
The character is stunned and gets one action per round.  Lasts one round.
</description>

<term>Tired</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Tired Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Tired</subentry></indexentry>       
The character is tired.  Make Strength, Speed and Movement checks at -3.
</description>

<term>Unaware</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Unaware Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Unaware</subentry></indexentry>
See the description of Aware in the Surprise section on page<pageref>sec:aware</pageref>.
If a character is not Unaware they are Aware.
</description>

<term>Unconscious</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Unconscious Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Unconscious</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has blacked out or been otherwise incapacitated due to a
stunning blow to the head or too much pain.  They are not necessarily in immediate
danger to their lives. They can perform no actions.
</description>

<term>Ungainly</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Ungainly Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Ungainly</subentry></indexentry>       
creature that has trouble turning and changing direction.
must make a move turn in the same direction as the charge straight
after making the charge.      
</description>

<term>Unsteady</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Unsteady Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Unsteady</subentry></indexentry>       
The character has been knocked off balance.  This condition lasts for
one turn.  The character defends with disadvantage, and movement is halved.
</description>    

<term>Vulnerable[Damage-Type-Keywords<ellipsis/>]</term>
<description>
<indexentry>Vunerable[] Condition</indexentry> 
<indexentry>Conditions<subentry>Vunerable[]</subentry></indexentry>
The character has all damage increased by 50<percent/> of its normal damage.
For example, if a character is Vulernable[Fire] and they take 6 points of
damage with the Fire keyword then they would take an extra 3 damage.  The extra
damage is added after any boon, bane or other modifier. 
</description>    
</descriptions>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<chaptertitle>Equipment</chaptertitle>
{% include "docs/fragment_equipment_list.xml" %}
</chapter>

<chapter>
<chaptertitle>License</chaptertitle>
{% include "docs/fragment_license.xml" %}
</chapter>


<chapter>
<chaptertitle>Tables</chaptertitle>


{% include "docs/tables/check_dcs.xml" %}

{% include "docs/tables/misfortune_missile_attack.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/misfortune_defence.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/misfortune_magic.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/misfortune_misc.xml" %}

{% include "docs/tables/near_death_table.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/wound_table.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/misfortune.xml" %}
{% include "docs/tables/misfortune2.xml" %}
<!-- FIRE & ACID -->
<!-- FALLING -->
<!-- DROWNING & SUFFICATION -->
<!-- POISON -->
<!-- COLD -->

</chapter>


{% if add_index_to_core %}
<index/>
{% endif %}
</book>

