<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  <titlepage>
    <vspace>2</vspace>
    <title>Malleus Deum</title>  
    <vspace>6</vspace>
    <img src="resources/dragon_title/dragon.jpg" scale="0.6"/>
    <vspace>6</vspace>
    <subtitle>Igitur qui desiderat pacem, praeparet bellum.</subtitle>
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <author>Blaize A. Rhodes</author>
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <author>William F. Rhodes</author>
    <vspace>1</vspace>
    <version>{{ db.version }}</version>
  </titlepage>


  <tableofcontents/>  

  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Game Balance and Design Philosophy</chaptertitle>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Motivation and Design</sectiontitle>      
      <p>
        This game has the following design goals:
      </p>

      <olist>
        <li>
          <p>
            The authors believe that the big name RPGs are showing their age.  Dungeons
            and Dragons is now 40 years old.  While there are a large number of indie rpgs
            that have explored interesting new rpg design elements, Dungeons and Dragons
            has remained relatively static, its development ossified by negative feedback
            to changes from its large existing fan-base.  These rules represent a response
            to this state of affairs.  
          </p>    
          
          <p>
            Malleus Deum is an attempt at a <emph>modern</emph> rule set.  It  
            tries to integrate advances in RPG rule design into an otherwise traditional RPG 
            rules system.  Specifically we try to include an Aspect-like mechanic from FATE, 
            linear magic-users like 13th age and Dnd5e, a strategic initiative phase from Dr 
            Who to encourage non-combat resolutions, simple unified resolutions, morale,
            and adding benefits and complications to dice results.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            In this game we are trying to deemphasize combat.  Not remove it.  But
            take an opportunity to try and provide rules that will allow the GM
            to shine the light on other parts of the game: negotiation, morale,
            fleeing and pursuit, investigation and personal development.
          </p>

          <p>
            It's nice to have a change in pace and scenery.  We have tried to design a
            game where combat plays a major role, but other aspects of the game, such
            as role-playing, negotiation, non-lethal combat, and investigation, are also
            a possibility.
          </p>
        </li>
        
        <li>
          <p>
            We feel it is important for users of the game that the game license allow people
            to contribute to the game on their own terms and have, therefore, released the
            game under the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0, which is available 
            online.  In a nutshell, you are free, to: 
            <list>
              <li>Share — to copy, distribute and transmit the work, to</li>
              <li>Remix — to adapt the work, and to</li>
              <li>Make commercial use of the work</li>
            </list>
            
            Under the following conditions:
            <list>
              <li>Attribution — You must attribute the work in the manner specified by 
              the author, but not in any way that suggests that they endorse you 
              or your use of the work.  
              </li>
            </list>
          </p>

	  <p>
	    All creative commons licenses require attribution.  We suspect it may have
	    something to do with establishing the provenance of the license.
	  </p>	    
        </li>      
        

        <li>
          <p>
            Modular and Customizable: Our goal is that you should be able to include the bits 
            you want, exclude the bits you do not, customize whatever you like, add whatever 
            house rules you like, then build your own set of rule books and modules and
            print them.
          </p>

          <p>
            Modularity also makes maintaining balance in an evolving game easier
            as some parts of the system can be tweaked without effecting other parts.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Moderately heavy-weight rules complexity means that the rules are a little more 
            complicated than, for example, FATE, FUDGE, Basic Dnd, or Call of Cthulhu and a 
            little less complicated than say DnD4e.   Combat needs to be easy enough that 
            GMs can throw challenging encounters together on the fly.  But the rules for 
            character progression need to be rich enough to capture and keep the imagination
            of the players.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Geared to a low magic setting.  At high level magic becomes difficult to GM
            with a myriad of unforeseen interactions and unintended consequences.  In the
            authors opinion, there are also problems with game balance in high fantasy
            settings.  As George Martin said: ``If you look at The Lord of the Rings, what
            strikes you, it certainly struck me, is that although the world is infused with
            this great sense of magic, there is very little onstage magic. So you have a
            sense of magic, but it's kept under very tight control.''.  We also refer the
            interested reader to Sandersons Rules of Magic.
          </p>
        </li>

        <li>
          <p>
            Malleus Deum is designed specifically for fantasy settings.  We feel that generic
	    role playing systems do not fit any milieu particularly well - they are the jacks
	    of all trades and masters of none.
          </p>
        </li>
	
        <li>
          <p>
            We hope to develop this game via a process of gradual incremental improvement.
	    There is a constraint on the corporate model of RPG development where each new
	    version of the rules has to be significantly different from previous versions
	    otherwise they cannot justify the prices they charge for the new books or resell
	    you the same modules.  An open source model has no such constraints.  We hope
	    that an open approach will allow a slow process of identifying problem areas with
	    the rules and fine-tuning those rules in a slow and incremental process.
          </p>	  
        </li>


        <li>
          <p>
	    The default milieu for the game draws elements from the standard fantasy sources:
	    Lord of the Rings, Conan the Barbarian, Dungeons and Dragons, and Warhammer and
	    also some slightly unusual sources: Jim Butchers Dresden Files, Charles Stross's
	    Laundry Files and Lovecraft.  
          </p>
        </li>
        
      </olist>

      <p>
	We hope you enjoy the game.
      </p>

      <!--
          <figure position="!b">
          <img src="./resources/werewolf2.jpg" scale="0.7"/>
          </figure>
      -->
    </section>    
    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Design Principles</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	Good game design requires a balanced mechanical foundation.
	In this chapter we lay out the design principles we use to try to
	ensure compelling game play and good game balance.  In later sections we will
	apply those principles to individual game mechanics.
      </p>


      

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Simplicity</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
	  We do not believe that complex game mechanics are necessary for good gameplay.
	  Keeping the number and complexity of the game mechanics of the game small
	  makes for a faster, easier and more enjoyable game to play.
	</p>

	<principle>
	  <principletitle>Simplicity</principletitle>
	  <label>Simplicity</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    Keep the number of mechanics to a minimum.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Operant Conditioning</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
	  Behavioural psychology, and more specifically, operant conditioning,
	  suggests that the best training schedule is one with random positive
	  reinforcement and not continuous feedback.  What that means in English
	  is that random stepped increases in player character advancement is
	  <emph>``more fun''</emph> than gradual continuous improvement or improvement
	  at fixed times.
	</p>

	<principle>
	  <principletitle>Random Reinforcement</principletitle>
	  <label>Random Reinforcement</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    Character progression should increase in large and infrequent semi-random
	    discrete steps, and not gradually.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Game Theory</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
	  It has been claimed that a well designed game presents players with problems
	  that force them to make	interesting decisions.   Game Theory has the concept
	  of a dominant strategy.  If a problem has a dominant strategy then there is
	  a solution to that problem that is clearly better than all the rest.  If
	  a game has problems have dominant strategies then they are not forcing players
	  to make interesting decisions.  
	</p>

	<principle>
	  <principletitle>Avoid Dominant Strategies</principletitle>
	  <label>Avoid Dominant Strategies</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    We should strive to provide choices to players that do not have any clearly
	    better general-purpose solution when creating, developing and playing his
	    character.  Force the characters to make meaningfull choices.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Succeed more than you Fail</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  Let us define the playable range for standard check dice mechanics to be the range
	  of values that have a probability from, say, 30<percent/> to 80<percent/>.  This
	  represents the range that <emph>most</emph> but not all checks should be in to
	  make for an interesting game.
	</p>

	<p>
	  If players have more than an 80<percent/> chance of
	  succeeding, then play becomes a little too easy and monotonous.  If players have
	  less than a 30<percent/> chance of succeeding then play becomes frustrating.  This
	  range is a little arbitrary but good enough for the purposes of this discussion.
	</p>
	
	<principle>
	  <principletitle>Playable Range</principletitle>
	  <label>Playable Range</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    Checks have a playable range which is not too hard and not too easy.
	    Most checks in the game should fall in the playable range.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
	
	<p>
	  Furthermore, experience suggests that, on the whole, players prefer to succeed in
	  their checks more than they fail, by which we mean that the typical
	  probability of success should be in the range 50-70<percent/>.
	</p>

	<principle>
	  <principletitle>Succeed more than you Fail</principletitle>
	  <label>Succeed more than you Fail</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    On average, checks should succeed more often than fail.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Make Players Roll</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  We will steal an idea from DungeonWorld and Numenera and make players roll
	  for defence when they are being attacked.  This will keep them busy and engaged
	  and free up time for the GM.
	</p>      
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Archetypes Differentiation</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
    	  The character archetypes should feel different to play and
    	  have strengths and weaknesses to provide variety and tactical
	  options during game play.  For the purposes of discussion we can break
	  the archetypes into four groups: Tanks, Damagers Support (Controllers, Healers, etc)
	  and Generalists.
	</p>

	<p>
	  We expect that the Tanks should be more defensive than the other classes, the
	  Damagers should do more damage.  Support should be sub-optimal in the
	  damaging and defense roles but have additional strategic and/or buffing options
	  available to them during combat.

	  The Generalists are specialized non-combatants.  We introduce them because 
	  we are trying to deemphasize combat.  At the same time we want the generalists to 
	  have reasonable options within combat and be able to be reasonably
	  effective otherwise combat is boring for these archetypes.  To this end it is
	  important that the generalists performance in combat is worse than that of
	  the combat specialists, but not drastically so.  We need to define an envelope
	  within which there is a difference between combat ability, but that difference
	  is not so great that the generalists feel left out of combat.
	</p>
	
	<principle>
    	  <principletitle></principletitle>
    	  <label>Archetype Differentiation</label>
    	  <principlebody>
	    Archetypes should be either specialists, strong in one area and weak in
	    others or generalists that are somewhat competent in combat.
    	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>	
	<subsectiontitle>Monster Combat Classes</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  We will give monsters a very similar combat classification to those used by Dnd 4e
	  as it introduces a nice level of strategy to combat.  Each monster
	  has a level and a combat role: Grunt, Brute, Soldier, Artillery, Elite, Skirmisher,
	  Lurker, or Elite.  In addition they can have a hybrid role, i.e.  Solo, Controller,
	  or Leader that augments their role in combat.
	</p>

	<descriptions>

	  <term>Grunts</term>
	  <description>are the typical foot soldier type monster.
	  </description>

	  <term>Brutes</term>
	  <description>are the monster equivalent of Damagers.  They have higher
	  damage and hit points than grunts, and a lower armour class.
	  </description>

	  <term>Elites</term>
	  <description>
	    are like Brutes but get two or more attacks.  They are the sergeants or
	    the second in command types.
	  </description>
	  
	  <term>Soldiers</term>
	  <description>
	    are the monster equivalent of tanks. They have higher AC than the Grunts,
	    and have similar HP and damage.  They might have abilities that make them sticky.
	  </description>

	  <term>Artillery</term>
	  <description>
	    are ranged attackers with lower ACs and HPs than Grunts.
	  </description>

	  <term>Lurkers</term>
	  <description>
	    typically have lower HP and AC than Grunts but they have special abilities
	    that allow them to avoid detection.
	  </description>
	  
	  <term>Skirmishers
	  </term>
	  <description>
	    have similar HP and AC as Grunts.  They may do higher damage and they have
	    abilities that grant them extra mobility.
	  </description>
	</descriptions>


	<p>
	  The hybrid roles include the following:
	</p>

	<descriptions>

	  <term>Controllers </term>
	  <description>
	    have the same kinds of abilities as their PC analogs.  They are able to buff
	    their side, or debuff their opponents, allow their allies to move unhindered
	    across the battlefield, etc. 
	  </description>	  
	  
	  <term>Leaders</term>
	  <description>
	    have abilities that let them control their own troops or intimidate their
	    opponents.  They might be considered a special subtype of controller.
	  </description>
	  
	  <term>Solos</term>
	  <description>
	    Solos are monsters that can fight a party of adventurers on their own.  They
	    have similar AC to the Grunts but a lot more HP, they do a lot more damage and
	    they should have multiple attacks and possibly special abilities.
	  </description>	 	  
	</descriptions>	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Level Equivalence</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  To make it easy to compare monster and PC strengths monsters and characters
	  of the same level should have similar AC and do similar damage.  Monsters
	  will typically have fewer HP.
	</p>      
      </subsection>      

    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Game Mechanics</sectiontitle>
      
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Standard Checks</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
	  It follows from Principle<ref>Succeed more than you Fail</ref> that for
	  standard checks, such as to-hit rolls, there is a finite
	  range of values within the 2d12 or 2-24 range that are reasonable and enjoyable
	  to choose for difficulty values.
	</p>

	{% include "docs/tables/probabilities_2d12.xml" %}
	
	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/std_check_2d12_vs_d20.png" scale="0.45"/>
	  <caption>To Hit Probabilities 2d12 vs d20</caption>
	  <label>figure:tohit2d12vsd20</label>
	</figure>

	<p>
	  Based on the following graph, see Figure<ref>figure:tohit2d12vsd20</ref> and
	  Table<ref>table:probabilities_2d12</ref>,
	  we can see that the playable range, with a success rate of 30-80<percent/>
	  for a 2d12 mechanic is about 11 to 18 with a difference of 7.  The playable range
	  for 1d20 is 7 to 17 with a difference of 10.  It follows that bonuses to Std
	  Checks, must be smaller than equivalent bonuses in a d20 system, <eg/> a +2 bonus
	  in a d20 system like DnD is roughly equivalent to a +3 bonus in a 2d12 system.
	  A +4 bonus in a d20 system is roughly equivalent to a +5 bonus in a 2d12 system.
	</p>

	<principle>
	  <principletitle>Std Checks Bonuses should be at most +4</principletitle>
	  <label>Bonuses for Std Checks should be at Most +4</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    Because the 2d12 checks have a smaller playable range than d20 systems
	    the maximum, unadjusted, difference for a standard check bonus between
	    any two archetypes at the same level should be less than or equal to +4.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>      

	<p>
	  Note that the average result for 2d12 is also higher, 13 in our 2d12 system
	  versus 10.5 in a d20 system.
	</p>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Dice Pools</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  Dice pool mechanics are used for a number of different things Magic, Mettle, and
	  Luck.  Here we take a quick look at dice pool behaviour.  In Table
	  <ref>dicepools</ref> we provide a range of difficulties
	  (and overcharge values for spells).  Assuming that dedicated first level spell casters
	  can cast a few spells before replenishing their dice pools it follows, from Table
	  <ref>figure:dicepools</ref>, that their dice pools should contain about 2 to 3
	  dice which will allow them to cast six to nine difficulty 3 spells.  Further,
	  suppose we wish a 10th level caster to be able to cast a similar number of
	  difficulty 14 spells, then their dice pool size should be about 6 to 9 dice.
	</p>

	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/dice_pools.png" scale="0.18"/>
	  <caption>Dice Pool Difficulties vs Number of Dice Rolled</caption>
	  <label>figure:dicepools</label>
	</figure>

	{% include "docs/tables/dice_pool_cost.xml" %}
      </subsection>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <sectiontitle>PC Attacks</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>PC To-Hit Checks</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  To-Hit rolls are basically a kind of Std Check. Consequently, the same narrower
	  playable range applies to the to-hit rolls of different classes.  We aim to
	  have a reasonable small difference in combat ability between generalist classes
	  and combat specialist classes in Malleus Deum.  It would seem that in order to
	  have the generalist characters be able to enjoy combat <emph>the to-hit bonus
	  difference between generalists and combat specialists should be no more than
	  3 for characters of the same level</emph>.
	</p>

	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/to_hit_bonus_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	  <caption>PC To Hit Bonus by Level</caption>
	  <label>figure:to_hit_bonus_by_level</label>
	</figure>      
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Monster Armour Class</subsectiontitle>	
	<p>
          For a typical monster of the samel level PC Combat classes should hit
	  on average two in three times.  Non combatants should hit 
          ever slightly less frequently.  Monster armour classes then flow from
	  the desired hit ratio and the PC per level to hit table.
	</p>

	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/monster_ac_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	  <caption>Monster AC by Level</caption>
	  <label>figure:monster_ac_by_level</label>
	</figure>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>PC Damage</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
	  We can choose the amount of damage PCs deal fairly arbitrarily and scale other
	  game mechanics accordingly (such as monster and PC hit points).  The base damage
	  for a weapon is d8.  Weapons that do d10 should be two handed. Weapons that do d6
	  should have other advantages, eg they can be thrown, are easy to learn, can be
	  concealed about ones person, etc.  We want to make the choice of weapons an
	  actual choice, no dominant strategy, so	there cannot be a best weapon.
	</p>

	<p>
	  We will also adopt the damage scaling system from 13th Age.  At certain levels,
	  we will increase the number of dice rolled for damage.
	</p>
	
	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/pc_dmg_bonus_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	  <caption>PC Damage Bonus by Level</caption>
	  <label>figure:pc_dmg_bonus_by_level</label>
	</figure>
	
	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/pc_avg_dmg_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	  <caption>PC Average Damge by Level</caption>
	  <label>figure:pc_avg_dmg_by_level</label>
	</figure>
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Monster Hit Points</subsectiontitle>

	<p>
          In order to balance play we have the following set of rules of thumb to 
          allow us to maintain game balance.  Characters that deal average damage
	  should be able to kill a Grunt of their level with two average hits.
	  Non-combat specialist characters should be able to kill
	  a monster in two or three average hits.
	</p>

	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/monster_hp_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	  <caption>Monster HP by Level</caption>
	  <label>figure:monster_hp_by_level</label>
	</figure>	
      </subsection>



    </section>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Monster Attacks</sectiontitle>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Monster Attack Difficulties</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Monster attack difficulties should be roughly equivalent to player characters
	  attack difficulties of the same level.  However players roll to hit and
	  we want a single target number of monster to hit difficulties so we will
	  take the monster to-hit difficulties from the average of the player to hit
	  rolls.  See Figure<ref>figure:monster_attack_difficulty_by_level</ref> for
	  monster attack difficulties.
	</p>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./docs/graphs/monster_attack_difficulty_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Monster Attack Difficulty by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:monster_attack_difficulty_by_level</label>
      </figure>      
	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Defense Checks</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Defense checks are made by players to avoid being hit by monsters.
	  The most common defense checks are Armour, Dodge, Block and Parry Checks.
	  Based on the following graph it seems that in order to have the generalist
	  characters able to enjoy combat the to-hit difference between generalists
	  and combat specialists should be no more than 2.  We can work back from the
	  desired 
	</p>

	
      </subsection>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./docs/graphs/pc_ac_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>PC Defense Difficulty by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:pc_ac_by_level</label>
      </figure>      


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Monster Damage</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Monster damage for a typical Grunt should be one par for a player character
	  of the same level (it makes the maths easy), see Figure
	  <ref>figure:pc_avg_dmg_by_level</ref>.
	</p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>PC Hit Points</subsectiontitle>
	
	<p>
	  In order to make combat sufficiently dangerous while still mitigating
	  the effect of a few lucky roles on monster attacks we decide that
	  a PC should be able to survive between four and six hits from a typical
	  monster of the same level.  To simplify matters we can require that a
	  typical monster does the same amount of damage as the character of the
	  same level.
	</p>

	<principle>
	  <principletitle>PCs should be able to take 4-6 hits.</principletitle>
	  <label>PCs should be able to take 4-6 hits.</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    Most PCs should have enough hit points to sustain four hits from an
	    average monster of their level.  Tanks should have enough hit points
	    to sustain six.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>

	<figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	  <img src="./docs/graphs/pc_hp_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	  <caption>PC HP by Level</caption>
	  <label>figure:pc_hp_by_level</label>
	</figure>
      </subsection>      
    </section>

    


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Abilities</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Creating New Abilities</subsectiontitle>       
	
	<p>
	  An average level skill should cost 5 skill points.
	</p>

	<p>
	  If skills require successes/attempts then they must have a Check defined.
	  The check should include a DDC.  If the check uses a dice pool the ability
	  should also have an overcharge value.  The overcharge should be a value
	  relative to the DC used .. e.g. DC + 5.
	</p>

	<principle>
	  <principletitle>No Dominant Strategy</principletitle>
	  <label>No Dominant Strategy</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    There should not be a dominant strategy for any particular character.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
	
	<principle>
	  <principletitle>Meaningful Difference</principletitle>
	  <label>Meaningful Difference</label>
	  <principlebody>
	    Character archetypes should be sufficiently different from one another.
	  </principlebody>
	</principle>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Ability Progression</subsectiontitle>       
	<p>
	  Abilities should have a type and a level so that we can make
	  make archetypes different and so we can make the players make
	  meaningfull choices when developing their characters.  
	</p>

	<corollary>
	  <corollarytitle>Skills should have a Type</corollarytitle>
	  <corollarybody>
	    Skills have to be typed in order to
	  </corollarybody>
	</corollary>

	<corollary>
	  <corollarytitle>Abilities should be Skills</corollarytitle>
	  <corollarybody>
	    It follows from <ref>Simplicity</ref>, that standard abilities
	    like Strength, Intelligence etc from d20 games should be Skills.
	  </corollarybody>
	</corollary>	
      </subsection>           
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Spells</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Spells and Game Balance</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Spells that impinge on the scope of other archetypes.
	  OK provided they can only do one domain
	</p>

	<p>
	  Spells that are so good no one uses anything else.
	  Fireball.
	</p>    
      </subsection>           
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>

