<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--

Checklist


Creating an Archetype
- Make sure that characters have enough melee abilities to be in the right range.
- Make sure that no abilities are greater than the maximum abilities


Creating a Monster
- Check the Defence DC is in the correct range for the Monster Level.
- All monster stats should be divisible by 3.


We can then calculate Monster Attack DCs based off those numbers?
(they'll be lower cause now we want the players to defend successfully 62% of the time).


HOW DO WE CALCULATE THE PLAYERS BASE AC?
WHAT ABOUT RAW DC FOR DEFENSIVE THINGS?

-->

<book>
<titlepage>
<vspace>2</vspace>
<title>Malleus Deum</title>  
<vspace>6</vspace>
<img src="resources/dragon_title/dragon.jpg" scale="0.6"/>
<vspace>6</vspace>
<subtitle>Igitur qui desiderat pacem, praeparet bellum.</subtitle>
<vspace>1</vspace>
<author>Blaize A. Rhodes</author>
<vspace>1</vspace>
<author>William F. Rhodes</author>
<vspace>1</vspace>
<version>{{ db.version }}</version>
</titlepage>


<tableofcontents/>  

<chapter>
  <chaptertitle>Design Philosophy and Game Balance</chaptertitle>


  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Motivation and Design</sectiontitle>

    <p>
      Malleus Deum is an attempt at designing a <emph>modern</emph> rule set.  It  
      tries to integrate advances in RPG rule design into an otherwise traditional RPG 
      rules system.  Specifically we try to include an Aspect-like mechanic from FATE, 
      near linear magic-users like 13th age, a more stream-lined or non-existent, initiative
      phase, a set of simple unified mechanics, from games like Dungeon World and Index Card RPG,
      morale, and adding boons and banes to dice results.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      This game has the following design goals:
    </p>

    <olist>
      <li>
        <p>
          The authors believe that the big name RPGs are showing their age.  Dungeons
          and Dragons is now nearly fifty years old.  While there are a large number of indie RPGs
          that have explored interesting new RPG design elements, Dungeons and Dragons and its peers
          have remained relatively static, their development ossified by negative feedback
          to changes from its large existing fan-base.  Dungeons and Dragon's own popularity
	  has slowed its evolution.  The big TTRPGs that dominate the market aren't changing.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
	  In addition the business model of the commercial RPGs
	  forces punctuated evolution of the game rules.  An entirely new version of the
	  rules comes out every couple of years.  We believe that gradual evolution, as
	  found in living rule books, would produce better results, faster.  
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          It is nice to have a change in pace and scenery.  We have tried to design a
          game where combat plays a major role, but other types of gameplay are possible.
          We aim to provide rules that will allow the GM to shine the light on other parts
	  of the game: negotiation, morale, fleeing and pursuit, stealth, investigation,
	  non-lethal combat, and personal development.
        </p>
      </li>
      
      <li>
        <p>
          We feel it is important for users of the game that the game license allow people
          to contribute to the game on their own terms and have, therefore, released the
          game under the Creative Commons Attribution License 3.0, which is available 
          online.  In a nutshell, you are free, to: 
          <list>
            <li>Share — to copy, distribute and transmit the work, to</li>
            <li>Remix — to adapt the work, and to</li>
            <li>Make commercial use of the work</li>
          </list>
          Under the following conditions:
          <list>
            <li>Attribution — You must attribute the work in the manner specified by 
            the author, but not in any way that suggests that they endorse you 
            or your use of the work.  
            </li>
          </list>
        </p>

	<p>
	  All creative commons licenses require attribution.  We suspect this may have
	  something to do with establishing the provenance of the license.  If we could
	  reasonably release the rules under a freer license, we would.
	</p>	    
      </li>      
      

      <li>
        <p>
          Medium-weight rules complexity means that the rules are a little more 
          complicated than, for example, FATE or Dungeon World, and a 
          little less complicated than say DnD4e or Pathfinder.   Combat should be easy
	  enough that GMs can throw challenging encounters together on the fly.  But the
	  rules for character progression need to be rich enough to capture and keep the
	  imagination of the players.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          Geared to a low magic setting.  At high level magic becomes difficult to GM
          with a myriad of unforeseen interactions and unintended consequences.  In the
          authors opinion, there are also problems with game balance in high fantasy
          settings.  As George Martin said: ``If you look at The Lord of the Rings, what
          strikes you, <ellipsis/> is that although the world is infused with
          this great sense of magic, there is very little onstage magic. So you have a
          sense of magic, but it's kept under very tight control.''.  We also refer the
          interested reader to Sandersons Rules of Magic.
        </p>
      </li>
      
      <li>
        <p>
          Malleus Deum is designed specifically for fantasy settings.  We feel that generic
	  role playing systems do not fit any milieu particularly well - they are the jacks
	  of all trades and masters of none.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
	  Realistic-ish.  We want to make some compromise between fantasy and realism, between
	  escapism and reality.   If the game is too fantasical then suspension of belief
	  becomes difficult and so to does immersion.  If the game is too realistic then
	  where is the fun?  Use historical names when you can.
        </p>
      </li>
      
      <li>
        <p>
	  Following from the previous point we aim for a medium grim-dark tone.  In the Matrix
	  movie Agent Smith says <emph>Did you know that the first Matrix was designed to be
	  a perfect human world? Where none suffered, where everyone would be happy. It was a
	  disaster. No one would accept the program.</emph>.  We want hope.  But at the same
	  time we want there to be darkness so that the player characters can be the light in
	  that darkness.  All societies are faulty; hedonistic or corrupt, or blood-thirsty.
	  Take society and turn it up to 11.	  
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
          Modular and Customizable: Our ultimate goal is that you should be able to include
	  the bits you want, exclude the bits you do not, customize whatever you like, add
	  whatever house rules you like, then build your own set of rule books and modules
	  and print them.  If the rules can be easily customizable to different genres then
	  that would be a good thing.
        </p>

        <p>
          Modularity also makes maintaining balance in an evolving game easier
          as some parts of the system can be tweaked without effecting other parts.
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
        <p>
	  The default milieu for the game draws elements from the standard fantasy sources:
	  Lord of the Rings, Conan the Barbarian, Dungeons and Dragons, Warhammer and
	  also some slightly unusual sources: Jim Butchers Dresden Files, Charles Stross's
	  Laundry Files and Lovecraft.  
        </p>
      </li>

      <li>
	<p>
	  Uses a player-facing dice system where the players roll most of the dice to allow
	  the GM more time to manage the game, and keep the players involved in the game.
	</p>
      </li>	  
    </olist>
    
    <p>
      We hope you enjoy the game.
    </p>

    <!--
        <figure position="!b">
        <img src="./resources/werewolf2.jpg" scale="0.7"/>
        </figure>
    -->
  </section>    
  

  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Design Principles</sectiontitle>

    <p>
      Good game design requires a balanced mechanical foundation.
      In this chapter we lay out the design principles we use to try to
      ensure compelling game play and good game balance.  In later sections we will
      apply those principles to individual game mechanics.
    </p>
    

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Simplicity</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	We do not believe that complex game mechanics are necessary for good gameplay.
	Keeping the number and complexity of the game mechanics of the game small
	makes for a faster, easier and more enjoyable game to play.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Simplicity</principletitle>
	<label>Simplicity</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Use only a small number of simple game mechanics.  
	</principlebody>
      </principle>

      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>Everything is an Ability Check</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  All checks made are ability checks.  Everything comes back to this one mechanic.
	  There are two types of check, std checks 2d12, and dice pool checks, three if you count
	  aspect checks which are a special case of std check.	    
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>

      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>Keep Monster Stats Simple</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  Monsters and PCs should have asymmetric complexity and rules.  The PCs need
	  sufficient complexity that their development can entertain players who are
	  interested in the mechanistic progression of their characters.  The monsters
	  need to be simple enough that a GM can throw together a simple encounter on
	  the fly, with no preparation.   The rules should reflect this.  Many rules
	  should only apply to PCs, and we should ignore the extra complexity for monsters.
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>      
    </subsection>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Operant Conditioning</subsectiontitle>	
      <p>
	Behavioural psychology, and more specifically, operant conditioning,
	suggests that the best training schedule is one with random positive
	reinforcement and not continuous feedback.  What that means in English
	is that random stepped increases in player character advancement is
	<emph>``more fun''</emph> than gradual continuous improvement or improvement
	at fixed times.  I think this can be applied to character progression and
	to dice results.  For dice results we think this means dice mechanics like
	those in FATE are contra-indicated.   There's a reason why rolling a 20
	feels good.  It's a rare enough event to be special.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Random Reinforcement</principletitle>
	<label>Random Reinforcement</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Character progression should increase in large and infrequent semi-random
	  discrete steps, and not gradually.  Choose a dice mechanic that has
	  exciting variations in results.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Dice Mechanics must have Variance</principletitle>
	<label>Dice Mechanices Variance</label>
	<principlebody>
	  The underlying dice mechanics must have enough variety of outcomes that
	  rolling for a check is an interesting activity.  There has to exist the possibility
	  of both great and terrible outcomes when making a check.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Game Theory</subsectiontitle>
      
      <p>
	It has been claimed that a well designed game presents players with problems
	that force them to make interesting decisions.   Game Theory has the concept
	of a dominant strategy.  If a problem has a dominant strategy then there is
	a solution to that problem that is clearly better than all the other solutions.
	If a game provides problems that have dominant strategies then they are not
	forcing players to make interesting decisions.  This just adds complexity
	and wastes time, so it should be avoided.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Avoid Dominant Strategies</principletitle>
	<label>Avoid Dominant Strategies</label>
	<principlebody>
	  We should strive to provide choices to players that do not have any clearly
	  better general-purpose solution when creating, developing and playing his
	  character.  Force the characters to make meaningfull choices.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Significant Difference</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	The idea behind this principle is that small differences in monster statistics and
	the like have very little effect to the strategies used by the players (Runehammer).
	Small changes give the illusion of difference in gameplay without actually providing any.
	Further all the extra detail only introduces extra complexity the GM has to remember.
	To address this constrain all monster stats to numbers divisible by three.  Make
	differences between monsters large.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Significant Differences</principletitle>
	<label>Remove minor complexity in monster design</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Try to constrain game mechanics to a small number of significant values.
	  Make monster stats divisible by three.  Make differences between monsters
	  obvious.  Make the Std Check difficulties all divisible by three.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>      
    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Succeed more than you Fail</subsectiontitle>

      <p>
	Let us define the playable range for standard check dice mechanics to be the range
	of values that have a probability from, say, 30<percent/> to 80<percent/>.  This
	represents the range that <emph>most</emph> but not all checks should be in to
	make for an interesting game.
      </p>

      <p>
	If players have more than an 80<percent/> chance of
	succeeding, then play becomes a little too easy and monotonous.  If players have
	less than a 30<percent/> chance of succeeding then play becomes frustrating.  This
	range is a little arbitrary but good enough for the purposes of this discussion.
      </p>
      
      <principle>
	<principletitle>Playable Range</principletitle>
	<label>Playable Range</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Most checks should have a probability of success that falls within a playable range
	  which is not too hard and not too easy.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
      
      <p>
	Furthermore, experience suggests that, on the whole, players prefer to succeed in
	their checks more than they fail, by which we mean that the typical
	probability of success should be in the range 50-70<percent/>.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Succeed more than you Fail</principletitle>
	<label>Succeed more than you Fail</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Generally checks should succeed more often than fail, aim for 60<percent/>.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Make Players Roll</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	We will steal an idea from DungeonWorld and Numenera and make players roll
	for defence when they are being attacked.  This will keep players busy and
	engaged and free up time for the GM.  On the downside this reduces the
	ability of the GM to fudge results.
      </p>

      <p>
	We have a system where the GM can Roll against a players DC, or vice versa, or they
	the GM can make contested rolls with the player.  So not all rolls need to be
	made by the players.	  
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Make Players Roll</principletitle>
	<label>Make Players Roll</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Make players roll most of the dice.  It keeps them happy and allows
	  the GM time to think.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Keep Hit Points Low</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Having high hit points compared with the amount of damage done slows combat.  Every
	combat then has a slow initial period where hit points are gradually reduced.	  
	Keeping hit points low at high levels makes combat more interesting (Professor
	DungeonMaster).
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Keep Hit Points Low at High Levels</principletitle>
	<label>Keep Hit Points Low</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Hit points at high levels should not be much greater than hit points
	  at low levels.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Players will make their characters do what the rules let them</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	I heard someone say something like this: "Warhammer FRPG is for
	people who think they're playing Dungeons and Dragons
	but are actually playing Call of Cthulhu."  The rules of the game
	determine what you do when playing the game.	We want to promote
	more role-playing, investigation, stealth and strategic thinking.  This implies
	that we need to have rules that cover non-combat areas of play.
      </p>      
    </subsection>      
    
    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Compose Encounters</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	The unit of composition for modules should be the encounter.  Traditionally
	encounter difficulty is determined by adding the difficulty (Challenge Rating)
	of all the monsters in an encounter.  This assumes that the the difficulty of
	an encounter is linear with new monsters.  This is clearly not the case.
	Instead the unit of adventure composition should be the encounter.  Ideally,
	GMs should tweak existing encounters of known, and tested, difficulty.  We
	are not suggesting that all encounters need be balanced, just that it is
	nice to avoid surprises.
      </p> 

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Make Encounters the Unit of Composition</principletitle>
	<label>Make Encounters the Unit of Composition</label>
	<principlebody>
	  It's less risky to modify existing, tested, encounters than compose
	  new ones from scratch.  Provide lists of tested encounters as starting
	  points.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>      
    

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Encounter AI</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Having monsters behave in intelligent ways makes combat interesting.
	Create AI (Runehammer, Matt Colville) or outline monster
	strategies, for encounters.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Archetypes Differentiation</subsectiontitle>	
      <p>
    	The character archetypes should feel different to play and
    	have strengths and weaknesses to provide variety and tactical
	options during game play.  For the purposes of discussion we can break
	the archetypes into four groups: Tanks, Damagers, Support (Controllers, Healers, etc)
	and Generalists.
      </p>

      <p>
	We expect that the Tanks should be more defensive than the other classes, the
	Damagers should do more damage.  Support should be sub-optimal in the
	damaging and defense roles but have additional strategic and/or buffing options
	available to them during combat.

	The Generalists are specialized non-combatants.  We introduce them because 
	we are trying to deemphasize combat.  At the same time we want the generalists to 
	have reasonable options within combat and be able to be reasonably
	effective, otherwise combat is boring for these archetypes.  To this end it is
	important that the generalists performance in combat is worse than that of
	the combat specialists, but not drastically so.  We need to define an envelope
	within which there is a difference between combat ability, but that difference
	is not so great that the generalists feel left out of combat.
      </p>
      
      <principle>
    	<principletitle></principletitle>
    	<label>Archetype Differentiation</label>
    	<principlebody>
	  Archetypes should be either specialists, strong in one area and weak in
	  others or generalists that are somewhat competent in combat.
    	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>


    <subsection>	
      <subsectiontitle>Monster Combat Classes</subsectiontitle>

      <p>
	We will give monsters a very similar combat classification to those used by Dnd 4e
	as it introduces a nice level of strategy to combat and communicates to the GM
	quickly the role the monster might take in combat.  Each monster
	has a level and a combat role: Minion, Grunt, Brute, Soldier, Artillery, Skirmisher,
	Lurker, or Elite.  In addition they can have hybrid roles, <ie/> Solo, Controller,
	or Leader that augments their role in combat.
      </p>

      <descriptions>
	<term>Minions</term>
	<description>very weak monsters.  One good hit should kill these guys.  Their
	attacks should typically hit as hard a those of Grunts.
	</description>

	<term>Grunts</term>
	<description>are the typical foot soldier type monster.
	</description>

	<term>Brutes</term>
	<description>are the monster equivalent of Damagers.  They have higher
	damage and hit points than grunts, and a lower armour DC.
	</description>

	<term>Elites</term>
	<description>
	  are like Brutes but get two or more attacks.  They are the sergeants or
	  the second in command types.
	</description>
	
	<term>Soldiers</term>
	<description>
	  are the monster equivalent of tanks. They have higher Armour than the Grunts,
	  and have similar HP and damage.  They might have abilities that make them sticky.
	</description>

	<term>Artillery</term>
	<description>
	  are ranged attackers with lower Armours and HPs than Grunts.
	</description>

	<term>Lurkers</term>
	<description>
	  typically have lower HP and Armour than Grunts but they have special abilities
	  that allow them to avoid detection.
	</description>
	
	<term>Skirmishers
	</term>
	<description>
	  have similar HP and Armour as Grunts.  They may do higher damage and they have
	  abilities that grant them extra mobility.
	</description>
      </descriptions>
      
      <p>
	The hybrid roles include the following:
      </p>

      <descriptions>
	<term>Controllers</term>
	<description>
	  have the same kinds of abilities as their PC analogs.  They are able to buff
	  their side, or debuff their opponents, allow their allies to move unhindered
	  across the battlefield, etc. 
	</description>	  
	
	<term>Leaders</term>
	<description>
	  have abilities that let them control their own troops or intimidate their
	  opponents.  They might be considered a special subtype of controller.
	</description>
	
	<term>Solos</term>
	<description>
	  Solos are monsters that can fight a party of adventurers on their own.  They
	  have similar Armour to the Grunts but a lot more HP, they do a lot more damage and
	  they should have multiple attacks and possibly special abilities.
	</description>	 	  
      </descriptions>	
    </subsection>
  </section>


  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Standard Check Game Mechanics</sectiontitle>
    
    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Standard Checks</subsectiontitle>
      
      <p>
	We're going to go with a 2D12 mechanic for standard game checks.  The range is
	similar to that of a d20 and we can use doubles to indicate boons and
	banes.
      </p>
      
      <p>	  
	It follows from Principle<ref>Succeed more than you Fail</ref> that for
	standard checks, such as to-hit rolls, there is a finite
	range of values within the 2d12 or 2-24 range that are reasonable and enjoyable
	to choose for difficulty values.
      </p>

      {% include "docs/tables/probabilities_2d12.xml" %}
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/std_check_2d12_vs_d20.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Check Probabilities 2d12 vs d20</caption>
	<label>figure:tohit2d12vsd20</label>
      </figure>

      <p>
	Based on the following graph, see Table<ref>table:probabilities_2d12</ref> and
	Figure<ref>figure:tohit2d12vsd20</ref>, we can see that the playable range, with
	a success rate of 30-80<percent/> for a 2d12 mechanic is about 11 to 18 with a
	difference of 7.  The playable range for 1d20 is 7 to 17 with a difference of 10.
	It follows that bonuses to Std Checks, must be smaller than equivalent bonuses in
	a d20 system, <eg/> a +2 bonus in a d20 system like DnD is roughly equivalent to
	a +3 bonus in a 2d12 system.  A +4 bonus in a d20 system is roughly equivalent to
	a +5 bonus in a 2d12 system.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Limit Std Check Bonuses to at most +4</principletitle>
	<label>Limit Std Check Bonuses to at Most +4</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Because the 2d12 checks have a smaller playable range than d20 systems
	  the maximum, unadjusted, difference for a standard check bonus between
	  any two archetypes at the same level (for which they should both have a
	  reasonable chance of success) should be less than or equal to +4.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>      

      <p>
	Note that the average result for 2d12 is also higher, 13 in our 2d12 system
	versus 10.5 in a d20 system.  The chance of rolling higher than any result is
	always greater for 2d12 then d20 rolls.  The chance to get 22 on 2d12 is about
	the same as getting 20 on a d20.
      </p>
    </subsection>


    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Advantage/Disadvantage on Std Checks</subsectiontitle>
      
      <p>
	If we look at Figure<ref>figure:tohit2d12vsd20</ref> we see that Advantage and
	Disadvantage are an option we can adopt.  Here Advantage is a 3d12 roll taking
	the top two dice.  Something to consider? 
      </p>
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/std_check_2d12_advantage_vs_disadvantage.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Advantage vs Disadvantage</caption>
	<label>figure:advantage_vs_disadvantage</label>
      </figure>      
    </subsection>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Balancing Player Characters</sectiontitle>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Approach</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Our approach to game balance is to choose some ranges for ability stats,
	for skill ranks and for weapon damage.  The rest of the game statistics,
	<eg/> hit points, armour DCs <etc/>, can all be derived from these initial
	decisions.  Our aim here is to make sure that the combat specialists are not
	too much better at combat than the non-combat specialists.
      </p>
    </subsection>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Primary Ability Bonuses</subsectiontitle>
      <p>	  
	We can start by limiting ability scores to a given range for each level.
	We do this so we can can model the effects of ability bonuses on Standard Checks.
      </p>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/primary_ability_range_by_pc_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Primary Ability Range by PC Level</caption>
	<label>figure:ability_range_by_pc_level</label>
      </figure>
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/primary_ability_bonus_by_pc_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Primary Ability Bonus by PC Level</caption>
	<label>figure:primary_ability_bonus_by_pc_level</label>
      </figure>	
    </subsection>

    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Ability Rank Bonuses</subsectiontitle>
      
      <p>	  
	We can also limit ability ranks to a given range for each level.
	Each skill provides a bonus equal to the rank of the skill.
      </p>
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/ability_bonus_by_pc_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Non-Primary Ability Bonus by PC Level</caption>
	<label>figure:skill_bonus_by_pc_level</label>
      </figure>	
    </subsection>
    
    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>To-Hit Checks</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	To-Hit rolls are a kind of Std Check.  We can calculate a range for
	the to hit bonuses for melee attacks, and from there we can calculate
	ranges for defensive checks.  The to-hit bonus is the sum of an ability
	bonus and the skill rank bonus.  Since the attacker usually gets to
	choose their weapon we can assume that they will choose a weapon that
	they are decent with.  We imagine that the character chooses a weapon
	for which their skill bonus is in the average to max range and the
	associated ability bonus is also in the average to max range. 
      </p>
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/to_hit_bonus_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>To-Hit Bonus by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:to_hit_bonus_by_level</label>
      </figure>

      
      <p>
	In order to make the maths more tractable we will introduce the simplifying
	constraint that the only thing that changes To-Hit and Defence Checks is the
	skill rank.
      </p>

      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>To-Hit and to Defence Check Bonuses</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  When designing to-hit and defensive checks, the bonuses for these checks should
	  be restricted to ability rank only.  By keeping the bonuses for to-hit and
	  defence checks dependent only on rank we make the maths and complexity of
	  balancing combat much simpler.  It also helps prevent min-maxing.  Hopefully this
	  will force the characters to concentrate more on strategy within the combat.
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>
      
      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>Ability Bonuses for other Checks</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  For other checks we will allow ability bonuses to apply to the check rolls.
	  This will give different characters and allow specialization and differentiation.
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>	


      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>Magic Weapons do not effect To-Hit rolls</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  It follows that Magic Weapons can only cause effects and their bonuses can
	  only effect damage.  
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>	
    </subsection>


    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Defence DCs by Level</subsectiontitle>	
      <p>
	Consider a PC attacking a second PC or Monster.  We are going to require that a more
	specialized attacker hits an average defender in roughly two out of three attempts
	(as characters should succeed more than they fail).  The non-specialized attackers
	should hit ever slightly less frequently.   We can then work out the appropriate
	defensive check values for players from the to-hit bonus table See
	Figure<ref>figure:pc_attack_difficulty_by_level</ref>.  Note that for any given
	attack only one roll is made, either an attack roll or a defence roll, not both.
      </p>

      <p>
	For example to find the average Defensive DC at level 10 we can find the mid-point of
	the to-hit bonus at that level in Figure <ref>figure:to_hit_bonus_by_level</ref>,
	which we see is 9.  Then we add 12, the value for 2d12 that gives us a 62<percent/>
	chance of hitting, see Table<ref>table:probabilities_2d12</ref>.  So we see that 
	an average defensive check DC for this level should be 21.
      </p>

      <p>
	When we refer to defensive check DCs we are primarily referring to Dodge, Parry,
	Block, and Armour Checks.  The first three of these require a reaction so, in
	theory, at least one of these should be better than the Armour.  Armour Checks
	should be at the harder end of the Defensive Check DC spectrum.
      </p>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/defence_difficulty_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>PC Probability to hit Defence DCs by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:pc_attack_difficulty_by_level</label>
      </figure>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/monster_attack_bonus_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Monster Attack DC by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:monster_attack_dc_by_level</label>
      </figure>

      <figure position="!htbp">
	<img src="./resources/attack_vs_defence/attack_vs_defence.png" scale="0.5"/>
	<caption>Attack Success Probability</caption>
	<label>figure:attack_vs_defence</label>
      </figure>


      <p>
	So by requiring monsters and PCs to have similar ACs by level we can ensure that
	PCs have the same chance of hitting monsters and other PCs and keep things
	relatively simple and consistent.  However, because we want PCs chance to-hit
	monsters to be about two times out of three, and we want the PCs chance to be
	able to-defend to also be about two in three <emph>the monster attack DC and the
	PC attack DC must be different at the same level!</emph>
      </p>


      <p>
	We can calculate the average Defence DC in
	Figure<ref>figure:pc_attack_difficulty_by_level</ref> by adding the average PC
	To-Hit bonus from Figure<ref>figure:to_hit_bonus_by_level</ref> to 12 (the target DC
	with a 60%% chance of succeeding without modifiers).
      </p>

      <p>
	We can also calculate the average Monster Attack DC in
	Figure<ref>figure:monster_attack_dc_by_level</ref> by adding the average PC
	Skill Level bonus from Figure<ref>figure:skill_bonus_by_level</ref> to
	12 (the target DC  with a 60% chance of succeeding without modifiers).
      </p>

      <playexample>
	<p>
	  At level 1 we can see from Figure<ref>figure:pc_attack_difficulty_by_level</ref>
	  that the average Defensive Check for a PC or Monster should be around 15 (somewhere
	  between 12 and 18). On the other hand, we can see that the average 1st level
	  Monster Attack DC should be about 13 from
	  Figure<ref>figure:monster_attack_dc_by_level</ref>.
	</p>
      </playexample>
      
      <playexample>
	<p>
	  At level 10 we can see from Figure<ref>figure:pc_attack_difficulty_by_level</ref>
	  that the average Defensive Check for a PC or Monster should be around 21 (somewhere
	  between 18 and 24). We can also see that the average 10th level
	  Monster Attack DC should be about 16 from
	  Figure<ref>figure:monster_attack_dc_by_level</ref>.
	</p>
      </playexample>		
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Weapon Damage</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	So that takes care of attack and defence rolls for both PCs and NPCs.  Now
	let us look at weapon damage and hit points.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	We can choose the amount of damage PCs deal fairly arbitrarily and scale other
	game mechanics accordingly (such as monster and PC hit points).  We will choose
	fixed damage for weapons and use boons and banes of the attack or defence
	rolls to modify the damage (halve or double the damage). We can start with an assumed
	base damage for a weapon of about 5 hit points.  Weapons that do 6 or 7 should be two
	handed. Weapons that do 4 should have other advantages, eg they can be thrown, are easy
	to learn, can be concealed about ones person, are improvised weapons etc.  We want to
	make the choice of weapons an actual choice so
	there should not be a <emph>best</emph> weapon. Weapon design should be handled
	so that there is no dominant strategy.  Different characters should want to use
	different weapons.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>PC Damage</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	We will adopt the damage scaling system from 13th Age.  At certain levels,
	we will dramatically increase the damage -- this helps to counter the
	linear fighters, quadratic wizards problem, it also provides some conditioning
	reinforcement as the change to damage is significant.  This increase will
	only apply to the weapons damage, not to any other bonuses applied to that damage.
      </p>
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/pc_dmg_multiplier_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>PC Damage Multiplier by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:pc_dmg_multiplier_by_level</label>
      </figure>

      <p>
	Finally we partition the modifiers to try to minimize complexity.  So
	to-hit and defence rolls will be modified by skill Level alone.  Damage can be
	modified by level (above), any magic weapon bonuses to
	damage (up to +3).
      </p>

      <!-- ************************** FIXME ABILITY BONUS ?? -->
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/pc_avg_dmg_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>PC Average Damage by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:pc_avg_dmg_by_level</label>
      </figure>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>Melee Ability between Characters should not be Too Large</principletitle>
	<label>Melee Ability between Characters should not be Too Large</label>
	<principlebody>
	  With a less combat-oriented, lower-powered magic system we need spell casters
	  to fight hand to hand from time to time.  This should not be too painful for
	  them.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
      
      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>Special Melee Attacks should do less Damage or be less Versatile
	than the standard Attack</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  If an attack has a special effect then that attack should
	  do less damage or the application of the skill must be limited to some special
	  context, otherwise the character has no decision to make.
	  Disarm or Push are examples of the first sort, while Brace Against Charge is an
	  example of the second.
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Monster Hit Points</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
        We have the following set of rules of thumb to allow us to maintain game balance.
	Characters that deal average damage should be able to kill a Grunt of their level
	with two average hits. Non-combat specialist characters should be able to kill
	a monster in two or three average hits, see Figure<ref>figure:monster_hp_by_level</ref>.
      </p>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/monster_hp_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>Monster HP by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:monster_hp_by_level</label>
      </figure>	
    </subsection>



    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Monster Damage</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Monster damage for a typical Grunt should be on par for a player character
	of the same level (it makes the maths easy), see Figure
	<ref>figure:figure:pc_avg_dmg_by_level</ref>.  We can work out the desired
	PC hit points from the monster damage.
      </p>
    </subsection>

    
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>PC Hit Points</subsectiontitle>
      
      <p>
	In order to make combat sufficiently dangerous while still mitigating
	the effect of a few lucky roles on monster attacks we decide that
	a PC should be able to survive between three and four hits from a typical
	monster of the same level.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>PCs should be able to take 3-5 hits.</principletitle>
	<label>PCs should be able to take 3-5 hits.</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Most PCs should have enough hit points to sustain three hits from an
	  average monster of their level.  Tanks should have enough hit points
	  to sustain up to five.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/pc_hp_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
	<caption>PC HP by Level</caption>
	<label>figure:pc_hp_by_level</label>
      </figure>
    </subsection>            
  </section>    


  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Dice Pool Game Mechanics</sectiontitle>

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Dice Pools</subsectiontitle>

      <p>
	Dice pool mechanics are used for a number of different things. Characters have
	three dice pools: Magic, Mettle, and Luck.  Dice pools are also used for magic items.
	We use dice pools where there is a resource that we want players to manage.  This
	forces the characters to make decisions about when to use these resources.
      </p>

      <p>
	Some dice pools, particularly magic, have an overcharge value which is the number of
	sixes rolled when making a dice pool check.   A spell overcharges if the number of
	sixes rolled is greater than the level of the spell being used (with some effects
	from armour and magical equipment, such as staves).  If spell overcharges
	then the spell succeeds but has unexpected side effects.
      </p>
      
      <p>
	Similarly, dice pool checks have an exhaust value.  Every die that rolls the exhaust
	value or lower is exhausted, <ie/> lost from the pool.  Exhausted dice may or may not
	be recovered depending on the pool. Here we take a quick look at dice pool behaviour.  In
	Figures<ref>figure:dicepools_a</ref> through<ref>figure:dicepools_b</ref> we
	provide a range of difficulties and overcharge values for dice pool checks.
	In Table<ref>figure:dicepools</ref> we provide a table of the cost in dice
	to make a dice pool check with a given number of dice rolled and a given
	exhaustion value.
      </p>

      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/n_d6s.png" scale="0.6"/>
	<caption>Number of 6s Rolled </caption>
	<label>figure:n_d6s</label>
      </figure>      
      
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/dice_pool_1_to_14.png" scale="0.18"/>
	<caption>Dice Pool Difficulty vs Number of Dice Rolled, A</caption>
	<label>figure:dicepools_a</label>
      </figure>
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/dice_pool_15_to_28.png" scale="0.18"/>
	<caption>Dice Pool Difficulty vs Number of Dice Rolled, B</caption>
	<label>figure:dicepools_b</label>
      </figure>
      
      {% include "docs/tables/dice_pool_cost.xml" %}
    </subsection>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Spell Casting</subsectiontitle>

      <subsubsection>
	<subsubsectiontitle>Dice Pool Size per Level</subsubsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  Here we'll take a look at the number of dice that player characters should
	  have in their dice pools at different levels.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Let us say that dedicated first level spell casters can cast a handful of
	  low level spells before replenishing their dice pools.  Recall that dedicated
	  spell casters still should have some hand to hand combat ability. Each dice
	  used in the spell has a 1/3 chance of being exhausted (on average, see the rules
	  section on magic for more information).  We can see that for a 2 dice spell
	  (e.g. DC 3 spells, see Table <ref>figure:dicepools_a</ref>)
	  we spend 2/3 of a dice every time we cast a spell.  And so to cast six 2 dice
	  spells the dice pool needs to contain 6 x 2/3 = 4 dice.
	</p>

	<p>	    
	  Now, suppose we wish a 12th level caster to be able to cast a similar number
	  of 6 dice spells (a 12th level caster would then be able to cast three times
	  as many DC 3 spells as a first level character).  The DC for 6 dice spells
	  are DC 14 and DC 15.  So the dice pool for a 12th level caster would be 12 dice.
	</p>

	<p>
	  We probably would not increase the dice pool for casters drastically above
	  level 12.  Instead their abilities will increase by increasing the number of
	  spells and spell promotions they get.  They will become more efficient and
	  more controlled casters, but not more powerful casters after level 12.
	</p>
	
      </subsubsection>

      <subsubsection>
	<subsubsectiontitle>Difficulty and Levels</subsubsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  If we look at the difficulty tables there are some things to note.
	  First each row of graphs shows one DC, starting with DC 2 and going up
	  to DC 19.  For comparison DC 2 spells should correspond to cantrip level
	  spells in DnD (note they're not free and they can fail, but they are cheap) and
	  DC 3 spells correspond to about 1st level spells in DnD.
	  The Difficulty (DC) is a measure of how expensive the spell is to cast.
	  The Overchage (OC) is basically how dangerous the spell is to cast,
	  a smaller overcharge is more dangerous to cast than a larger overcharge.
	  As the character gains levels in a spell the Overcharge value of the spell
	  increases meaning that the spell becomes less dangerous.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The second point of interest is that the left hand column has the suggested
	  initial overcharge for a dedicated spell caster.  Note that all casters cast
	  spells at level 1 or higher and therefore have at least a +1 increase in the
	  overcharge value.  The middle column has the suggested initial overcharge for
	  theurgic (clerical) spells.   Clerical spells are less dangerous to cast so that
	  some clerical casters can use armour without too much risk of overcharge or
	  shorting.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The different difficulties mean that there are different tiers of spell
	  corresponding with the expected cost in dice to cast.
	</p>
      </subsubsection>	
    </subsection>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Monster Morale Pools</subsectiontitle>

      <p>
	Here we investigate the effect of Morale DC on expected success for monsters
	with different dice pools.   We will make the basic morale check 5 and say that
	for an average combat we should be making around three morale checks.  Checks
	caused by magic may set their own DC.
      </p>
      
      <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
	<img src="./build/morale_dc_comparison.png" scale="0.18"/>
	<caption>Morale Dice Pool Difficulty vs Number of Dice Rolled, B</caption>
	<label>figure:morale_dicepools</label>
      </figure>      
    </subsection>
  </section>



  
  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Abilities</sectiontitle>

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Creating New Abilities</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	All skills should have an associated check.  You cannot gain proficiency
	in a skill without making checks.  Skills should have a default difficulty
	value (DDC) as a suggestion to the GM.
      </p>

      <principle>
	<principletitle>No Dominant Strategy</principletitle>
	<label>No Dominant Strategy</label>
	<principlebody>
	  There should not be a dominant strategy for any particular character.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
      
      <principle>
	<principletitle>Meaningful Difference</principletitle>
	<label>Meaningful Difference</label>
	<principlebody>
	  Character archetypes should be sufficiently different from one another.
	  In principle that means try not to have one archetypes abilities overlap
	  too much onto those of other archetypes.  This can be particularly difficult
	  for spell casters.
	</principlebody>
      </principle>
    </subsection>


    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Ability Progression</subsectiontitle>       
      <p>
	Abilities should have a type and a level so that we can 
	force archetypes to be a little different and so we can have the players make
	meaningfull choices when developing their characters.  
      </p>

      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>Skills should have a Type</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  Skills have to be typed in order to constrain character development
	  a little.
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>

      <corollary>
	<corollarytitle>Abilities should be Skills</corollarytitle>
	<corollarybody>
	  It follows from <ref>Simplicity</ref>, that standard abilities
	  like Strength, Intelligence etc from d20 games should also be Skills.
	</corollarybody>
      </corollary>	
    </subsection>           

    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Spells and Archetype Design</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	It is easy to design spells that break game balance.  There
	are two ways that this happens.  First are spells that impinge
	on the scope of other archetypes,  <eg/> spells that impinge
	on rogue-like class abilities, causing invisibility or silence.
	The second problem are spells that are so good players never
	cast anything else.  A good example of this is fireball in
	Dungeons and Dragons.  Our solution to both these problems
	is to make the spells expensive enough, in terms of the cost
	to the dice pool, or danger of overcharge, that the use of
	these spells does not become ubiquitous.
      </p>
    </subsection>
  </section>
</chapter>


\appendix 
\addcontentsline{toc}{chapter}{APPENDICES}

<chapter>
  <chaptertitle>Archetype Balance</chaptertitle>
  
  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Archetype Balance</sectiontitle>
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Checklist</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Here we present a check-list to make sure that new archetyoes are 
      </p>

      <list>
	<li>Determine the name, inspiration, and colour for the new archetype</li>
	<li>Determine the archetypes role, one of: Tank, Damager, Support,  and Generalists. </li>
	<li>Determine starting abilities</li>
	<li>Determine level promotions</li>
	<li>Check that the Archetypes HP at all levels conforms with
	Figure<ref>figure:appendix_pc_hp_by_level</ref></li>
	<li>Check that the Archetypes attack <emph>and</emph> defence abilities conforms with
	<ref>figure:appendix_ability_range_by_level</ref> at all levels</li>
	<li>Determine starting gear</li>
      </list>
    </subsection>

    <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
      <img src="./build/pc_hp_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
      <caption>PC HP by Level</caption>
      <label>figure:appendix_pc_hp_by_level</label>
    </figure>	

    <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
      <img src="./build/ability_range_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
      <caption>PC Ability Range by Level</caption>
      <label>figure:appendix_ability_range_by_level</label>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>



<chapter>
  <chaptertitle>Monster Design</chaptertitle>
  
  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Monster Balance</sectiontitle>
    <subsection>
      <subsectiontitle>Checklist</subsectiontitle>
      <p>
	Here we present a check-list to make sure that the power of a monster at a given level is
	roughly equivalent to the power of a player character at the same level.  We try to do this
	as an aid to designing encounters. We are not suggesting that level three player characters
	should only fight level three monsters.
      </p>

      <list>
	<li>Determine the name, inspiration, and colour for the new monster</li>
	<li>Determine the monsters role Minion, Grunt, Brute, Soldier, Artillery, Skirmisher,
	Lurker, Elite, Solo, Controller, or Leader</li>
	<li>Determine monster abilities</li>
	<li>Determine monster attacks</li>
	<li>Determine a desired ``level'' for the monster</li>
	<li>Check that the monsters HP at conforms with Figure<ref>figure:appendix_pc_hp_by_level</ref></li>
	<li>Check that the monsters attack and defence abilities conform with
	<ref>figure:appendix_ability_range_by_level</ref> for the monsters level</li>
      </list>
    </subsection>

    <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
      <img src="./build/pc_hp_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
      <caption>PC HP by Level</caption>
      <label>figure:appendix_pc_hp_by_level</label>
    </figure>	

    <figure position="!htbp" fullwidth="true">
      <img src="./build/ability_range_by_level.png" scale="0.45"/>
      <caption>PC Ability Range by Level</caption>
      <label>figure:appendix_ability_range_by_level</label>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <chaptertitle>Balancing other Game Elements</chaptertitle>

  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Encounter Balance</sectiontitle>

    <p>
      We doubt that encounters should be balanced.  It makes life dull.  But the GM
      should understand how challenging an encounter is likely to be for a party of
      a given level.  
    </p>

    <p>
      The way we propose to work out the level of an encounter is through trial and
      error.  We will define a few standard party groups to test an encounter against.
      I can't see any other way of doing this.  In any case, despite our best
      efforts, given randomness in the game, the encounter levels should be regarded
      as a suggestion at best.
    </p>
  </section>


  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Spell Balance</sectiontitle>

  </section>


  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Magic Item Balance</sectiontitle>

  </section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <chaptertitle>Colour</chaptertitle>

  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Basic points</sectiontitle>

    <p>
      FIXME: here or in the GMG?
    </p>
  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <chaptertitle>Leveling Up</chaptertitle>

  <section>
    <sectiontitle>New Abilities</sectiontitle>

    <p>
      The following table is used as a general guide for designing leveling up benefits for
      archetypes in an attempt to keep their powers approximately the same.  Note the advances
      and new abilities are generic.. the variability here should be constrained by limiting
      the advances by tag and by providing choices, e.g +Hammer1 means gain a first rank ability
      with the hammer tag, +Hammer1×2 means gain two first rank ability with the hammer tag,
      >Hammer2 means upgrade a first rank hammer ability to a second rank hammer ability provided
      the first rank has been mastered. >Hammer3 means upgrade a first or second rank hammer
      ability provided the prerequisite rank has been mastered.  When adding new skills there
      should be some plausible way the character acquired those skills.
    </p>

    <table>
      <tablecategory>FullWidth</tablecategory>
      <tablespec><fixed>0.17</fixed><fixed>0.17</fixed><fixed>0.17</fixed><fixed>0.17</fixed><fixed>0.17</fixed></tablespec>
      <tabletitle>Level 2 Advances</tabletitle>
      <tableheaderrow>
	<td>Everyone</td>
	<td>Fighter</td>
	<td>Spell Caster</td>
	<td>Loremaster</td>
	<td>Generalist</td>
      </tableheaderrow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>Martial ▲3</td>
      	<td>Martial +1</td>
      	<td>Spell +1</td>
      	<td>Lore ▲3</td>
      	<td>Lore ▲3</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>+Martial1</td>
      	<td>&gt;Martial3</td>
      	<td>&gt;Spell3</td>
      	<td>&gt;Lore3</td>
      	<td>+Lore×1</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>&gt;Lore3</td>
      	<td>Stamina+1</td>
      	<td>&gt;Lore3</td>
      	<td>+Language1</td>
      	<td>+Language1</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>+Lore1</td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td>&gt;Physical3</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>&gt;Language3</td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td>&gt;Primary2</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>&gt;Physical1</td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>Health+1</td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      </tablerow>
      
      <tablerow>
      	<td>+Arts1|+Crafts1</td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
      	<td>&gt;Primary1</td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      	<td></td>
      </tablerow>
    </table>
  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <chaptertitle>Economics</chaptertitle>

  <section>
    <sectiontitle>Historical Basis</sectiontitle>

    <p>
      <!-- FIXME; in history stuff is too cheap.. !!  we'll change from a cp->1penny to a cp-> 1farthing  -->
      We will base our prices off historical prices, around the 1400s, pegging the conversion from
      one farthing to one copper piece.  This gives us the following conversion from in-game currency
      to 14th century English currency.  Doing this provides two benefits, first the pricing should be
      reasonably internally consistent, and secondly it will communicate the disparate wealth distribution
      present at the times.  Both of these should contribute to the realism without any extra
      in game overhead.  When adding equipment feel free to approximate the cost to some close but nice
      and round value to make life easy.

      Here are some historical prices
      http://medieval.ucdavis.edu/120D/Money.html

      <!--
	  Money goes as follows:
	  1 pound (L) = 20 shillings (s)

1 crown = 5 shillings
1 shilling = 12 pence (d)
1 penny = 4 farthings
1 mark = 13s 4d  
      -->	
    </p>

    <table>
      <tablecategory>Standard</tablecategory>
      <tablespec><fixed>0.44</fixed><fixed>0.44</fixed></tablespec>
      <tabletitle>Currency Conversion Table</tabletitle>
      <tableheaderrow>
	<td>14th C English Currency</td>
	<td>In Game Currency</td>
      </tableheaderrow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>1 Farthing</td>
	<td>1 Copper Piece</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>1 Penny (d)</td>
	<td>4 Copper Piece</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>1 Shilling (s)</td>
	<td>48 Copper, Approx 5 Silver</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>1 Crown</td>
	<td>24 Silver Pieces</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>1 Pound (L)</td>
	<td>100 Silver Pieces, 10 Gold Pieces</td>
      </tablerow>

      <tablerow>
	<td>1 Mark</td>
	<td>640 Copper, 64 Silver</td>
      </tablerow>
    </table>
    </section>
  </chapter>  
</book>
