<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>Candlemass</chaptertitle>
    <section>        
      <sectiontitle>Overview</sectiontitle>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Dramatis Personae</subsectiontitle>        

	<descriptions>
	  <term>Johannn Schnee</term>
	  <description>
	    In his late sixties, bad tempered and a drunkard, Johann is a minor lord who has
	    been given the title of Chief Investigator of the town by his older brother, Bertolf
	    Schnee.  The job is largely a sinecure, but Johann is surprisingly good at it.
	    It is his job to look into strange and unexplained crimes and events within the town
	    and its surrounding lands.
	  </description>

	  <term>Yvan Schoder</term>
	  <description>
	    Member of the Cult of the Ghouls.  Has infiltrated Johann Schnee's residence
	    as a replacement butler.  Seeking to poison Johann and end his investigations into
	    the disappearances.
	  </description>
	  
	  <term>Rolf Koch</term>
	  <description>
	    One eyed former butler.  Has been kidnapped by the Cult of the Ghouls and is currently
	    hanging from a hook in the Ghouls lair, still alive.
	  </description>
	  
	  <term>Lucia Bianchi</term>
	  <description>
	    The ghoul.  Apparently a pale brunette girl in her late teens.  In reality a fiend that
	    devours the rotting flesh of humans.   Refers to herself as a little girl, refers to her marks
	    as kind sirs, refers to her victims as little piggies.
	  </description>

	  <term>Bertolf Schnee</term>
	  <description>
	    A minor lord in charge of the city watch, brother of Johann.
	  </description>

	  <term>Arnhild Gelfand</term>
	  <description>
	    High priestess of the Ghoul cult
	  </description>

	  <term>Timo Engelman</term>
	  <description>
	    Lowly follower of the Ghoul cult.
	  </description>
	</descriptions>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Overview</subsectiontitle>        

	<descriptions>
	  <term>Intro</term>
	  <description>
	    The scene is Laibstadt on Candlemass eve.  There have been a number of gruesome murders.
	  </description>

	  <term>Johann and Yvan</term>
	  <description>
	    Johann leads a team of investigators looking into the murders.  Yvan is a cult member that
	    has infiltrated Johann's household and is seeking to poison him.
	  </description>

	  <term>Ashburg</term>
	  <description>
	    Meet the guards (an out).  Meet various people to distract from the doxy.
	    Meet someone who points them in the right direction
	    Meet the doxy Lucia Bianchi, the doppelganger.  
	    Finds the church.  Lucia attacks, there's a scream.	    
	  </description>    

	  
	  <term>Doxy</term>
	  <description>
	    Lucia Bianchi is in town looking for a copy of Black Book by the Mad monk Desiderius Lenz,
	    which prophecies the end of the world.
	  </description>

	  <term>See the Church Symbol Hear the Scream</term>
	  <description>
	  </description>
	  
	  <term>The Cellar</term>
	  <description>
	  </description>
	  
	  <term>The Pantry</term>
	  <description>
	  </description>

	  <term>The Church</term>
	  <description>
	  </description>
	</descriptions>
      </subsection>


      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Intro</subsectiontitle>        

	<p>
	  Provides some background and exposition.
	  It is candlemass.. the last full moon of winter, the night most holy unto mithras.
	  A killer has been at work in the city 
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  <list>
	    <li>Rivalry between Johann and the City Guard</li>
	    <li>Map showing the incidents of missing people around cheapside.
	    Has a distinct pattern</li>
	    <li>Disappearances peak on full moons</li>
	  </list>
	</p>	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Johann and Yvan</subsectiontitle>
	<p>
	  <olist>
	    <li>Explain that they're to see Johann Schnee as a matter of utmost urgency.. do not delay.</li>
	    <li>
	      Porter to take them across the river.
	      Knock on the door.
	      Do you have an appointment?  Yvan wants to turn them away.  Untill Johann yells from above to let them in.
	      The tatoo on Yvan's arm.  Perception check
	      Do you have something for me? Letter of introduction.
	      Johann explains his butler is new.  His old butler has gone missing.
	      Johann is drinking
	      Yvan tries to take the bottle of wine away.. Johann objects. Yvann orders another bottle.
	      Johann explaims that murders happen every full moon.  Tonight is a full moon.
	      Johann drinks a lot .. he's clearly an alcoholic.
	      Johann explains about the location of the bodies.. young men, eaten.  Canibals
	      Johann mentions his position .. he's an informal arm of the city guard that his brother runs.  He looks int
	      Yvan brings in a bottle with a bunch of glasses.. the wine seems cheap and has a bitter taste.
	      
	      Johann explains that using modern scientific methods he has mapped the locations of the bodies somewhere here.. on his desk.
	      Yvan stands around in case he's needed further.
	      Johann explains that if they're quick they may catch the perpetrator in flagrante delicto.. so to speak.  We must stop any further murders and get to the bottom of this.
	      Johann apologises for the rush .. but his previous employees are no longer available.  If pressed he explains that they were found in an alley last full moon.  They're marked on the map.

	      At this point Johann will look pale.. start to slur his words.  Stand up and then abruptly fall over.
	      Any kind of check will reveal that Johann has been poisoned.
	      Players who drank the wine will feel ill themselves.
	      Yvan leaves and locks the door.
	      Lore check will suggest using a purgative.  Salt in the pantry.
	      Yvan. chase?
	      If they catch him they'll see 
	      They all vomite.. and Johann recovers.. tells them to go.
	    </li>
	  </olist>
	</p>


	{% set encounter=encounters.get('candlemass.butler') %}
	{% include "docs/encounter_template.xml" %}
	
      </subsection>

      <subsection>
	<subsectiontitle>Ashburg .. some random encounters</subsectiontitle>        

	<p>
	  The purpose of these random encounters is to distract from the meeting with the city guard
	  and from the meeting with Lucia.   In part to provide expositionary information and
	  in part to make the guards turning up seem less contrived should that be
	  required, and in part to make the denouement when Lucia attacks more exciting.
	</p>

	
	<p>
	  A list of incidental encounters.
	</p>
	
	<descriptions>
	  <term>Orphans</term><description> Noldil and Baltzer, begging for money for food.  Will wish the characters "Merry Candlemass, sirs"</description>
	  <term><emph>City guard</emph></term><description>Meet the guards.  Captain Gerold.. huge black beard.  "These look some likely lads.
	  What are you boys up to tonight then?"  They'' first make sure that they're not
	  up to no good.. "you stand out a bit from the crowd round ere".
	  Explain to them that the streets ain't safe.  Say "We'll be keeping an eye out for you".
	  If they mention Johann the Guards talk about finding the previous dudes.
	  The purpose of this meeting is to foreshadow the guards turning up later and
	  provide background and exposition.</description>
	  <term>Fortune teller</term><description>Old Lena .. will ask for a 1 gp (expensive) and and
	  take them by the hand... then will fall on the ground with her eyes white, throwing up for a bit..
	  then she'll get up and leave, screaming at them to keep away from her, she will keep the coin if they don't ask about it
	  otherwise she'll throw the coin at them.</description>
	  <term>Brothel Owner</term><description>Henriette, big boobed brunette with her decolatage on full
	  display, running a whore house, she's got some girls outside and some patrons talking to them,
	  drinking ale.  If she can't talk them into a turn with the girls she tries to get them to buy an
	  ale for 2sp each.</description>
	  <term>Drunkards</term><description>two drunks brawling Veit (vitus) and Arnulf, six blokes watching in a circle.. gambling on the outcome.  The fight is over some woman, Hanna</description>
	  <term>Busker</term><description>Pankratz, an old down and out minstrel, playing sad candlemass songs on his lute, he's got his hat out in front of him with a couple of coppers in it.</description>
	  <term>Two "drunks"</term><description>one "recognizes" one of the party members as
	  being an old friend Milosh (or Margaritte) approaches and hugs them.
	  Attempts to pick their purse.  Perception check 18.  </description>
	  <term>Prostitutes</term><description>One bearing the symbol of the ghoul cult.  Knows where the church
	  is</description>
	  <term>Gang of drunk rich hooligans</term><description>Looking for a fight.  Leader is Kirstanus (gaudy rich clothes, weak chin, but big).  He will say "What are you looking at!  What are you fucking looking at?"  Second in command is Gelfrid (has a van dyke beard).. he'll try and talk Kirstanus out of it.  Initiative is 10 damage d6.. they're drunk.  They have swords  .. attack at 13.   Kirstanus will fight until his friends run.. getting angrier and angrier each time he's hit.. HP 20/10.  If a fight starts the others will join in HP 10/10.. every time they're hit they'll make a will save 3d6 against a target of 4.  If one runs save again for the next one. etc.
	  Can be talked out of it</description>
	  <term><emph>Count Nicholas Mezmerat</emph></term><description>Foreign Ambassador, Round face, Fez. Cloak.  Out for a stroll.</description>
	  <term><emph>The Krap Wagon</emph></term><description>
	  Yosh and Stan Shmenge. The characters will come across Yosh and Shtan, and subsequently the church.
	  Yosh and Shtan Shmenge,  Father and son on the crapwagon.   Here to stop the characters
	  from entering the church for a little bit so that Lucia can attack the fop.	  
	</description>
	<term><emph>Lucia</emph></term><description>Dirty blonde, quite attractive and Young (17?) prostitute offers them a good time.  "Come on mister I ain't got no money and a girls gotta eat".  "Ain't it a cold night.. don'tcha want to come and warm me up a bit?"  <emph>If asked about the murders</emph> .. she'll say "yeah it ain't half scary".. "Why are you so interested?".  "Well I can show you somefing for a silver.".  "One of em bodies was found in this ere building." ..  Go to Entering the Abandoned Building. <emph>If not asked about the murders</emph>They can hear singing starting from the chapel.  Go to the Fop.
      </description>

      <term><emph>The Fop</emph></term><description>
      Helwig, rich fat young man stumbling down the lane in the opposite direction in a fine blue doublet. Will nod at the characters in passing.  Lucia's customer, and later, her dinner.
    </description>      
    
    <term><emph>The Chapel</emph></term><description>
    They get to the front of the chapel an old disused building.. unburned.  When there's a Scream..
    Goto the Scream.
  </description>      
  
  <term><emph>The Scream</emph></term><description>
  <p>
    A scream attracts the characters from Lucia's location.  She is no where to be seen.
    Right inside the doors of her burned out abandoned building are a straw bed on the ground and a candle.
    Find the girl.  Lucia is lying in the corner covered in blood her neck at a grotesque angle.
    There's a trail of blood going down the stairs.  If the players try and help her she will attack
    them with surprise (probably) and flee down the stairs.  If they leave her she will wait till they
    are gone and follow them .. she will close the door behind her, lock it, and say "Three little piggies
    how delightful.  And I am soo hungry".  Before blowing out the candle and attacking.
  </p>
</description>



<term><emph>Entering The Abandoned Building</emph></term><description>
<p>
  In reality a fiend that devours the rotting flesh of humans.   Refers to herself as a little girl,
  refers to her marks as kind sirs, refers to her victims as little piggies.  ``Fancy showing a
  girl a good time?'' and ``A girls got to eat don't you know''.
</p>

<p>
  Once the party enters Cellar B with the girl behind them she reveals who she is.
  Fight.  If some players run they can come back in the morning.  If they fall they
  awake in the abbatoir.
</p>   
</description>


<term><emph>The Reveal</emph></term><description>
<p>
  A scream attracts the characters
  Find the girl.  The girl screams that the man has run down there (to Cellar B).
</p>
</description>
</descriptions>


<p>
  See the church (eyes).
  Hear the scream.
</p>


<table>
  <tablecategory>Figure</tablecategory>
  <tablespec>
    <fixed>0.1</fixed>
    <fixed>0.8</fixed>
  </tablespec>
  <tabletitle>Rumours</tabletitle>

  <tableheaderrow>
    <td>Roll</td>
    <td>Rumour</td>
  </tableheaderrow>

  <tablerow>
    <td>1</td><td>He's a flesh eating fiend wot done it.  So's I've been told</td>
  </tablerow>
  <tablerow>
    <td>2</td><td>What was left of em was like somefing from a butchers barrel.</td>
  </tablerow>
  <tablerow>
    <td>3</td><td>Heard talk of them .. have some weird name Eayilat Aljue Allaamutanahi or something?</td>
  </tablerow>
  <tablerow>
    <td>8</td><td></td>
  </tablerow>
  <tablerow>
    <td>12</td><td>If shown the symbol.  Will know where the chapel is and give rough directions!  "There's that sign drawn up on the wall.. and they's always singing in there and whatnot"</td>
  </tablerow>
  <tablelabel>table:{{ doc_name }}-rumours</tablelabel>
</table>

</subsection>


<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>The Encounter with Lucia Bianchi</subsectiontitle>
  <p>
    This is where Lucia brings her victims.   The front door has a
    bolt and an open lock in it.
  </p>

  <p>
    Things Lucia knows:
    <list>
      <li>The ghouls are followers of the opener of ways... believing that it will bring down the humans</li>
      <li>The prophecy has to do with the "Opener of Ways"</li>
      <li>She has been tasked with finding a copy of the prophecy</li>
      <li>The prophecy comes from the Mad monk Desiderius Lenz</li>
      <li>She is seeking the Heilige-Lanze, Holy Lance</li>
      <li>She belives that Laibstadt is the land of wine and bread mentioned in the prophecy (the Aelfwin and Laibstadt .. Elf wine and Bread Town)</li>
    </list>
  </p>
</subsection>


<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>Cellar</subsectiontitle>
  <p>
    Find the girl.  The girl screams that the man has run down there (to Cellar B).
  </p>
  
  <p>
    Once the party enters Cellar B with the girl behind them she reveals who she is.
    Fight.  If some players run they can come back in the morning.  If they fall they
    awake in the abbatoir.
  </p>   
</subsection>


<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>The Pantry</subsectiontitle>        
  <p>
    Dead and dying hanging on hooks.
  </p>   
</subsection>

<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>Enter The Chapel</subsectiontitle>        
  <p>
    The room is full of suplicants chanting in a foreign language (Lagashi).
    When the characters enter the room a hushed silence will fall across the room.
    If the characters enter from the pantry the high priestess will refer to them as
    ``Enemies of the Holy One'' and ``Defilers'' and will urge the followers to attack.
    If the characters enter from the street after speaking with Yosh Shmenge the Priestess
    will order them out.
  </p>

  <p>
    The supplicants attack with their hands or candle sticks or pews.  There are thirty of them.
    Just call it an endless supply.  Because of the crowdedness the damage they deal will be reduced.
    Only three supplicants can attack any player.  This can be reduced to 2 if they
    back up to a wall, barricade themselves behind something or 1 if they back into a corner.  The attack
    goes on until 12 are killed at which point they break, or after things start looking bad for the characters
    at which point the guards turn up (say 5 rounds).  The supplicants have defence 10, attack 12 and do d3 damage.
  </p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>Treasure</subsectiontitle>	
  <p>
    In a small wooden box hidden amongst the rubble are the following items:
    <list>
      <li>A short note documenting the demon El'Azabat</li>
      <li>Two scrolls: Lesser Portal I, and Summon I</li>
      <li>The prophecy fragments 1 and 2.</li>
      <li>Small book written in Lagashi.</li>
      <li>21 gold soverigns, 15 silver nobles and 3 copper groats in a small leather pouch.</li>
    </list>	  
  </p>
</subsection>

<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>Chapel</subsectiontitle>
  <p>
    Realization that they're all ghouls.  Outs: Guards or the Sun?
  </p>  
</subsection>

<subsection>
  <subsectiontitle>Aftermath</subsectiontitle>
  <p>
    If Yvan Schroder is captured he will be reticent to talk.  But if he knows the gig is up
    he knows the following.
    <list>
      <li>They've been looking at stopping Johann since last month when his previous investigators
      ran into Lucia</li>
      <li>Rolf Koch was taken so that Yvan could infiltrate the Schnee household</li>
      <li>Yvan was tasked with giving Johann poison</li>
      <li>He was building up the nerve to do it when the characters turned up and he decided he better do it now.</li>
      <li>He got the poison from Lucia.</li>
      <li>He is a member of the Eayilat Aljue Allaamutanahi (The family of endless hunger, sometimes known as the Culte des Goules).</li>
      <li>He has been promised eternal life in return for his services</li>
    </list>
  </p>  
</subsection>

{% set encounter=encounters.get('candlemass.ghoul') %}
{% include "docs/encounter_template.xml" %}

<handout id="letter_of_introduction" scale="0.8"/>
<handout id="johann_schnee" scale="2.0"/>
<handout id="suburb" scale="0.15"/>
<handout id="symbol" scale="1.20"/>
<handout id="prophecy1" scale="0.15"/>
<handout id="prophecy2" scale="0.15"/>
<handout id="el_azabat" scale="0.15"/>
</section>
</chapter>
</book>
