<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>

{% from "docs/macro_npcs.xml" import build_npcs with context %}
  
  <chapter>
    <chaptertitle>The Dwarven Mines under Laibstadt</chaptertitle>


    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Setup</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	The dwarves keep a subset of the old mines functional and free from
	vermin for smuggling goods into the city.  They don't want to clear
	out the rest of the mines because they act as a deterent to people.
	There is an entrance to the tunnels in the basement of the Murengers Arms.
      </p>

      <p>
	After a while in the tunnels Grundewald will lead them up to a tee intersection,
	one arm of which is walled off.  Grundewald will knock a hole in the wall to
	allow the characters to climb through.  But he will stay by the hole to stop
	any intrusions into the safe tunnels.   Grundewald offers to come in if he hears
	any trouble (this is the out).
      </p>	
    </section>
    

    <section>
      <sectiontitle>Spiders in the Sewers</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	They find an old rats skull the size of a football.
      </p>

      <p>
	Characters in the mines under the city make a perception or dungeoneering
	check.. difficulty 15.  If successful they notice strands of a web like substance
	running along the ground.  If they touch it they feel it give a quick jerk.. like
	a fishing line.  Next round the spiders charge in.  If the characters didn't succeed
	then they are surprised.  Grundewald hands the characters an old dwarven map with the
	relevant path lined out.
      </p>

      <p>
	Out: The ratmen turn up.  
      </p>	

      {{ build_npcs("dwarven_mines.spider") }}
	
    </section>



    <section>
      <sectiontitle>The Ratmen Cometh</sectiontitle>

      <p>
	Hearing the commotion a local gang of ratmen slavers come running in and try and
	capture the party.  If captured they will be taken via tunnels down to the docks
	and sold to the 
      </p>


      <p>
	Out: Grundewald turns up.
      </p>	
      
      {{ build_npcs("dwarven_mines.ratmen") }}
	
    </section>
    
  </chapter>  
</book>
